<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest defence of my book entituled, Quakerism expos'd as also of my broad sheet : with a scheme of the Quakers yearly synod, and other books presented anno 1699 to the Parliament : and G. Whitehead's inside turn'd outward, by reprinting his ancient book Ishmael, &amp;c. intirely, shewing thereby the Quakers ancient testimony of contempt of the Holy Scriptures and blasphemy against the blessed Trinity ... / by Francis Bugg.</title>
            <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12399593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12399593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 271:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest defence of my book entituled, Quakerism expos'd as also of my broad sheet : with a scheme of the Quakers yearly synod, and other books presented anno 1699 to the Parliament : and G. Whitehead's inside turn'd outward, by reprinting his ancient book Ishmael, &amp;c. intirely, shewing thereby the Quakers ancient testimony of contempt of the Holy Scriptures and blasphemy against the blessed Trinity ... / by Francis Bugg.</title>
                  <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
                  <author>Atkinson, Christopher. Ishmael and his mother cast out into the wilderness.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>3 pts.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Janeway, Jun., for the author, and sold by J. Robinson [and 3 others],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Ishmael and his mother cast out into the wilderness" has special t.p. and imprint: London : Printed for G. Calvert, 1655.</note>
                  <note>The second part contains: A cutting switch for the wounded snake.</note>
                  <note>Caption title to pt. 3: A reply to a book entituled, A defense of An apology for the Quakers, in answer to a book entituled, Quakerism expos'd.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements ([4] p.) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724? --  Quakerism expos'd to publick censure.</term>
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</term>
               <term>Field, John, 1652-1723. --  Defence of An apology for the people called Quakers.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Modeſt Defence Of my Book, Entituled, <hi>Quakeriſm Expos'd:</hi> AS ALSO, Of my Broad Sheet; with a Scheme of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Yearly Synod; and other Books, preſented <hi>Anno</hi> 1699. to the PARLIAMENT. AND G. <hi>Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Inſide Turn'd Outward,</hi> by Reprinting his Ancient Book <hi>Iſhmael, &amp;c.</hi> intirely; ſhewing thereby the <hi>Quakers</hi> Ancient Teſtimony of Contempt of the Holy Scriptures, and Blaſphemy againſt the Bleſſed Trinity; and they tell us they are not chang'd. By <hi>FRANCIS B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GG.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>There ſhall be falſe Teachers amongſt you, who ſhall bring in Damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, <bibl>
                        <hi>2 Pet. ii. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Janeway,</hi> Jun. for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; and ſold by <hi>J. Robinſon,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard; <hi>H. Rhodes,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Bride-Lane, Fleetſtreet; Ch. Broome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet;</hi> and <hi>J. Marſhall</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1700.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:2"/>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Humbly Dedicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas the <hi>Quakers,</hi> for many Years, have preſented their Books and Papers to the <hi>Parliament</hi> under many fair Shews, whilſt the Tendency of their Doctrine is to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Chriſtianity; and I being ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereof, think it my Duty to God and my Country, both as a Chriſtian, and Free-born <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> to diſcover the ſame; and therefore to obviate ſome Objections, I do moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg Leave to Apologize for my ſelf in this Affair, ſince by many Books of the <hi>Quakers</hi> I have been repreſented as an indigent Perſon, a Mercenary Agent, one that is prompt on by other, a <hi>Judas, &amp;c.</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:61238:3"/> thereupon I am greatly deſirous to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your Honours, that I am no ſuch manner of Perſon: And as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration thereof, I have ſomewhat to offer in my own Defence, which is briefly this.</p>
                  <p>I came of a good Yeoman Family, and have lived in good Repute all my Days, having had a competent Eſtate of near a Hundred Pound a Year, beſides Stock; and that whilſt I was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> I was of good Repute and Eſteem amongſt them; I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their Teachers with no little Charge, I put Cloaths on the Backs of ſome, and Money in the Purſes of others: I was Regiſter to their Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Quarterly Meeting about Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or Eighteen Years together, to which I rode Fifteen or Sixteen Miles every Month, and all this freely, as themſelves know, if they would ſpeak: I was Priſoner for the Cauſe of <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm</hi> Three Years and Four Months, and for Meetings I ſuffered by Fines and Diſtreſſes more than One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pound; and when we built a
<pb facs="tcp:61238:3"/> Meeting-Houſe, (for before Meeting were at my Houſe) I gave 20 <hi>l.</hi> towards it; and to that Day all freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Retribution; all which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, might abate the edge of their Defamations, and lead them to keep to the Matter in Controverſie: And ſince (upon a ſight of their Errors) I left them, I have been Uſeful, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Mercenary; I have born all Town-Offices, as Overſeer, Conſtable, and Church-warden; I have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an Aſſeſſor, and ſometimes Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of His Majeſty's Taxes, ſerv'd on Juries of Life and Death, as well as <hi>Niſi Prius;</hi> in all which places I have diſcharged my Truſt free from any Accuſation.</p>
                  <p>And ſince I have more narrowly looked into their Principles, and found them to be Pernicious to both Church and State, I have firſt uſed all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Means to Reclaim them: But when they perſiſted therein, and would juſtifie, excuſe, and defend all things, whether agreeable to the Scriptures of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:61238:4"/> or in Contradiction to them, I have thought it my Duty to diſcover their Pernicious Ways, and therein I have proceeded upon a Principle of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and can with good Conſcience ſay, that from firſt to laſt, no Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyman in the Kingdom ever asked or deſired me to write one Book, Page or Line, againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> nor have any one Man (Clergy or Laity) ſeen this Book till printed; tho' I do grant, that by my Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Writing for more than Twenty Years together, and by the Charge of Printing, together with other Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes incident to Tradeſmen, I have been reduced; and I am not aſhamed to acknowledge, that the Gentry, the Juſtices of Peace, the Clergy, and ſome Proteſtant Diſſenters, have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended their Bounty towards my Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; and which, the <hi>Quakers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do to their own People: And if this be Cauſe ſufficient to render me a <hi>Judas,</hi> or Mercenary, they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mercenary <hi>Judas</hi>'s among themſelves.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:4"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have read in the Book of <hi>Eſther,</hi> That when <hi>Haman</hi> deſigned the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, then in Captivity, how Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Defence thereof, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Eſther</hi> 3.6, 14, 16. <hi>I will go in to the King, which is not according to Law, and if I Periſh, I Periſh.</hi> And it is in the remaining Story of <hi>Eſther</hi> in the Greek and Latin Copies, <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Mordecai</hi> appeals to God thus, <hi>Thou knoweſt, O Lord, that it was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Malice, nor Preſumption, nor of any Deſire of Glory that I did this,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>I</hi> came to underſtand the Pride and Cruelty of <hi>George Fox</hi> and his Accomplices, which was equal to that of <hi>Haman,</hi> who in <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>'s time (as by their Books appear) were for Slaying and Baniſhing all the Clergy in the Kingdom, and how averſe they ever were againſt Liberty of Conſcience (as elſewhere <hi>I</hi> have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) as alſo what Enemies they were to the Holy Scriptures and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Saviour, namely, Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, damning the
<pb facs="tcp:61238:5"/> Ever-bleſſed Trinity to the Pit of Hell, and divers other Blaſphemies, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny here to relate; <hi>I</hi> was ſtirred in my Spirit to appear in Defence of our Holy Religion, which their Doctrine tends to overthrow; ſaying with Queen <hi>Eſther, If I Periſh, I Periſh;</hi> and can appeal to God, as <hi>Mordecai</hi> did, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thou knoweſt, O Lord, that it was neither of Malice, nor of Preſumption, nor any Deſire of Glory, that I did this,</hi> &amp;c. And who knows but for ſuch a time as this, <hi>I</hi> was deliver'd from them by the good Hand of Providence.</p>
                  <p>And (Right Honourable) that which is chiefly defir'd by me, is, (and that in Concurrence with many Thouſands of good Chriſtians) that the <hi>Quakers</hi> may be examined, whether what <hi>I</hi> object againſt them be ſo or no; and if found true upon them, that they may then be obliged to Retract and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn what is Erroneous, as well as Dangerous; and this is no Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Nor do <hi>I</hi> know of any who deſire any Alteration of the Act of Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:5"/>
                  <p>I have likewiſe read the Story of <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> wherein the Fraud of the Prieſts of <hi>Bell</hi> is ſet forth; who pretended (as our Quakers do) that they ſerved in the Temple freely; and that their God Eat up all the Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet before him: But upon Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it was found far otherwiſe. Even ſo I make this offer, and that on the Terms of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Propoſition, to make it appear (notwithſtanding the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Loud Clamours againſt the Clergy, for their Tythes, and other Dues, ſet apart by Law for their Maintainance, whilſt they Serve at the Altar) that Ten of the Quakers Teachers have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more Gifts than Fifty of our Epiſcopal Divines, Rectors of Pariſhes, in the Counties of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk;</hi> only by ſtrewing a few Aſhes on the Floor, or ſomething Equivolent. But as the Prieſts of <hi>Bell,</hi> were too powerful for <hi>Daniel,</hi> without Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Government; even ſo are the Quakers for me. I can only diſcover the Riddle, and propoſe a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to try them by; but cannot bring
<pb facs="tcp:61238:6"/> the Matter about to bring proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without Aſſiſtance from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But as <hi>Daniel</hi> by his three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Medicine, <hi>Pitch, Fat, Hair,</hi> boil'd together, by God's Bleſſing, burſt in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Babylonians Dragon,</hi> their other Idol-God; even ſo have I been Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment l, with the help of Pen, and Ink, Paper, well preſt together, and applied Warm, with God's Bleſſing, Burſt in ſunder the Quakers great Idol, their Darkneſs within, (which they call Light). So that their Infallibility is flown one way, and their Sinleſs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection another; their Spiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning they pretend to [ſo as to know who are Saints, and who are Devils, and who are Apoſtates, without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Word] this way, and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that way. And if to bring this to paſs, I have ſometimes taken the freedom of the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. who ſpeaking to the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> in a Holy Deriſion of them and their Idol Gods; ſaid, <hi>Ver.</hi> 27. <hi>And it came to paſs at Noon, that</hi> Elijah <hi>mocked them and ſaid, Cry aloud, for he is a
<pb facs="tcp:61238:6"/> God, either he is Talking, or he is Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, or he is in a Journey, or peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he Sleepeth, and muſt be Awaked,</hi> &amp;c. if then I have taken ſuch freedom, with the falſe Quaker Prophets, and their Dumb Idols, which can neither See, Hear nor Underſtand, much leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern who are Saints, who are Devils, or who are Apoſtates, without ſpeak-ever a Word; or if I have with the Woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. by way of Metaphor, brought about a Form of Speech, with deſign to get the Quakers examined, whether what have been Objected againſt them, be true or not; I hope it is Pardonable, ſince in all Ages in the World, the ſame Cauſe leads to the ſame thing. For I do Believe, (and not without Ground) That as there never was a People, ſince <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, pretended to ſuch High Prophetical Attainments; ſo likewiſe there never was a Sect of Falſer Prophets ſince the time of <hi>Elijah,</hi> nor that ever held ſuch Blaſphemous
<pb facs="tcp:61238:7"/> Principles as their Books ſet forth: And they ſay they are the ſame ſtill, their Principles the ſame, and not changed.</p>
                  <p>Be not deceived (I beſeech you) by the Quakers, who appear like the Phariſees, Fair and Beautiful even like Painted Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers; Remember the Subtilty of the <hi>Gibionites, Joſh.</hi> 9. how they by their Diſſimulation deceived good <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and all the Princes of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> The Quakers tell you they own the Scriptures to be given by Divine Inſpiration; but mean not one word of it, like other Chriſtians; for ſo they own their own Books.</p>
                  <p>They tell you they own a Scripture Trinity, but mean not a word of it: This is a Matter (Right Honourable) of great weight; and your Honours will find it as difficult a thing, to gain the true meaning of the Quakers, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Authority of the Holy Scriptures, and their Belief of a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Trinity, as <hi>Constantius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour found it, in the Examination of <hi>Arius</hi> the Heretick, to get his true meaning, touching the Faith of one
<pb facs="tcp:61238:7"/> Subſtance: For the Quakers (as did <hi>Arius</hi>) mean as they have written; but how? Namely, in their own Books; I mean of that ſort they read in their Meetings, and keep cloſe among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; one of which I have herein Reprinted. In theſe ſorts of Books they deny the Scriptures to be the Written Word of God; For it is (ſay they) a Rotten Foundation, Duſt, Death, and Serpents Meat. In like manner they diſſemble the Doctrine of the Trinity, when they pretend to own it; whilſt in their Books they Damn it to the Pit and Lake. All this, and much more, I offer to make appear, who am, with all Submiſſion,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Honours most Humble and most Obedient Servant, Fran. Bugg.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:61238:8"/>
                  <head>A PREFACE, By Way of PARABLE.</head>
                  <p>THere was an Iſland, very Populous, and well Scituated, the Air good, and the People generally of a ſound Conſtitution, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by wholeſom Laws, and profeſſed the moſt Reformed Religion of any Nation round about them: But ſo it fell out, that in the North Part of this Iſland, <hi>Anno</hi> 1650. there aroſe a great Sea-Monſter<note n="†" place="margin">Viz. Geo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>x, <hi>alias</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Magus.</note>, of a Luciferian Pride, who pretended, that he, and all that received, embraced, and had the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that moved him, were equal to God: That he was the Eternal Judge of the World, and knew who were Saints, who were Devils, and who were Apoſtates, without ſpeaking ever a Word; and he having betrothed himſelf to a young Harlot<note n="*" place="margin">i. e. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>nters.</hi>
                     </note>, ſhe conceived, and brought forth her Young; to whom ſhe drew out her Breaſts, and gave them Suck, and they multiplied exceedingly, and many of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came fiery flying Serpents<note n="†" place="margin">Such of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ts, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>re him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>h Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>es.</note>, and ſpread themſelves like Locuſts, all over the Iſland; ſome entering the Churches, where they ſtung both Men, Women, and Children; others entered into the Market-places, Barns, Orchards, and private Chambers; like the Frogs in <hi>Egypt,</hi> poyſoning the Air, and infecting much People.</p>
                  <p>Upon this, the Phyſicians, both Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts were extreamly allarmed, not well knowing what to do, or what Courſe to take, to ſtop
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:61238:8"/> the Gangrene of this Peſtilential Diſeaſe, and to heal the People, who were bitten by theſe Serpents; but as wiſe Phyſicians, they took their Chriſtian Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>i. e.</hi> The Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</note>, and turn'd over to this Chapter, and that Verſe, and made excellent Receipts, which were ſold at reaſonable Rates at every Bookſellers Shop, and prepared many Antidotes againſt the Venom of this dangerous Infection: But theſe wounded Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being intoxicated by the Venom of theſe Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, they refuſed all theſe Chriſtian Offers; but the Phyſicians (as in Duty bound) reſolved to apply their Medicines to the grieved part of this wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bewitched People, who like the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of old, ſaid, That this Monſter was the Power of God<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Journal,</hi> 3d Index, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Letter M.</note>; that he wrought Miracles; that he had Power to bind and looſe whom he pleaſed; and cried out, who is able to make War with the Beaſt: But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Power and Prevalency of this Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, they applied (as aforeſaid) their Medicines ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warm, and withal giving them ſome Phyſick to purge away the Dregs of their Diſtemper; which as ſoon as they had done, and before they could finiſh their Prayers for a Bleſſing upon their Endeavours, theſe diſeaſed People grew into a raging Fit, and raved at the Phyſicians like mad Men, ſaying, <hi>We are perfect, and free from Sin, ſound, and have no need of any Phyſician;</hi> for as they did not think themſelves obliged to ask Forgiveneſs of Sin to God, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their Errors to Man, ſo they reſolved to uſe none of their Medicines, and therefore bad them be gone, calling them by theſe Names following, <hi>viz. The Idle Gormondizing Prieſts of</hi> England,<note place="margin">The Guide miſtaken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>W. Penn,</hi> p. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>no ſort of People have been ſo univerſally through Ages the very Bane of Soul and Body of the Univerſe, as that Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tribe, for whom the Theatre of God's moſt dreadful Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is reſerved to act their Eternal Tragedy upon.</hi> With this the Gentlemen were amazed, and looking one upon another, ſaid, <hi>Good Lord, may it pleaſe thee to forgive our Enemies, Perſecuters and Slanderers, and to turn their Hearts: Grant us, O Lord, to love our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and by the Example of thy Martyr</hi> Stephen, <hi>to pray for our Perſecuters,</hi> &amp;c. And when this Prayer was
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:61238:9"/> ended, they judging it their Duty to do Good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Evil, they again tried another Expedient, thinking their Diſtemper lay in their Brain, and being ſomewhat Lunatick, was the Cauſe of thoſe violent and abuſive Words. Well, they gave them ſome Pills, advis'd them to be ſtill, and take ſome Reſt; but before this Phyſick could work, they fell into another Convulſion Fit, and raved as much as ever; (yea, all of them, except ſome few, who were not wilfully ignorant, who, by the Bleſſing of God upon their Endeavours, came to their Sences, and remain ſo to this Day, as Monuments of God's Mercy, praiſing his Great and Glorious Name, and returning their Thanks to the Phyſicians who labour in the Word and Doctrine,) calling the Phyſician, (methinks I hear them ſtill) <hi>Baal</hi>'s <hi>Priests, Conjurers, Thieves, Robbers, Blind Guides, Devils, Serpents, the Sir-Symons of the Age, a Viperous and Serpentine Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Witches, Bloodhounds, Merchants of</hi> Babylon, <hi>Dogs, Sodomites</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Is this from a Chriſtian Spirit? See their <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. p. 7, 8.</note>, <hi>we</hi> (ſaid this Intoxicated People in their mad Zeal) <hi>have nothing for them but Woes and Plagues, who have made drunk the Nations, and laid them to ſleep on downy Beds of Sin-pleaſing Principles, whilſt they have cut their Purſes, and pickt their Pockets;</hi> Tophet<hi>'s prepared for them, to act their Eternal Tragedy upon; whoſe Scenes will be renewed, Direful, Anguiſhing Woes, of an Eternal Irreconcileable Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. And in excuſe for theſe dreadful Thunderbolts, <hi>W. Penn</hi> thus ſaith, <hi>That had theſe Expreſſions been Ten Thouſand times more ſignificant, earneſt, and ſharp, againſt that curſed bitter Stock of Hirelings, they had been but enough, and I would then ſay not enough; but that the Reverence I bear to the Holy Spirit</hi> (i. e. in the Quakers) <hi>would oblige me to acquieſce in whatever he ſhould utter, through any Servant or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">W. Penn<hi>'s</hi> Ser. Apol. <hi>p. 156.</hi>
                     </note>, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>At this the Gentlemen ſtood amazed, thinking with themſelves that all the Furies of Hell could not help them with more dreadful Curſes, much leſs Ten Thouſand times more ſharp, and ſo they left them, as fit only for <hi>Bedlam.</hi> Upon this there was ſome diſſenting Phyſicians<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Faldo,</hi> and others.</note> in this Iſland, who alſo had good Skill of this Malady, with which this People
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:61238:9"/> were infected by the Venom of the Scorpions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-noted, and in great Pity to them, they ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diligently into their Chriſtian Diſpenſatory, and found therein divers Receipts, and of the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Medicines, they apply'd both Corroſive and Lenitive, but nothing took place, (except only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a few, who were not willingly Ignorant, and of an obſtinate Temper) but the Treatment they had for them was much of the ſame Nature of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-noted; for they called them, <hi>An ill-bred Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Crew</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Is this from a Chriſtian Spirit?</note>, <hi>the Bane of Religion, and Peſt of the World, the old Incendiaries to Miſchief, and beſt to be ſpared of Mankind, againſt whom the boiling Vengeance of an irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated God is ready to be poured out</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Quake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm a new Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 165.</note>, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Whoever read this Book, and my former Books, will find this Parable unfolded.</p>
                  <p>Thus, Reader, you ſee here is nothing but Plagues, and Woes, Hell and Damnation, both for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, and Nonconformiſts, for all their Love, Care and Pains; are theſe mad People then to be dealt with, as a Man would deal with any other well-diſpoſed People? I think not: If then you find me in ſome Caſes to deal roughly with them, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel not; it is for their Good, ſince <hi>the way</hi> (as one of themſelves ſay) <hi>to recover the Deceived is to diſcover the * Deceivers:</hi> And <hi>this Witneſs it true,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid touching the <hi>Cretians, Tit.</hi> 1.12, 13. ſo may I (and that for the ſame Reaſon) ſay of the <hi>Quakers, viz.</hi> one of themſelves, even a Prophet of their own ſaid, <hi>The Cretians were always Liars, evil Beaſts, Slow-Bellies,</hi> this witneſs is true, (<hi>ſaid St.</hi> Paul) <hi>wherefore Rebuke them ſharply,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that is, (as in the Dutch Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations)</hi> Severely <hi>or</hi> Cuttingly, <hi>a Similitude taken from Phyſicians, who cut off the dead Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. Then not ſoftly, with ſmooth Words, ſewing Pillows under their Armholes, as ſome did in former Ages; and for which they were ſharply reproved; no, no, they muſt be launched, and the Wound laid open<note n="†" place="margin">A Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Wound muſt have a Deſperate Cure.</note>, and ſearched to the bottom, and then we may hope of a Cure; and this Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, has ſeemed proper to me ever ſince I have
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:61238:10"/> practiced; for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> like the <hi>Cretians</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Diſſemblers with God and Man; they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Liars; they were always evil Beaſts, and Slow-Bellies; and for the Truth of this, St. <hi>Paul</hi> (touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Cretians</hi>) produceth a Prophet, or a Poet of their own, who gave that Witneſs; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they were always Liars, yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of this Evidence of their own Poet, <hi>this Witneſs it true;</hi> therefore rebuke them ſharply, Severely or Cutting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in order to cut off the dead Fleſh; and in like manner I ſhall produce a Propheteſs of their own, who alſo is a Poet, and a Writer, and Defender of their Way, and in their Unity, which ſtands princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in Lying, and Diſſembling; and when ſhe does write in the Defence of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſhe is as great a Liar as the reſt; yet in this Caſe her <hi>Witneſs is true,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Cretian</hi> Poet.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore I ſhall briefly recite ſome Paſſages out of ſome Letters, writ by her to my ſelf, and to Mr. <hi>Criſp;</hi> as alſo out of a printed broad Sheet, all wrote by <hi>Anne Docwra,</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> one in their Unity, as above-noted, which Letters we have ſtill by us, as well as her printed Paper, and which are more at large recited in my Book, <hi>The Chriſtian Ministry of the Church of</hi> England <hi>vindicated, &amp;c.</hi> p. 2. and my <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim's Progreſs,</hi> &amp;c. 2d Ed. p. 54, 121, 129. and her Witneſs in this Caſe is true, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p n="1">I. I have <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> given witneſs againſt <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi>'s Book, <hi>Judgment fixed,</hi> &amp;c. we have <hi>(continues ſhe)</hi> Knights of the Poſt amongſt us, <hi>&amp;c. This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. That the honeſt <hi>Quakers</hi> (for ſome ſuch there are amongſt them) have ſuſpected <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> (by his Craft and Subtilty, in defending or excuſing what he muſt know to be erroneous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them) to be a Jeſuit, at leaſt like them. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. That their Second-Day Meeting put Names to their Certificates, and Paſſages into their Books, without either Conſent or Knowledge of the Parties or Authors. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="xix" facs="tcp:61238:10"/>
                     <p n="4">IV. That the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſeparate Meetings for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (with Doors ſhut) are dangerous to the Peace of the Nation. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">V. That the Magiſtrates look upon Common Bankers (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> Fund) to be as bad as Arms and Ammunition, and not (ſaid ſhe) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon, for Money anſwers all things. If Friends (ſaid ſhe) would put away this <hi>Dagon,</hi> and take Money only for their preſent Neceſſity, things would ſoon be better. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">VI. That the <hi>Quakers</hi> Diſtinct Men's Meetings (touching their Government within the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and oppoſite to it) ſerve to little Purpoſe, but to ſhelter great Bellies, and to protect the Proud and Vicious. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">VII. That their Teachers, <hi>G. Whitehead, Sam. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</hi> are the moſt confident Liars, and wicked Forgers, that ever ſhe met with. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">VIII. That their Second-Day Meeting both ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, and altered the Sence of her Letters, to make Lies ſeem true; of which Forgery ſhe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> to be Guilty; for (continue ſhe) <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> is not Sophiſter great enough. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">IX. I had (ſaid ſhe) a ſharp Conference with <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> for his Clamouring againſt <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> and <hi>John Ainſloe,</hi> in his abuſeful Narrative, herein (ſaid ſhe) he <hi>(Sam. Cater)</hi> have uſed my Name in Print, to juſtifie him in his Conſcious Pamphlet with <hi>Francis Bugg:</hi> I (ſaid ſhe) laid it before him ſmartly; he is very bold, (continues ſhe) and the moſt confident Liar that ever I met with. <hi>This Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">X. That <hi>G. W.</hi> forged a Certificate in's <hi>Judgment Fixed. This witneſs is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thus much from a Propheteſs of their own, one in their Unity, and that have wrote many Books in Defence of Quakeriſm; one in 1699. by which Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we may know that the Quakers, like the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> were always Liars, evil Beaſts, ſlow Bellies; but not only ſo, but Liars, Forgers; and, to ſpeak Comparatively, Knights of the Poſt, Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its,
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:61238:11"/> and dangerous to the Government; Slanderers to their honeſt Friends, whilſt they protected the proud Blaſphemers, and Vicious Hypocrites; and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, the Evidence which a Prophet of the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> ſaid was true, (who ſaid, and ſaid truly, that the <hi>Cretians</hi> were always Liars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) why? Becauſe he knew the Truth thereof; and as to the Evidence which this Prophereſs, <hi>Anne Docwra,</hi> has given of the Quakers, I ſay it is true; why? Becauſe I know it to be ſo in the Caſes now recited: But further, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, I ſhall recite an Abſtract of a Letter ſent me, dated <hi>January</hi> the 19th, 1699. from <hi>Robert Sandiland,</hi> who formerly was one of their Teachers: But upon Conviction of his Errors, and the groſs Hypocriſies of the Quakers, he has left them, (as many others have done) and Retracted not only his Errors, which he (with my ſelf, <hi>G. Keith, Tho. Criſp,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) held, but alſo his uncharitable Language to me, and others, tho' much, of what his Books con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, was, as <hi>Anne Docwra</hi> ſays, foiſted in as his, yet none of his; and I am apt to think the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>G. W.</hi> was the Forger in his Book; for which horrible Practice he (I fear) has a large Account to give. Now follows <hi>R. S.</hi>'s Letter ſomewhat abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Loving Friend, <hi>Francis Bugg.</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>AS concerning my Book, printed <hi>1683.</hi> Entituled, <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. whatſoever it herein, inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, (or any other of my Books) with the ſound Chriſtian Faith and Doctrine, I do now wholly Diſown, and Retract; together with all Harſh and Uncharitable Expreſſions on thee, or any others, named in my Book; and particularly theſe Verſes, <hi>p. 97. viz.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Team, Rogers, Pennyman, Bullock</hi> and <hi>Bugg,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Dark Devil, driven dungy God's deſperately Lugg;</l>
                           <l>That are ty'd to the Tail of their ſeparate Schiſm,</l>
                           <l>Papiſts, Libertiniſm, Heatheniſm, Judaiſm, Atheiſm.</l>
                        </q>
                        <p>I do ſay, and affirm, that tho' theſe Verſes were put into my Book as mine, yet I aſſure thee that they were none of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, I did not compoſe oneword of them; but they were made by another Hand, and put into my Book, together with the
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:61238:11"/> whole Ninth Chapter, which was likewiſe done by another Hand, and put alſo into my ſaid Book, (as mine) whilſt I was in the Country; and after I had left it with the Second-Day-Meeting for the Preſs, and they did with it what they pleas'd, as thou knoweſt they uſe to Read and Correct all Books brought before them; and <hi>G. W.</hi> I ſuppoſe may remember who it was that writ that whole Ninth Chapter<note n="*" place="margin">Yea, and I gueſs that it was <hi>G. W.</hi> himſelf.</note>, from <hi>p. 91, to 100.</hi>— Bleſſed be God, that their groſs Errors in the Fundamentals of the Chriſtian Religion, are now ſufficiently Detected; and there is nothing remains now for them to do, but either openly and freely to Retract (and Condemn) them, or elſe to be expoſed, and liable to all the ill Effects and Conſequences, which must unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attend their obſtinate perſiſting in their Errors.—</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Robert Sandilands.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>But to ſhew the horrid Cheats, wicked Forgeries, and deep Hypocriſies of this their Second-Day Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will exceed the bounds of a Preface; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for a compleat Syſtem of this their black Art in their dark Divinity, I refer my Reader to my <hi>Pilg. Prog. &amp;c.</hi> 2d Edit. <hi>p.</hi> 149, to <hi>p.</hi> 170.</p>
                  <p>And that I may not leave a Stone unturned that may diſcover the pious Frauds of this Painted Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, I ſhall recite a brief Abſtract of <hi>W. Mucklow</hi>'s Book, Entituled, <hi>The Spirit of the Hat, &amp;c.</hi> he being a Man of Note amongſt them, and may be called in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Sence a Prophet of their own, and whoſe Evidence in this Caſe is true; yea, I know it to be ſo: For the Quakers were always Liars, evil Beaſts, Slow-Bellies, whilſt yet they pretend to Infallibility, and alſo that their Books are given forth from the Immediate Eternal Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Foxonian</hi> Unity is to yeild Obedience to the Body, tho' no Conviction inwardly of the Truth of the thing commanded; ſaying, who is able to make War with us? Theſe are the high ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Words of proud <hi>Babel. This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That <hi>G. Fox, &amp;c.</hi> was of an Antichriſtian Spirit. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That their Miniſters (in their Meetings for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, conjoin'd together to ſubvert our Laws and Liberty. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:61238:12"/>
                  <p n="4">4. That <hi>G. Fox</hi> was lifted up with Luciferian Pride, ſaying, he had Power to bind and looſe whom he pleaſe. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That <hi>Sol. Eccles,</hi> one of their Prophets and Teachers, ador'd <hi>G. Fox</hi> with Divine Attributes. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. That their People bowed down on their Knees to <hi>G. Fox</hi> for Abſolution; [in particular, <hi>John Fretwell, Chriſtopher Gilborn, James Naylor,</hi> which was Idolatry.] <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s Luciferian Pride was manifeſt, when he gave out a Paper, That his Marriage with <hi>Margaret Fell,</hi> Widow, was a Figure of the Marriage between Chriſt and his Church, and that his ſaid Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was above the State of <hi>Adam</hi> in his Innocency, in the State of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> that never fell. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. That great Pains had been taken by <hi>Sam. Newton</hi> and <hi>John Bolton,</hi> to bring to light the unheard-of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and Beaſtly Wantonneſs, and filthy Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Teachers. <hi>This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. That <hi>John Bolton</hi> had a Confeſſion in writing of one or two of the Females concerned in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Actions; ſhewing alſo that many eminent ones in their Miniſtry reſorted to them daily, giving them theſe Appellations, Innocent Laſſes, and Daughters of <hi>Sion. This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. That the Quakers repreſent ſuch as diſcover theſe their Abominations, <hi>Envious, Malicious, Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, Bad, Dirty</hi> and <hi>Factious</hi> Spirits, who are gone from Truth, <hi>&amp;c. This Witneſs is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> rebuke them Sharply, Severely, or Cuttingly; who, notwithſtanding their high Pretences to Meekneſs, Charity, Self-Denial, Temperance, and other Graces of the Spirit, yet are found to be Liars, evil Beaſts, Slow Bellies, great Forgers, groſs Hypocrites, and proud Blaſphemers. Read over the 20 Inſtances, and <hi>R. Saudiland</hi>'s Letter of Retractation; together with what elſe you find in this and my other Books; for to them I refer for further Demonſtrations of the Deceitfulneſs of theſe vain Pretenders, and high Boaſters.</p>
                  <pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:61238:12"/>
                  <p>If they tell you this Book of <hi>W. Mucklow</hi>'s is anſwer'd, and again complain that I take no Notice thereof, as <hi>Joſ. Wyeth</hi> does of the Author of <hi>The Snake in the Graſs, &amp;c.</hi> in his <hi>Anguis Flagillatus,</hi> &amp;c. to them I thus reply, that their pretended Anſwers are in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity no Anſwers, otherwiſe than mock Anſwers to abuſe the World, and to blind their Proſelytes, and to paint over the Poyſon of their foul Opinions; and this is eaſie to diſcern by any that will be at the Pains to read what is wrote on both ſides; and by conſidering their way and manner of anſwering Books. See <hi>G. W.</hi>'s <hi>Truth and Innocency vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. in theſe three Inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. Their Way of Tranſpoſing.</item>
                     <item>II. Their Way of Adding Words.</item>
                     <item>III. Their leaving Out Words.</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of their Tranſpoſing Words.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>First,</hi> As to Tranſpoſing, <hi>G. Fox</hi> having taught in his <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> &amp;c. ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 213. <hi>You cannot know Scripture, but by the ſame Degree of the Spirit that the Prophets and Apoſtles had,</hi> &amp;c. this was objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Quakers; as Pride in them that ſo thought, and falſe Doctrine in them that ſo teach; ſee <hi>A Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 8. to which <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> reply'd in his <hi>Truth and Innocency,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>Theſe Words,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhould be</hi> Tranſpoſed, <hi>it ſhould run thus: Thou canſt not know Scripture but by a Degree of the ſame Spirit the Prophets and Apoſtles had.</hi> Now by thus Tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Words we may read <hi>Acts</hi> 12.2. <hi>That</hi> James <hi>ſlew</hi> Herod <hi>with the Sword;</hi> and ſo overthrow the Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Holy Scriptures, whether Doctrinal or Hiſtorical. Now whether <hi>G. W.</hi>'s Method of Tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Words of their Prophets, was not to cover and palliate their Errors, let the wiſe in Heart judge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Their Way of Adding Words.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Again, their Way of Adding Words. <hi>A Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 26. the Clergy having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the Quakers, a Blaſphemous Poſition out of <hi>Burrough</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 273. <hi>viz. The Sufferings</hi> (ſays Burroughs) <hi>of the People of God</hi> (i. e. Quakers) <hi>in this
<pb n="xxiv" facs="tcp:61238:13"/> Age, is a</hi> Greater <hi>Suffering, and</hi> more Unjuſt, <hi>than in the Days of Chriſt, his Apoſtles,</hi> (and Martyrs) <hi>or any time ſince — What was done to Christ or his Apoſtles was</hi> Chiefly <hi>done by a</hi> Law, <hi>and in</hi> Great Part <hi>by the</hi> Due Execution <hi>of a</hi> Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To this <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> the Quakers Soderer, replies; ſee his <hi>Truth and Innocency,</hi> &amp;c. p. 44. not once mentioning the Page in the ſaid <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> on purpoſe (no doubt) to lead his Reader from the Sight and Scent of their Blaſphemy; and that which confirms me therein is, that he dropt the latter part of the Quotation, <hi>viz. What was done to Chriſt or his Apoſtles, was</hi> Chiefly <hi>done by a</hi> Law, <hi>and in</hi> Great part <hi>by the</hi> Due Execution <hi>of a</hi> Law. No, this was ſo apparently Blaſphemous, that as hardy as he <hi>(G. W.)</hi> is, he was aſhamed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite it; but whilſt he blames others for ſplitting Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, Mangling and Curtailing, he is a profound Practitioner of it; but in <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>ibid.</hi> being loth to let it paſs wholly unſpoken to, he there ſays, <hi>Inſtead of</hi> [Due Execution] <hi>it ſhould rather have been ſaid</hi> [by a Regular and Judicial Procedure.] But how far this mends the Matter, let all true Chriſtians judge; <hi>viz.</hi> whether the Proceedings of the Jews againſt our Saviour when they Scourg'd him, Spit upon him, Platted a Crown of Thorns upon his Head, Smote him with the Palms of their Hands; when <hi>Herod</hi> and his Men of War ſet him at nought, and mocked him, and the like Indignities, which were not then, nor now, done to the greateſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors: I ſay, was this <hi>A Regular and Judicial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure</hi> againſt our Bleſſed Saviour, as <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> (he being expert in Law Terms) grants it to be in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Brother <hi>Burroughs?</hi> Again, <hi>George,</hi> one Queſtion more; were the Jews Nailing his Innocent Hands and Feet (in whoſe Mouth never was Guile, nor ſinful Thought in his Breaſt) to the Croſs, and the Soldiers piercing his Side with a Spear, ſo that his Precious Blood<note n="†" place="margin">Which the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſay is no better than the Blood of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Saint.</note> ſtreamed out at five Places; I ſay, was this <hi>A Regular or Judicial Procedure?</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in your next. Again, <hi>A Regular and Judicial Procedure,</hi> ſuppoſeth a Tranſgreſſion of ſome Law: And <hi>Burrough</hi> ſays expreſly, that he not only ſuffered
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:61238:13"/> by a Law, but in a great part by the <hi>Due Execution</hi> of a Law, as above. Again, and <hi>George,</hi> ſince you grant that all the Indignities, and cruel Sufferings our Saviour underwent, (for the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) was by <hi>A Regular or Judicial Procedure,</hi> which preſuppoſeth a Law, and that Law tranſgreſſed; therefore be plain for once, and tell us what Law it was by which he was (for the Tranſgreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) <hi>Regularly and Judicially proceeded againſt;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently therefore Condemned, Crucified, and Slain by the Jews; if you cannot do this, then condemn both your <hi>Truth and Innocency</hi> as Blaſphemy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of their Leaving out Words.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly, G. Fox</hi> having taught in his Book, <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> &amp;c. p. 8. ſaying, HE <hi>that</hi> Hath <hi>the ſame Spirit that raiſed Jeſus Chriſt, is</hi> Equal <hi>with God;</hi> this being urged againſt the Quakers as Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy by the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergy in their Book aforeſaid, i. e. <hi>A Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. p. 6. the Quakers Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> ſays, in his <hi>Truth and Innocency,</hi> &amp;c. p. 9. <hi>We</hi> (ſays <hi>George) deny the Words as there printed,</hi> (tho' not until near 40 Years after printed) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Words [He that hath] <hi>ſhould be left out.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, <hi>George,</hi> may not the <hi>London</hi> Jews by the ſame Art, and with as much <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their deceaſed Brethren the Jews in their Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt Jeſus Chriſt, in the Days of his Fleſh, who ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 8.48. <hi>Say we not well, that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a Devil?</hi> But then, by <hi>G. W.</hi>'s Rule of Arguing, the <hi>London</hi> Jews may now ſay, The Words <hi>[and haſt a Devil]</hi> ſhould be left out; they only meant, that he was the compaſſionate Samaritan, mentioned <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33. Would this do, <hi>George?</hi> No ſure, theirs was plain Blaſphemy, and <hi>Fox</hi>'s is as plain Blaſphemy, who ſaid he was equal to God, as aforeſaid.</p>
                     <p>Thus, Reader, have I ſhewed thee the Quakers way of anſwering Books, <hi>viz. Firſt,</hi> by <hi>Tranſpoſing</hi> Words; by which, if allowed, I have proved, that <hi>James</hi> ſlew <hi>Herod. Secondly,</hi> That by their <hi>Adding</hi> Words they likewiſe may excuſe any Blaſphemy,
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:61238:14"/> as <hi>Whitehead</hi> here doth his Brother <hi>Burroughs,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>firſt,</hi> that the Quakers Sufferings are greater than Chriſt's, and all his Apoſtles and Martyrs under the Heathen Emperors, and Bloody Maſſacres to this Day. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Sufferings of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are more unjuſt than all the forementioned. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That what was done to Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs, was chiefly done by a Law. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and in great part by the <hi>Due Execution</hi> of a Law: But ſays <hi>Whitehead, It ſhould rather have been ſaid [by a Regular or Judicial Procedure;]</hi> and truly this is ſo far from clearing <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> and his Brethren (for they are all of one Mind, being lead into theſe Blaſphemies by their Darkneſs within, which they call Light) that it rather confirms what he Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſaid, than otherwiſe: And no great Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for the Quakers in Print deny that Perſon which ſuffered upon the Croſs to be properly the Son of God<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Apol. <hi>p. 146.</hi> For a Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Penn</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, read <hi>John 14.28.</hi> yea, the whole Chapter.</note>; and the Jews being of the ſame Faith, they ſaid, as in <hi>John</hi> 19.7. <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to die, becauſe he made himſelf the Son of God.</hi> Thus do both Jews and Quakers agree in their Fundamentals, the Quakers deny him properly to be the Son of God, and the Jews put him to Death, becauſe he ſaid he was the Son of God; and both Jews and Quakers herein reſiſt the Teſtimony of God himſelf, the Glorious Angels, the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Army of Martyrs; yea, all Chriſtian Churches to this Day; and becauſe my ſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers urge that they may be examined touching theſe their Blaſphemous Books, therefore they cry out <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, Perſecution, Fr. Bugg</hi> would raiſe the <hi>Monſter</hi> of <hi>Perſecution;</hi> with this they make a Noiſe, and raiſe a Duſt, but fear no ſuch thing; they only fear being examined about their Blaſphemous Books, and obliged by Authority to Retract them, and then down goes their beloved Darling <hi>Infallibility.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And what remains now, but to follow the Pious Example of good King<note n="†" place="margin">Againſt the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib,</hi> King of <hi>Syria.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.14. <hi>And</hi> Hezekiah <hi>received the Letter of the Hand of the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and read it; and</hi> Hezekiah <hi>went into the Houſe of the Lord, and ſpread it before the Lord, and prayed,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:61238:14"/> And therefore that God may give a Bleſſing to our Labour; and for his Name Sake Rebuke this Spirit of Blaſphemy, which have entered this our Iſland; and if it be his Holy Will, to convince the Gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his Sacred Word and Ordinances. For as St. <hi>Paul</hi> Teacheth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10. <hi>He that ploweth plows in Hope, and he that threſheth in Hope, ſhall be partaker of his Hope,</hi> eſpecially if he faint not; and though to Plow, and Threſh, and Beat Clods, be hard Work; yet 'tis a neceſſary Work to Prepare the Field. For the Seedſmen who are ordained thereunto, not that the Plowmen or the Sowers have wherewith to Glory; for <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apolo</hi> water, but it is God alone that giveth the increaſe: And to him (not unto us) belong the Glory. And tho' it has been my work to Plow and Break the Clods, which is hard Labour; and to threſh the Mountains, that the Fields may be prepared, and fitted for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's uſe; yet I can ſay, according to the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God has given me, I have not deſired to break the Bruiſed Reed, nor to quench the Smoaking Flax, by being harſh to the weak, or ſevere to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but have cut down the Lofty Weeds, and hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down the Tall Ceders, who ſtood in oppoſition to the way and work of God, which he is bringing to paſs in the Earth: And therefore I ſhall conclude in the Prayers of our Church, beſeeching God of his Great Mercy to give his Bleſſing to my weak En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours; And ſay,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We Sinners do beſeech to thee to hear us, (O Lord) and that it may pleaſe thee to Rule and Govern thy Holy Church Univerſal in the Right Way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to keep and ſtrengthen, in the true Worſhiping of thee, in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs of Life thy Servant</hi> William <hi>our moſt Gracious King and Go-,vernuor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to Rule his Heart in thy Faith, Fear and Love; and that he may evermore have Affiance in thee, and ever ſeek thy Honour and Glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to be his Defender and Keeper, giving him the Victory over all his Enemies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:61238:15"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to Illuminate all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of thy Church, with true Knowledge and Underſtanding of thy Word; and that by their Preaching and Living they may ſet it forth and ſhew it accordingly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to endue the Lords of the Council, and all the Nobility, with Grace, Wiſdom, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to Bleſs and Keep the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, giving them Grace to execute Juſtice, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to give to all thy People Increaſe of Grace, to hear meekly thy Word, and to receive it with pure Affection, and to bring forth the Fruits of the Spirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to bring into the way of Truth, all ſuch as have Erred and are Deceived.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to Strengthen ſuch as do ſtand, and to Comfort and Help the weak Hearted, and Raiſe up them that Fall, and finally, to beat down Satan under our Feet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to Defend and Provide for the Fatherleſs Children and Widows, and all that be Deſolate and oppreſſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to forgive our Enemies, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors and Slanderers, and to turn their Hearts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to give us [and all Men] true Repentance; to forgive us all our Sins, Negligences and Ignorances, and to endue us with the Grace of thy Holy Spirit, to amend our Lives according to thy Holy Word.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt;</p>
                     <p>As it was in the beginning, is now, and ever ſhall be, World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PArt 1. Page 1. line 13. for <hi>of God,</hi> read <hi>for God,</hi> p. 8. l. 1. f. <hi>derided,</hi> r. <hi>divided.</hi> p. 21. l. 14. r. <hi>doth blind.</hi> p. 32. l. 12. f. 45. r. 35. p. II. p. 12. l. 16. f. <hi>third,</hi> r. <hi>ſecond part.</hi> p. III. p. 13. l. 32. f. <hi>unwilling</hi> r. <hi>willing.</hi> p. 26. l. 12. <hi>on this</hi> del. p. 15. l. 7. f. <hi>K.</hi> C. II. r. <hi>K.</hi> C. I. in Cutting off his Head; for that (ſay they) was a remarkable Record of the Righteous Judgment of God.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See their Book,</hi> Weſt Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to North, <hi>p.</hi> 97.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61238:15"/>
                  <head>George Whitehead TURN'D <hi>TOPSIE-TURVY.</hi> PART I.</head>
                  <p>I Find in a Book wrote by <hi>W. Penn,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>A Key, &amp;c.</hi> [and preſented to the Parliament, 1699. to obviate the Objections againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Books then preſented to both Houſes of Parliament by the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergy.] this Paſſage to the Reader in his Epiſtle, <hi>i. e. It is very Unfair, as well as Indiſcreet, in any, to Oppoſe and Calumniate what they do not</hi> Underſtand. <hi>It has been</hi> (ſays he) <hi>our Unhappineſs, far more than all our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have been able to ſay againſt us, that hitherto we remain</hi> Unknown <hi>by thoſe who yet ſtick not to condemn us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:61238:16"/>
                  <p>This indeed, if true, might Apologize for them; but it is ſo far from that, that were their Principles, and the Danger of them, fully known, it would operate more againſt them, that all their Adverſaries (as they account them) have yet ſaid againſt them, for want of knowing them ſo fully, as by their Fruits in time poſſibly may be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: But whoſe Fault is it that they are no better known? Is it not their own? By their two-fac'd Practice, and double Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in all they ſay or write, their Books be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two ſorts, contrary each to other, ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their Titles and Directions, one ſort to the World's People; whether to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Biſhops, Judges, Juſtices, Prieſts, and Profeſſors, in many of which they'll pretend to own the Scriptures, yea, and a Scripture-Trinity too, tolerably well; but their other ſort of Books to their Diſciples, directed with theſe and the like Titles, <hi>viz. This is only to go amongſt Friends.</hi> Again, <hi>This is only to go among Friends, and not otherwiſe.</hi> Again, <hi>Written only for Friends that can read it.</hi> In which they tell you, the Scriptures are <hi>Death, Duſt, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, a Rotten Foundation, a Dead Letter, the Husk,</hi> &amp;c. and that ſuch as tell People that the Scriptures are the written Word of God, are no Miniſters of Chriſt; that the Scriptures are not a Means to bring People to the Knowledge of God, and to work Faith in them; and that the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61238:16"/> Trinity of Perſons is for the Lake, and the Pit: But notwithſtanding all this, and ten times more that I could recite, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of their acknowledging to the World's People, as above, the Excellency of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and that it's of Divine Authority, and the beſt Book extant in the World, in direct Oppoſition to their Doctrine they teach to their poor deluded and willingly ignorant Diſciples; yet they frequently call their own Books <hi>The Word of God,</hi> as in many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I could ſhew: Nay, I have one Book of theirs by me, wrote by <hi>Chriſtopher Tayler,</hi> one of their ancient and approved Teachers, bearing this Title, <hi>Certain Papers, which is the Word of the Lord;</hi> and in <hi>p.</hi> 2, 3, 16. of that Book it's ſaid, <hi>To you all this is the Eternal Word of God:</hi> Nay, further, <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> preferrs them to be of greater Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority than the Bible. Thus do they, to their Diſciples, contemn, villifie, and ſet at nought the Sacred Word of God, whilſt they extol their own Pamphlets, as <hi>The Word of the Lord;</hi> yea, <hi>The Eternal Word of God;</hi> and as ſuch, of greater Authority than the Holy Scriptures: How then is it poſſible for ſuch as are not Converſant with their Books to know them?</p>
                  <p>Indeed, to underſtand <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> rightly, is the Buſineſs of an Age, I have had more than Forty Years Experience of them, and yet I do not know the Depth of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Hypocriſie; I mean, of their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61238:17"/> for amongſt their Hearers I do believe there are many honeſt (tho' miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded) amongſt them; I my ſelf in my young Years was carry'd away with their Diſſimulation, and a great Zeal I had, tho' I muſt confeſs it was without true Scripture Knowledge: But ſome Years before I left them, I ſaw them both to walk and act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Pretenſions, (a large Account thereof I have given in my <hi>Pilgrim's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi>) inſomuch, that I wrote four Books againſt their Hypocriſies whilſt with them, in hopes of a Reformation amongſt them; but ſtill, the more I came to examine into their Principles, and to obſerve their Practices, the more cauſe I found to leave them, and to this Day I have kept on Ripping and Stripping this well-favoured Harlot, who calls her ſelf <hi>the only true Church of Chriſt, and that out of her there is no Salvation;</hi> as in <hi>Joſiah Coole</hi>'s Book, <hi>The Whore unvailed,</hi> &amp;c. p. 12, 16, 18, 28, 31, 41, 50. where alſo ſhe aſſerts their Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; and that there's no Tares in their Church; that their Light is Judge of all Controverſies, all Power in Heaven and Earth being committed to it, and Miracles thereby wrought: And that ſhe agree with the Papiſts, that our Bible is a brazen-fac'd Book, an unjuſt, corrupt and perverſe Bible, elſe ſhe would not have printed it after them, without a Word of Reproof; and the more I came to ſtudy this Point, the more cauſe I found to diſcover, and lay bare her
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61238:17"/> Nakedneſs to the view of the Nations; and my Labour has not been in vain, but have proſpered, notwithſtanding <hi>G. W.</hi>'s Inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Demureneſs, and hardy Boldneſs, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf and Brethren from my ſeveral and repeated Charges of divers Kinds, tho', like the Magicians of old, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.7. he has done much Hurt: But this Book of his I am now Reprinting will be like <hi>ver.</hi> 18. I know and am perſwaded there is a Finger of God's Divine Providence that has attended thoſe who have denied themſelves, and have faithfully managed this Controverſie of God's Glory, and the Good of Souls, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to become as the Off-ſcouring of all things for his Name ſake.</p>
                  <p>But why do they ſtill complain they are not known? I do think if they look into my Books they may ſee themſelves as in a Glaſs, and ſo may others, eſpecially in <hi>New Rome Unmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>New Rome Arraign'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Picture of Quakeriſm drawn to the Life,</hi> &amp;c. my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Quakeriſm Expoſed;</hi> I ſay, theſe eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tho' I think there's none that I have writ but give ſome Diſcovery, mote or leſs; but if all theſe be wanting, read <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> and the Defence of it, and then I cannot think any thing is lacking to make the Quakers <hi>Known,</hi> and <hi>Underſtood:</hi> But if after all <hi>G. W.</hi> can with his Juggles and Paint blind the Eyes of ſome that are dim-ſighted, let them look well into his own
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61238:18"/> Book, <hi>i. e.</hi> Iſhmael <hi>and his Mother caſt out, &amp;c.</hi> which I herewith Reprint, [that ſo he may not ſay I leave out the foregoing or ſubſequent Words, his old and uſual Policy to blind his ignorant Followers,] and I am perſwaded they may ſee and know Quake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm to be the moſt horrible Hereſie that ever the World knew.</p>
                  <p>Indeed when the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergy preſented their Books to the Parliament, of the vile Hereſies, Seditions, and Blaſphemous Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> I thought it almoſt impoſſible for the <hi>Quakers</hi> to withſtand the Force of the Quotations taken out of their Books; but rather that they would have bluſhed, repented, and have begg'd of God and the Nation Forgiveneſs, for the Hurt they have done to Chriſtianity, and Scandal they have brought upon the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, both at home and abroad; but behold, <hi>G. W.</hi> like the Inchanters of old, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. with his cunning Craft, whereby he lies in wait to deceive, (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> well deſcribes ſuch;) as if he had eaten Shame, and drank after it, [whoſe Face is like Braſs, and his Forehead like Caſe-hardned Steel] he ventures to defend, vindicate, or excuſe every Error, every Blaſphemy, every Seditious and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Principle objected againſt them, the like of which was never broached before in <hi>England.</hi> And why not? For by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod he has taken (if allowed) he may do it: Nay, this I dare undertake, allowing me
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61238:18"/> his Method, to vindicate or excuſe all the Blaſphemous Hereſies and Treaſons that ever was wrote ſince the Days of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror; and thereupon it came into my Heart to Reprint one of his Books herewith, <hi>viz. Iſhmael and his Mother caſt out,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> except the Poſtſcript, to which no Hand is ſet, to avoid his future Cavils; and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hereafter may Reprint his <hi>Truth defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Truths Defence,</hi> if I ſee Cauſe: And tho' I ſhall not anſwer every Particular in his <hi>Truth and Innocency vindicated,</hi> yet I ſhall give ſome brief Hints of his Method, in defending the <hi>Quakers</hi> and himſelf from the Quotations taken out of their Books by the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergy, which I am ſure they did with great Care and Fidelity, and that to my Knowledge, <hi>viz. P.</hi> 6. <hi>Theſe Words [whom</hi> John <hi>ſaid he was not] we diſown in that place—his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ought to be conſidered.</hi> P. 9. <hi>We deny the Words as there printed, [He that hath] ſhould be leſt out.</hi> P. 11. <hi>We know they intended.</hi> P. 19. <hi>The Words ſhould be tranſpoſed.</hi> P. 25. <hi>They wanting due Points, —there wanted this Parentheſis.</hi> P. 29. <hi>He means Spiritually, and not Literally.</hi> P. 30. <hi>He meant Earthly Perſecuting Kings.</hi> P. 45. <hi>His Words ſhould run thus.</hi> P. 46. <hi>It ſhould rather have been.</hi> P. 52. <hi>Here I take him to mean.</hi> P. 63. <hi>Not warrantable Expreſſions.</hi> P. 55. <hi>He means—I know his Intent was not.</hi> P. 59. <hi>He means not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61238:19"/> derided.</hi> P. 61. <hi>Was never ſo intended.</hi> P. 62. <hi>The Words ſhould be tranſpoſed.</hi> P. 67. <hi>It was directly intended,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, give me but this Allowance, and I dare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to defend and excuſe all the Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Words, Blaſphemous Expreſſions, and Heretical Principles that ever was wrote by Pen; yet this is the Method that <hi>G. W.</hi> has taken, to excuſe all the Blaſphemies and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Principles quoted by the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergy, out of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books, inſtead of condemning them to the Flames, as he ought to have done, had he had the tenth part of that Sincerity he oft pretends to: Nay, moreover when ſome of the Quotations were ſo apparently Seditious, as that they ſtruck at the very Conſtitution of our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Government, <hi>viz. That a Parliament choſen by moſt Voices could not act for God, nor the Good of his People,</hi> and wrote by a Prophet too, enough to raiſe the Mob; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as <hi>Whitehead</hi> did not dare to recite the ſaid Quotation, yet had he the Impudence to juſtifie his Brother <hi>Fox, p.</hi> 33. <hi>viz. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he</hi> (Fox) <hi>had an honeſt intent in what he writ on this Subject:</hi> Yet nevertheleſs in the ſame Page, and <hi>p.</hi> 64. his Heart ſo ſmote him, that he cried out, <hi>I would not</hi> (ſays <hi>Whitehead) be underſtood in any wiſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Peoples juſt Rights of Elections;</hi> not underſtood! No, I believe it; that is, tho' he owns <hi>Fox</hi>'s Seditious Doctrine, tho' he defends and juſtifies it, ſaying, <hi>Certainly he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61238:19"/> had an honeſt Intent in what he writ on this Subject,</hi> yet he would not be underſtood ſo. The Engliſh of which is this, that tho' both <hi>Fox</hi> himſelf, and the reſt of their leading Gang, own this Doctrine as their Ancient Teſtimony, from which (as themſelves ſay) they have not deviated in any one Point, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſome Politick Reaſons he would not be <hi>So Underſtood;</hi> that is, he would not be underſtood to be what he really is; elſe why ſhould he juſtifie that in his Brother <hi>Fox</hi> which he diſowns in himſelf? Indeed he makes an Apology for <hi>Fox,</hi> that they were wrote occaſionally in the Commonwealths Day; what then? I grant they were firſt wrote in 1659. but then they were Reprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Quakers</hi> as one of their Ancient Teſtimonies Seven Years after, <hi>viz.</hi> 1665. and has gone among the Friends ever ſince, as the Word of the Lord, wrote by a Prophet of the moſt high, namely, <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> Jun. But <hi>George,</hi> if it was ſo <hi>certainly</hi> honeſtly writ, why didſt thou not recite it, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might have been Judges of it? Well, but ſince thou haſt not, I ſhall; <hi>viz. A Brief Diſcovery of ſome of the Blaſphemous and Seditious Principles and Practices of the Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. p. 17. <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> Jun. in his Works, Reprinted 1665. <hi>p.</hi> 87, 88. intitles his Epiſtles, <hi>A few plain Words to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by thoſe of the Army, or others, that would have a Parliament choſen by the Voices of the People,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>wherein is ſhewed unto
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61238:20"/> them according to the Scriptures of Truth, that a Parliament ſo choſen are not like to govern for God, or the Good of his People. Conſider theſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you; which in waiting upon the Lord, he by his Spirit of Wiſdom and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding opened in me concerning the chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Parliaments by the Voices of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And p. 89. he ſays, <hi>You are not like to ſee your Deſires fulfilled by a Parliament choſen by the Voices of the People;—Now if you believe theſe Scriptures,</hi> John 15.19. Matth. 7.13. Rom. 9.27. <hi>Then may you ſee, that a Parliament that is choſen by moſt Voices, are not like to act for God and the Good of his People,</hi> And p. 91. <hi>And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the chuſing of Parliament Men accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Cuſtom of</hi> England, <hi>which is called its Birthright, ſtands in reſpect of Perſon, and not in Equality; for the Rich; Covetous, Oppreſſing Men, who oppreſs the Poor, they have the only Power to chuſe Law-makers, and they will chuſe, to be ſure, ſuch as will uphold them in their Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And p. 92, 93. <hi>And we ſee the People have been in great Blindneſs, in contending for Parliaments ſo choſen.</hi> P. 149. Again, <hi>It is God's proper Right to give Laws unto Man:—Now in this Particular alſo Man have ſet himſelf in the Seat of God, and ſo have diſhonoured the one Lawgiver, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up many Lawgivers.</hi> P. 150. <hi>Now mark and conſider theſe things, ſeeing that the Righteous are fewer in number than the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61238:20"/> Unrighteous; and that the Lawmakers are choſen by the moſt Voices, and that of the Richeſt People outwardly, how are the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous like to be preſerved in outward Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by the Laws that are ſo made?</hi> P. 159. <hi>And I muſt deal plainly with you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in the Sight of God, who hath made</hi> Me <hi>a</hi> Prophet <hi>to</hi> This <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well, <hi>George,</hi> I have recited it, and do averr it was fairly quoted out of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Fox</hi>'s Works, Reprinted by your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, 1665. and it is not length of Time, or change of Governments, that can abate the Force of a Prophecy of a divinely inſpired Prophet: No, <hi>George,</hi> if God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty did inſpire this your Prophet, and reveal to him from Heaven, his Holy Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That a Parliament choſen by moſt Voices could not, or were never like, to Act or Govern for God or his People; then 'tis of Force, and you ought to ſtand by it in the Face of all Unbelievers; but on the contrary, if you do now ſee that <hi>Fox</hi> was an Impoſtor, (as I conceive that to be your Caſe) and that he was never ſo moved of God, but inſtigated by a deluding Spirit: then no marvel you dare not recite it, but, as in <hi>p.</hi> 69. make this guilty Excuſe, <hi>viz. We are only defenſive, and not under a neceſſity of reciting the Clergies whole Quotations:</hi> But whether only defenſive, we ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by and by. But, <hi>George,</hi> if this Excuſe of yours was your Prudence, leſt ſuch as you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61238:21"/> preſent your Books to ſhould ſee your old Seditious Principles; and which is ſtill worſe, that you ſhould have the Face to Reprint and Defend them; then, <hi>George,</hi> I would willingly know where your Honeſty and Sincerity is you ſo often boaſt of. But enough of this, I ſhall proceed to another of your Juggles, as bad as this, in <hi>p.</hi> 29. viz. <hi>As to what theſe Men</hi> (i. e. the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> Clergy) <hi>quote againſt us,</hi> p. 16. <hi>to prove us Antimonarchial, they are very broken in their Quotations with their many ſenſleſs Daſhes, like the Snake in the Graſs,</hi> Second Edition, p. 220. <hi>But varying in the Citation of the ſame Paſſage, theſe Men (i. e.</hi> the Clergy) <hi>have the Words, [Are not all theſe Elders, that doat ſo much of an Earthly King?]</hi> But the Snake, has it, <hi>[Are not all theſe Chriſtians, that will doat ſo much,</hi> &amp;c.] An excellent Critick: Here <hi>George</hi> is at his old Work, even ſplitting a Hair, if poſſible, and all to amuſe his Reader, and to put a Vail, if poſſible, over the <hi>Quakers</hi> moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Antimonarchial and Treaſonable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, eſpecially ſince of late in their Yearly Meeting, and other their late Prints, they have reaſſerted all theſe their Ancient Seditious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and tell us they are the ſame ſtill, and not changed, as in the Poſtſcript to their <hi>Iſhmael</hi> herewith Reprinted I ſhall ſhew; which, if ſo, they do indeed, as to themſelves, make void the Act of Indemnity, which otherwiſe would have blotted out theſe their old Sins:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61238:21"/> But ſince they ſay their Principles are now no otherwiſe than they were in the beginning, I think it is highly reaſonable that they ſhould be examined thereabout: And this I think ought to be the Deſire of every true Engliſh Freeholder.</p>
                  <p>But come, <hi>George,</hi> as to the varying of theſe Men, one ſaid, <hi>Are not all theſe Elders, &amp;c.</hi> the other, <hi>Are not all theſe Chriſtians, &amp;c.</hi> What harm is in all this, eſpecially ſince the Words of your <hi>Fox,</hi> in his Book, ſtiled, <hi>Several Papers given forth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> 1659. are, <hi>And are not all theſe</hi> Elders, Chriſtians, <hi>that will doat ſo much of an Earthly King, Traytors againſt Chriſt?</hi> Now what if the Clergy took only the Word <hi>Elders,</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Snake in the Graſs</hi> took the Word <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſince one is enough to ſhew your Meaning; tho' <hi>Fox</hi> (as his manner uſually was) put in more than enough, what harm is in all this pray? But if you had looked in <hi>p.</hi> 80. of my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs, &amp;c.</hi> there you would have found that I have put it even as <hi>Fox</hi> did, <hi>viz. And are not all theſe Elders Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that will doat ſo much of an Earthly King, Traytors againſt Chriſt?</hi> Oh, <hi>George,</hi> if I would go thorough this Book of thine, I could ſhew abundance of theſe thy Shuffles, and Legerdemain, uſed on purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy Readers. But now to the Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's Quotation, which I ſay is fairly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and carries the Force and Meaning of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61238:22"/> your great Apoſtle <hi>Fox;</hi> neither do the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> Clergy, nor the Author of the Book, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently intituled, <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> vary one tittle in the Relation of <hi>Fox</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; but if you think it do, I will now add <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to <hi>Elder,</hi> and then let the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſee how it helps your Cauſe, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one of thoſe Words had not been enough to expreſs your Senſe; but a Man near drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will lay hold of any Twig; and your Infallible Cauſe being Infallibly ſinking, you are forced to make uſe of ſuch Trifles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of reciting their Quotation, and then refuting it, as all fair Controvertiſts would do: And if not able ſo to do, then you ought to confeſs fairly, and acknowledge your Errors, and condemn your Apoſtle's Seditious Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>Now to the Quotation, <hi>A brief Diſcovery of ſome of the Blaſphemous and Seditious Principles and Practices of the Quakers,</hi> p. 16. G. <hi>Fox</hi> in his Book, <hi>Several Papers gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to Presbyterians,</hi> &amp;c. juſt before the Reſtoration, writ <hi>Anno</hi> 1659. and printed the beginning of 1660. he hath theſe Paſſages; <hi>Friends, To all you that deſire an Earthly King in</hi> England, &amp;c. <hi>whether Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, or others:— Did the Elders of old in the Days of Chriſt, or the Apoſtles, cry up any King but Chriſt, to have any King to rule over them but Chriſt? And doth not the Prieſts and Presbyterians cry for an Earthly King, and will have</hi> Ceſar?—<hi>And do they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61238:22"/> not in this crucifie Jeſus?—Are not all theſe</hi> Elders Chriſtians, <hi>that will doat ſo much of an Earthly King,</hi> Traytors <hi>againſt Chriſt?— Do you read that there were any Kings ſince the Days of the Apoſtles, but among the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Chriſtians—<hi>for Chriſt is King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone—I ſay, that is the falſe Church that doth not live—upon the Head of the Kings: — They that be true Elders — never go about to ſet up an Earthly King over them to Rule</hi> — Herod <hi>the King was mad at the Child Jeſus — there is the Fruit of Earthly Kings — and hath not this been witneſſed in</hi> England? &amp;c. <hi>Ignorant and fooliſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that would have a King; and what Work</hi> Joſhua <hi>made with the Kings; how he brought them out of the Cave,</hi> a fit Place for them— <hi>and all theſe Novices Chriſtians, that are crying up Earthly Kings — And we know that theſe Kings are the</hi> Spiritual Egyptians, <hi>got up ſince the Days of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Come, ſmooth <hi>George,</hi> with all thy Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Sincerity, why didſt thou not recite this whole Quotation? But it ſeems thou art not under a neceſſity to be plain-hearted: What! it ſeems this is too plain, and too manifeſt: What! to be abſolutely againſt all Kings, and Kingly Government, and thy Paint not able to cover it? But, <hi>George,</hi> thou alſo ſay'ſt, <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>Let their Books and ours be</hi> compared <hi>to clear our Innocency from theſe Adverſaries Calumnies.</hi> Ah, <hi>George,</hi> this is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61238:23"/> ſtill worſe; what! to add Hypocriſie to Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon! Thou knoweſt, <hi>George,</hi> in thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if <hi>thou</hi> haſt <hi>any,</hi> or if it be not quite ſeared, that at <hi>Weſt Dereham</hi> Conference your Friends had an Opportunity, were preſſed to it, but could not be prevailed with; nay, tho' there then were near Twenty of your eminent Teachers, and about an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of your Hearers, yet not one of them could be prevail'd with, either to compare your Books; nay, nor to own them; and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Doctrine contained in them; how then haſt thou now the Impudence to ſay, <hi>Let their Books and ours be compared,</hi> as above? Wherefore in your next be plain, whether you have not deviated in any one Point from what you were in the beginning, and whether you reſolve to juſtifie your Friends Ancient Books, as you ſay you can; ſee the Poſtſcript to your <hi>Iſhmael</hi> annexed.— I will only trouble my Reader in this Place with one Citation more, and it is about the Trinity, and in this <hi>George</hi> is as defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and ſhort, as in the other, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is as plain; which is, to cover over their Blaſphemy againſt the Bleſſed Trinity; to manifeſt which, there are ſeveral Charges out of divers Books of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> in the Book intituled, <hi>Some few of the Quakers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Horrid Blaſphemies, Hereſies, and their Bloody Treaſonable Principles Deſtructive to Government,</hi> out of which I ſhall mention but one, to ſhew as well how ſhort <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61238:23"/> is in reciting it (upon his Excuſe of being only defenſive, and thereby not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a neceſſity to cite the whole) as above noted; See <hi>Some few of the Quakers many Horrid Blaſphemous Hereſies,</hi> &amp;c. p. 1. out of <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> &amp;c. p. 246. <hi>The Scripture do not tell the People of a Trinity, nor Three Perſons, but the Common-Prayer-Maſs-Book ſpeaks of Three Perſons, brought in by the Father the Pope.</hi> To this <hi>George Whitehead</hi> Replies, <hi>Truth and Innocency vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated,</hi> &amp;c. p. 50. ſaying, <hi>Their firſt Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Scripture do not tell People of a Trinity, nor Three Perſons,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo dropt the other part of the Quotation out of <hi>Fox,</hi> viz. <hi>But the Common-Prayer-Maſs-Book ſpeaks of Three Perſons brought in by the Father the Pope.</hi> Theſe he left out, as now not proper to mention, ſince the Act of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration enforces the Acknowledgment of the Bleſſed Trinity, as the Condition of their Liberty.</p>
                  <p>But as a Salvo, <hi>p. ibid. George Whitehead</hi> urges another Book of <hi>George Fox</hi>'s, ſtiled, <hi>Some Principles of the Elect People of God called Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1671. p. 43. <hi>Of the Word</hi> Trinitas; <hi>there is no mention made in Scripture, yet the Scripture ſpeaks of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and all theſe are one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have with ſome Difficulty procuted this Book in order to trace and to find out <hi>George Whitehead</hi> in all his Subterfuges, and lurking
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61238:24"/> Places, and I find him as falſe, in citing <hi>Fox</hi> their Apoſtle, as in the above-noted: For of the 57 Words in <hi>Fox</hi>'s Paragraph, he <hi>(G.W.)</hi> has cited but 26 Words, which is not the one half, but the reaſon is, there is no more for his Turn, and his Buſineſs is only to ſerve a Turn, Jeſuit-like, as his Friend <hi>Anne Docwra</hi> well obſerves; now to the Quotation of <hi>Fox,</hi> which <hi>Whitehead</hi> has ſplit, <hi>viz. Some Principles of the Elect,</hi> &amp;c. p. 43. <hi>Of this Word</hi> Trinitas <hi>there is no mention made in Scripture, yet the Scripture ſpeaks of Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and of Water, Blood, and Spirit, and</hi> all theſe are one among us, <hi>as in the Primitive time among the Apoſtles, who gave no ſuch outward Names to them as Trinity, as the World now doth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Who then can believe this People, who thus ſplit Sentences, and mangle the Sence? For here is Six Perſons in the <hi>Quakers</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, Father, Son, Holy Ghoſt, Water, Blood, Spirit; all theſe are one among the <hi>Quakers;</hi> ſo that here is a twofold Trinity, <hi>Trinitas &amp; Trinitas,</hi> in the Unity of their Eſſence, where no one is greater or leſſer than the other, nor yet one before or after the other; for the Water is Spirit, the Blood is Spirit, and both the Light within, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and all within, and every of theſe Lights is their Eternal God: And to this agrees <hi>George Fox,</hi> Jun. in his Works, <hi>p.</hi> 66. <hi>viz. By one that witneſſeth</hi> God, <hi>Chriſt, the Light, the Word, the Spirit,
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:61238:24"/> the Truth, the Kingdom of God,</hi> within me <hi>and theſe are one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reader,</hi> Here is in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Eſſence <hi>Septem Perſonas;</hi> of which, no one was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, nor none greater or leſſer than another, and all within. Again, <hi>p. ibid. Stumble not at the Light, for if thou doſt, thou ſtumbleſt at</hi> God, <hi>at</hi> Chriſt, <hi>at the</hi> Door, <hi>the</hi> VVay, <hi>the</hi> Truth, <hi>the</hi> Life, <hi>the</hi> Rock, <hi>the</hi> Elect Stone, <hi>and</hi> all <hi>theſe are</hi> but one. Here again is one added; here is <hi>Octo Perſonas</hi> in the Unity of their Eſſence, of which no one was before the other, nor none greater or leſſer than the other; for the Stone is Light, the Rock is Light, the Life is Light, the Truth is Light, the VVay is Light, the Door is Light, and God is Light, and all within them: Only meaſurably, as <hi>p.</hi> 72. And verily, Friends, if you keep not to the meaſure of the pure God in you; ſo that God dwells in them by parts or meaſure; ſee <hi>p.</hi> 55, 83. <hi>ibid.</hi> The next thing I am to prove is their Light within to be the Eternal God; this done, I think I have proved that they, like Thieves and Robbers, have climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up another way, diſtinct from the Holy Apoſtles, Primitive Chriſtians, Saints, and Martyrs, and all Chriſtian Churches to this Day; in order to which, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 46, to 50. <hi>ibid. I the Light will fall upon you, and grinde you to Powder. All—who will not own me the Light in you; and—I will make you to know, that I the Light am the true E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61238:25"/> God, which created all things, and that there is not another beſide me can ſave. I matter not by what Name you are called by; whether it be King, Protector, Prince, Duke, Lord, Judge, Juſtice, Parliament, Prieſt, Lawyer, Gathered Churches, Army, Gentry, Mean Men, or Beggars, — I'll break all Sects and Opinions, and Gathered Churches, which are not in me, I'll break you in pieces; — I the Light in you will conſume it all, I'll Burn Heaven and Earth; I'll burn within and without; — I the Light will overturn Kingdoms, and Nations, and Rulers of all ſorts, and Armies, and gathered Churches, which will not own me the Light in them, to Guide and Lead them — And I will be your Dread, and ye ſhall be the Dread of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions — And ye ſhall Reign over all the World — I will give you Dominion over all your Enemies within and without, and I will make them</hi> all bow <hi>before you; and even as I am, (i. e.</hi> God) <hi>ſo ſhall ye be alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reader,</hi> from hence we may gather what Harangues they have in their Yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when their Doors are cloſe and ſecure, where they revive and re-aſſert their Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Teſtimonies; but their Trumpet gives ſuch an uncertain ſound, as none know but themſelves how to prepare to the Battel; you hear now that their Light within is God, the Eternal God by whom all things were made and created, and beſides their Light within, there is no God that can ſave; and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61238:25"/> yet ſometimes they Speak to their Light, and Teach their Light, even their Eternal God. For this ſee their Book, <hi>The Vials of the Wrath of God,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>G. Fox,</hi> Printed 1655, p. 6. <hi>Therefore to the Light in your Conſciences do I ſpeak,</hi> &amp;c. Sometimes their Light is Honeſt; that is, they have an Honeſt God. For this, ſee their Book, <hi>The Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of the Lord Blown,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>James Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> p. 2. <hi>To the Light in all your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I ſpeak, which is Honeſt of God.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their God is Blind, or Dim-ſighted; for this, ſee <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>News coming up out of the North,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The God of the World blind your Eye, which is the Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus have the <hi>Quakers,</hi> like the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites,</hi> deceived many Thouſands.</p>
                  <p>But hark, <hi>George,</hi> I have not yet done with your Guilty Excuſe. In your <hi>Innocency and Truth Vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 69. viz. <hi>We</hi> (ſays <hi>George) are only Defenſive,</hi> &amp;c. How <hi>George?</hi> What only Defenſive? That I do deny, and ſhall now make it appear, That from firſt to laſt you have been the Aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; altho' at preſent you are ſo cloſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tackt that you begin to call for a Ceſſation of Arms. But, <hi>George,</hi> we are now for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, or elſe no Quarter. It is not your Excuſe, That the Clergy in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s time were no Miniſters of Chriſt, nor your Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Epiſcopal Clergy, will now do, unleſs you condemn your Erroneous Books. See <hi>J. Feild</hi>'s Defence, <hi>&amp;c. If</hi> Francis Bugg
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61238:26"/> 
                     <hi>accounts thoſe Miniſters of Chriſt, that turned, and kept the Biſhops out of their Biſhopricks; how can he have the Face</hi> (ſays <hi>Feild) to own himſelf a Member of the Church of</hi> England? In this <hi>J. Field</hi> thinks he hits the Mark, but with a Reverſe; for, <hi>John,</hi> I do believe that in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s time there was a Chriſtian Miniſtry of Learned Clergy-men: And one Reaſon among others which make me ſo believe, is, becauſe they wrote many ſound Orthodox Books againſt <hi>Quakeriſm;</hi> and the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as they began, ſo they kept on againſt them: And that you are ſtill as great Enemies to the preſent Clergy, as you were againſt them, I ſhall ſhew anon. But I have not yet done with your Brother <hi>Whitehead;</hi> who with a mealy Modeſty ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers it out, That you <hi>Quakers</hi> are now only Defenſive; you are for an Amicable and Friendly Converſation, and no Lovers of Contention: Oh meek Saints! But hark, <hi>George,</hi> did not the <hi>Quakers</hi> firſt Challenge the <hi>Norffolk</hi> Clergy? I ſay, yea; and ſhall prove it from the Words of your Letter: viz. <hi>If you think you have Matter to charge us</hi> (Quakers) <hi>withal, let us have your Charge under your own Hands, and appoint Time and Place convenient; and we or ſome others of us will meet you as publickly as you pleaſe, — Any of you all, — Of your Cloth, — And ſtand a Publick Tryal,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>By which 'tis ſelf-evident that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Challenged the Clergy, and if I miſtake not, very boldly too; conſidering the many
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61238:26"/> groſs Errors, and horrid Blaſphemies you ſtand charged with, and convicted of, out of your moſt Authentick Writers. And for you, yea, I ſay, for ſuch a Tribe of Self-Condemned Schiſmaticks, to prick up your Ears, and to Challenge the moſt Learned Clergy the World have, and who are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the moſt Reformed Religion, and of an Eſtabliſhed Church by Law, I think this was bold with a witneſs.</p>
                  <p>But come, <hi>George,</hi> let us go back to your Beginning, and take our Meaſures from thence; for you would not have us take you for Changlings: You know <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> is the ſame, and the Principles of it; even what it always was, and will be to the End of the Chapter. For one ſingle Inſtance of which, I could give many. See your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Burroughs</hi>'s Epiſtle, prefixed to <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Great Myſtery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then being prepared of the Lord, and having received Power from on high, we went forth, as commanded of the Lord,— And the dread of the Lord went before us and behind us; and firſt of all our Mouths were opened, and our Spirits filled wih In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt the Prieſts and Teachers; and with them, and againſt them. Firſt we began to War; as being the Cauſers of the People to err; and the Blind Leaders, that carried the Blind into the Ditch: And againſt them as the Fountain of all Wickedneſs, abounding in the Nations, and as being the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61238:27"/> Iſſue of Prophaneneſs, — Shewing unto all them, and to all their People, that they were not Lawful Miniſters of Chriſt, ſent of him, but were Deceivers and Antichriſts, and ſuch whom the Lord never ſent. And we ſpared not publickly, and at all Seaſons, to utter forth the Judgments of the Lord againſt them, and their Ways, and their Churches, and Worſhips. — And this was our firſt Work which we entred upon, to Threſh down the Deceivers, and lay them open; that all People might come to ſee their Shame, and turn from them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thus then it plainly appears that the <hi>Quakers</hi> began this Conteſt, and have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it on in the ſame domineering and inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner, until of late: And nothing makes you pull in your Horns, but the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of your Bloody, Treaſonable, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Blaſphemous Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. And as a Third Inſtance that you are as Implacable Enemies to the preſent Eſtabliſht Church, Miniſtry, Scriptures and Ordinances, as you were in your dear Friend <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>'s Time, (as your Apoſtle <hi>Fox</hi> Saluted him) I ſhall cite ſome few of the Reaſons you give, why you deny the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Miniſtry, even in 1671, as more at large you may ſee in your Book wrote by <hi>George Fox,</hi> intituled, <hi>Some Principles of the Elect People of God called</hi> Quakers, Printed 1671, p. 5. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61238:27"/>
                     <head>Grounds and Reaſons why we deny the Worlds Teachers.</head>
                     <q>
                        <p>I. THEY (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Publick Miniſtry) are ſuch Teachers, as have told us the Letter was the Word, when the Letter ſays God was the Word; therefore we deny them, <hi>John</hi> 1.1.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Query.</hi> Where do the Scriptures ſay, that God the Father, the Firſt Perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is the Word? No; Chriſt, the Second Perſon, is the Word; proved by that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above quoted, and perverted by them. <hi>Whitehead</hi> in <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> p. 9.</p>
                     <q>
                        <p>II. <hi>They</hi> are ſuch Teachers as tell Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a Sacrament, for which there is not one Scripture; and ſo feed the People with their own Inventions; and therefore we deny them.</p>
                        <p>III. <hi>They</hi> are ſuch Teachers as have told us the Letter was the Light, whenas the Letter ſaith, Chriſt is the Light; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deny them, <hi>John</hi> 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Query.</hi> Where is the Man? What is his Name? What Book is it in? That the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſters ever ſaid, that the Letter (as they contemptuouſly call the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) was the Light mentioned <hi>John</hi> 1. or the Eſſential Word of God; only the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word of God, ſpoke forth by Men Divinely Inſpired; and as ſuch, are a Light, or give us Light; and are a Means to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61238:28"/> the Mind and Will of God, through the Influences of his Holy Spirit aſſiſting therein? No; this I take to be a falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, like that of <hi>Joſeph Wyeth</hi>'s <hi>Anguis Flagellatus,</hi> p. 158. <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                        <q rend="inline">Upon Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Chriſtopher Wade</hi>'s Words, they ſeem to imply, as if he had affirmed of the Scriptures, that they were the Eternal and Indwelling Word of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q> This is a Lie told in Hypocriſie; for I have read the Page through, and there is no ſuch Saying, or any thing like it. And thus do they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie their Adverſaries, both by falſe Citations, and Charges. Wherefore as the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſays touching the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> ſo may the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> conclude by the <hi>Quakers;</hi> both in reciting their Opponents, their reciting their Friends, and their Sham-Creeds and Proteſtations, in their late Books preſented to the Parliament, the Judges, Juſtices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> viz. <hi>Diſtruſt them in all they ſay.</hi> A <hi>Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of all which you have in this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. But to go on.</p>
                     <q>
                        <p>IV. <hi>They</hi> are ſuch Teachers as tell Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> is the Goſpel; (therefore we deny them.)</p>
                        <p>V. <hi>They</hi> are <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Merchants, that make a Trade of the Scriptures; —there-we deny them.</p>
                        <p>VI. <hi>They</hi> are ſuch Teachers, as take a Text out of the Saints Conditions; (<hi>i. e.</hi> out of the Scriptures,) therefore we deny them.</p>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61238:28"/>
                     <p>Theſe are ſome of the chief Reaſons why the <hi>Quakers</hi> deny the Publick Miniſters; and not only ſo, and there leave it; no; but in Magiſterial, Inſulting, Domineering manner, counſel and command the People, contrary to all the Laws made and eſtabliſhed, to go no more to Church: The like of which I do believe never was done by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting People (who enjoy their Liberty by Indulgence) ſince the World began; which after I have recited <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Motion from God,</hi> as he audaciouſly pretends, I ſhall recite this Counſel againſt the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhed Church; and next, his Authority from <hi>The Word of God,</hi> as he audaciouſly pretends, as in <hi>p.</hi> 15, 54. <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <p>Moved of the Lord, written from the Spirit of the Lord, for the Cleanſing of the Land of all <hi>Falſe Teachers, Seducers,</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and <hi>Witches,</hi> who beguile the People; and <hi>Inchanters,</hi> and <hi>Diviners,</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> and <hi>Hirelings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>All People that read theſe things, <hi>never</hi> come ye more at the <hi>Steeple-Houſe,</hi> nor <hi>Pay</hi> your <hi>Prieſts</hi> more <hi>Tythes</hi> till they have Anſwered them; for if ye do, ye uphold them in their Sins, and muſt partake of their Plagues, —<hi>This is the Word of the Lord God to you all,</hi> G. F.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>Reader, their Firſt and Great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>Pay your Prieſt no more Tythes;</hi> and their Second is like unto it, <hi>Never go more to the Steeple-Houſe;</hi> and upon theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61238:29"/> Two Commandments hangs their Law and their Prophets; and by this you may know that his Diſciples love him, in that they keep his Commandments. And the Reaſons he gives to enforce Obedience to their Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are, becauſe the Prieſts tell them that the Holy Scriptures are the written Word of God; becauſe they tell us of a Sacrament; becauſe they tell People, that <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> is the Goſpel; becauſe they take a Text out of the Scripture, and Expound it to the People: And for theſe and the like Reaſons, they call them Falſe Teachers, Seducers, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, Witches, Inchanters, Diviners, Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Hirelings: And for their Warrant, <hi>This is the Word of the Lord God to you all.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus do they ſit in the Judgment-Seat, even as in <hi>O. Cromwell</hi>'s Time; and for the ſame Cauſe, now, as then, they have Condemned not only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but Proteſtant Diſſenters too.</p>
                     <p>But, <hi>George,</hi> as I have turned thee topſy-turvy, ſo am I now turning thy Inſide outward, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by thy <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> &amp;c. thy Ancient Teſtimony and Principle; and thou ſayeſt thou art not changed. See thy <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to which I have neither added, nor diminiſhed, only the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Title-Page, Running Title, Marginal Notes, and Obſervations from <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. thy Name being on the Title-Page, the middle, and at the end, Signed and alſo Sealed with your Common Seal, <hi>i. e. Given forth from the Spirit of the Lord in us,</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But let me clear up one Paſſage in your <hi>Truth and Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency Vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <q rend="inline">As for this Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath poſitively diſowned the Words, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61238:29"/> affirms they are none of his, and that he writ not that Part of the Anſwer to <hi>Townſend,</hi> which was in the Year<note n="*" place="margin">It was 1655.</note> 1654. and that he ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand by nor own theſe Words. viz. <hi>And here thy Antiquity, and the Three Perſons, which thou would devide out of one, like a Conjurer, are all denied, and thou ſhut up with them in perpetual Darkneſs, for the Lake and the Pit.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, <hi>George,</hi> tho' thy Signing and Sealing this Book with thy Hand and Common Seal, as aforeſaid, were ſufficient to Entitle thee to this Helliſh Blaſphemy; as if thou hadſt Signed and Sealed a Bond of an Hundred Pound, made by a Scribe, would oblige thee to Pay the Debt; tho' thou didſt not write the Bond, yet, <hi>George,</hi> I have a further Demonſtration to prove the Book thine, and never heard that until 1690, (an Act being made, which enjoined all that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Toleration to own the B. Trinity) that you did diſown any part of this Book. But, <hi>George,</hi> Diſowning will not now do, you muſt Retract and Condemn it; and this to do, will be as bitter a Pill as it was to thee and thy Brethren to own K. <hi>W.</hi> III. <hi>Rightful and Lawful King</hi> of theſe Realms. For I have Mr. <hi>Smith</hi>'s Book, <hi>The Quakers Diſarmed,</hi> &amp;c. and your Book, <hi>Truth Defending the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> &amp;c. both Printed 1659. wherein he charges you with this <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and you both own and defend it. And firſt,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The</hi> Qua. <hi>Diſarm.</hi> &amp;c. Mr. <hi>Smith. He that writ this Book</hi> Iſhmael, <hi>opens a Door to Damnable Hereſies, you writ this Book,</hi> G. W. <hi>therefore you open a Door to Damnable Hereſies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>G. W. <hi>I deny it, I did not write all, there is ſomething ſcribled on it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi> True; here are ſome things writ on the back-ſide, I'll charge you with nothing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61238:30"/> but what is printed: Were you the Author of all that is printed in this Book; your Name is printed at the beginning, middle, and end of it.</p>
                     <p>G. W. <hi>About three Years ago, I and Four more writ it betwixt us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi> 
                        <q rend="inline">Pray tell me plainly whether you will own it or not; if you will not own it at all, then tell me what you will own, and what not; otherwiſe, when I have proved it a moſt wicked Book, you may diſown it, and ſo all my Diſcourſe fall to the Ground. 'Tis no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to me to ſpeak, or this People to hear vain Words. If you will not own it, ſpeak; but you may as well diſown to morrow all that you ſay to day, (telling us Words are but Wind) if you diſown what you have Printed and affixt your Name ſo often unto.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>G. W. <hi>Well, I will own it, prove what you can.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, <hi>George,</hi> leſt thou ſhould'ſt ſay this is an Adverſary's Book, (tho' that in this Caſe would not help Dun out of the Mire,) I ſhall now come to thy own Book, <hi>Truth defending the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="*" place="margin">Of Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the B. Trinity to the Pit and Lake.</note> ſaid in the Title-Page alſo, <hi>to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from the Spirit of Truth in</hi> G. W. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>P.</hi> 1. Queſtion recited out of the foregoing Book, to which this is in Anſwer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Smith. <hi>Do not you repent</hi> G. W. <hi>for your endeavouring vainly to Defend,</hi> Aug. 29. 1659. <hi>in ſo great a Congregation, theſe Poſitions printed in your Book of</hi> Iſhmael, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>G. W. <hi>The Poſitions we defended are according to the Scriptures of Truth, and them we need not repent of: As firſt, in denying the Bible to be the written Word of God: Secondly, in aſſerting the Scriptures not to be the Word: Thirdly, that there is no ſuch Word in the Scripture, as Three
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61238:30"/> Perſons in the Trinity; but it is a Popiſh</hi> Doctrine, <hi>mentioned in the Popiſh Maſs, or Common-Prayer-Book: Fourthly, And thou that affirm Three diſtinct Perſons in the Godhead, art a Dreamer; and he that Dreams, and tell Lies, he with his Imaginations and Dreams, is for the Lake.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Truth Defending,</hi> &amp;c. <q rend="inline">Where in the 33d <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> in <hi>The Quaker Diſarm'd,</hi> &amp;c. thou haſt falſly Charged <hi>George Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Book</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">Here he owns the Book, and defends the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> with proving ſeveral Blaſphemies in it, which is a wicked Lie and Slander; for thou never yet proved any Blaſphemy in it: For that thou counteſt Blaſphemies, was <hi>our</hi>
                           <note n="‖" place="margin">Mark, Our Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing.</note> 
                           <hi>Witneſſing</hi> againſt <hi>ſuch Doctrines</hi> as thou couldſt not prove by Scripture; as that of a Trinity of Three diſtinct Perſons in the Godhead, and that of the Letter being the Word.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Truth defending the</hi> Quakers <hi>and their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>P.</hi> 24. <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> therein reciting the 45th <hi>Queſtion</hi> of Mr. <hi>Smith</hi>'s, out of his Book <hi>The</hi> Quaker <hi>diſarmed,</hi> p. 6. for I have them both before me, <hi>G. W.</hi> thus Recites, and then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; <hi>viz. Do not you,</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly take to your ſelf an Attribute of God, while you pretend ordinarily to know the Hearts of Men; and tell Mr.</hi> Townſend <hi>of</hi> Norwich <hi>in the ſecond Page of your</hi> Iſhmael, <hi>that the Light of God is departed from his Conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. I think 'tis the faireſt Citation that ever I met with, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>G. W.</hi>'s, now comes his Anſwer: <hi>I (ſays</hi> G. W.) <hi>take no Attribute of God to my ſelf, but what God hath given me,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>And as for</hi> Townſend, <hi>I never ſaid that the Light was departed from his Conſcience, as thou haſt belied me; But that from the Light of God in his Conſcience he is departed</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">And ſo are the Words in p. 2. of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> as you may ſee: A plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note>, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Truth Defending,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>P.</hi> 25. <hi>In thy</hi> 46th Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>thou haſt</hi> (ſays <hi>G. Whitehead) charged me
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61238:31"/> with Printing Railing Language, with calling Prieſt</hi> Townſend <hi>Witch, Lyar, Blind Guide, in</hi> p. 3. <hi>of</hi> Our Book<note n="*" place="margin">A plain confeſſion, and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Book, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note>, <hi>&amp;c. —But there is not the Word</hi> Witch, <hi>but that thou would bewitch Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with thy Lies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Reader, I cannot inlarge, I now refer you to the Book which <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> owned, when he and his Partners Wrote it, when they Printed it, when they Diſputed with Mr. <hi>Smith, Aug.</hi> 29. 1659. when <hi>G. W.</hi> Printed his <hi>Truth Defending,</hi> &amp;c. which is at four or five ſundry times, and till 1690, which was 45 Years, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſowned it: Yet now he finds <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> ſinking, would inſinuate <hi>he did not Write it doth not Own the Words;</hi> is ſorry his Name is to it; and the like Diſſimulation. No, <hi>George,</hi> you muſt either Condemn it, as rank Blaſphemy, or Defend it; ſince your Hand Wrote it, Signed and Sealed it, as your Act and Deed.</p>
                     <p>Now therefore, <hi>George,</hi> my Advice is, That you go forthwith to your Second-Day-Meeting, and together with them, Condemn by Publick Cenſure under your Hands, this your Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Book <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and all other Books of yours, and of your Friends, of the ſame Nature and Tendency: For as St. <hi>Peter</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> I fear it may be ſaid to your Self, (and Partners.) Read <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21, 22, 23. <hi>Thy Heart is not right in the ſight of God; repent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this thy Wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the Thoughts of thy Heart (and the Words of thy Mouth) may be forgiven thee; for I perceive thou art in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and in the Bond of Iniquity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:31"/>
                  <p>ISHMAEL, AND HIS MOTHER Caſt out into the WILDERNESS Amongſt the wild Beaſts of the ſame Nature.</p>
                  <p>OR, A Reply to a Book entitulled, The Scriptures prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the word of God, put forth by one of Iſhmaels Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who calls himſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and a Paſtor of S. Auſtins and Savours Pariſh in Norwich; but is clearly made manifeſt by the light of God in his Servants, to be a ſcoffer, and an enemy to the Goſpel, which the Saints of God are Miniſters of, and ſufferers for, by ſuch as he is, who Iſhamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, hath laid his folly open, and is diſcovered to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who are of Abraham, and of the ſeed of Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALSO,</hi> A cleer diſtinction between the Miniſters of Chriſt, who are of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Prieſts of this generation, who are of Iſhmaels root; who with the Truth are plainly made manifeſt, by the light of Chriſt in us, who for the teſtimony of God do ſuffer by the ſons of Hagar, and this Generation of the Prieſts in Norwich: Given forth for no other end, but that the truth may be cleared from ſuch as ſcoff and deny it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Given forth from the Spirit of the Lord in</hi> us <hi>that do ſuffer in the Goal of Norwich for the truths ſake, which is perſecuted and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the Prieſts and Rulers of this City: Whoſe names in the fleſh is,</hi> Chriſtopher Atkinſon, George Whitehead, James Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter, Thomas Simonds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:32"/>
                  <p>OBſerve, <hi>Reader,</hi> That tho' the <hi>Quakers</hi> late Books ſeem to be more Orthodox than their Ancient Books, ſaid to be given forth (tho' moſt Blaſphemouſly) from the Spirit of the Lord, yet they are ſtill the ſame in Principle, tho' they otherwiſe word the Matter; for Proof of this, ſee their Book, <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity Revived,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>Joſ. Wyeth,</hi> Printed 1698, <hi>viz. Our Principles</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are now no other than what they were when we were firſt a People,</hi> &amp;c. Next, ſee <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Counterfeit Convert,</hi> &amp;c. p. 72. <hi>I may</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſee Cauſe otherwiſe to word the Matter, and yet our Intentions be the ſame,</hi> &amp;c. So that it is morally impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to underſtand the <hi>Quakers</hi> by their Words, whilſt they ſay and write one thing, and mean another, <hi>ARIUS</hi> like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore</hi> David <hi>ran and ſtood upon the</hi> Philiſtine, <hi>and took his Sword, and drew it out of the Sheath thereof, and ſlew him, and cut off his Head therewith: And when the</hi> Philiſtines <hi>ſaw their Champion was dead, they fled: And the Men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah <hi>aroſe and ſhouted, and purſued the</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, &amp;c. 1 Sam. 17.51, 52.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <div type="text">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61238:32"/>
                     <head>A bundle of papers,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 1. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> being brought unto <hi>our</hi> hands by one of the chief Prieſts of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, which he hath rak't up in his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, againſt the harmleſs people called Quakers, and being full of lyes and deceit, we are moved of the Lord for the truthes ſake, to cleare the truth from his lyes and deceit, and falſe accuſations, and to lay him and his two propoſitions (as he calls them) open unto the ſimple minded; who have been bewitched and deceived by ſuch deceivers and blind guides as he is; and put forth by one Sampſon Townſend, who calls himſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, and a Paſtor of Saint Auſtins and Savours Pariſh in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THE Title of thy confuſed papers is,<note n="†" place="margin">The Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi>'s Book.</note> The Scripture proved to be the word of God, as alſo the only foundation of faith, and rule of our obedience, or a clear conviction of the errors of the quakers, who blaſphemouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the Scriptures are not the word of God, nor the foundation of Faith, nor yet the only rule of our obedience; to which lyes and falſhoods we are moved to anſwer.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61238:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note>THE Scriptures proved to be the word of God is falſe, and one of the blind, deceitful imaginations, which thou and thy generation hath deceived people with, telling them, that that is the word which ſaith that God is the word, who made himſelf manifeſt in the days of old, before the Letter was, which word was Moſes rule, who wrote forth Scripture, and not the Letter but the word, which word by which Moſes was guided to ſpeak forth Scripture, and this is that word the Prophets propheſied of which dwelt amongſt us,<note place="margin">P. 2. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> which was before the world was, and ſeen before the Letter was written; now with the ſame life and power by which the Scripture was ſpoken, do we challenge thee to prove ſuch a Scripture as ſaith that it is the word of God, and thou that would make people believe that the Letter is the foundation, would make void the foundation, upon which the Prophets and Apoſtles were builded, which ſpoke forth the Letter, and thou that would build upon the Letter, hateth the Light and the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is Chriſt, from which the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſpoken, and thy foundation, and thy rule and obedience is tryed with it, and by it thou art judged, now that which is convicted by thy airy ſpirit is like unto thy ſelf, and is to be ſcorched up as the bryars, but the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light who are of God and in the truth, cannot be convicted by ſuch as thou art, who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61238:33"/> from the light of God in thy Conſcience is departed, and with it art to be condemned, ſo with the word and the life by which the Letter was declared thou art ſeen and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to be an enemy unto that from which the Scripture was declared, and here again I challenge thee to be a perverter of it, notwithſtanding all thy profeſſion from it, and whereas thou haſt directed this confuſed paper unto us, of whom thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the names, as followeth, to <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Atkinſon, James Lancaſter, George Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Symonds,</hi> now in <hi>Norwich</hi> Goale for their Errors and Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Thou ſayeſt if ever the truth of God were turned into a lye, it is by us (thou ſayeſt) that deny the Scriptures to be the truth of God, and pretend immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to be our rule for our actions, and canſt not produce any proof, but the words of a dead Man like thy ſelf, which thou calls Mr. Burroughs;</hi> to which we anſwer.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> By thee Prieſt <hi>Townſend,</hi> is the truth of God turn'd into a lye, and thou art taken with one in thy mouth, who ſaith that we before mentioned are in the Goal of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> for errors and miſcarriages, here thou ſlanderer we challenge thee to prove what errors or miſcarriages can be laid to our charge, what is thy lyes and ſlanders, that which you would make the people believe? and are we counted deceivers for declaring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61238:34"/> the Truth, and teſtifying againſt thee and thy generations, as it is counted an error in us to unvail thy deceits, and lay thee open to all men: here in the preſence of the Lord do we declare againſt thee, for errors and miſcarriages do we deny, and this thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſtuff wherein firſt thou ſayeſt that we deny the Scripture to be the truth of God, which is a lye, as thy own words makes it manifeſt, who in the ſame page of thy ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs diſcourſe, which now is laid open to the underſtanding of the Simple.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And again thou ſayeſt that we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Scripture to be the truth, and yet deny them to be the word of God, here let all that ſees thy confuſed paper judge thee, who art in Babel, where the confuſion is, and a miniſter of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture we own as it was ſpoken forth by them that lived in the word, and receive it as a Declaration of God, and of what he ſpoke unto them of former ages, Luke i.i.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 3. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> but thy words and imaginations we do deny, who would call that the word which ſaith God is the word, and that the light which is not the light, but ſaith Chriſt is the light, which is thy condemnation, that hates it in particular, and the worlds condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hates it in general, as is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, who hates revelations, and us who witneſs it, shutting thy ſelf forth from the Scriptures, and from them that gave them forth, whereas Chriſt ſaith, no man knows
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61238:34"/> the Father, but the Son, and to whom the Son will reveal him, as thou may read, Mat. ii. 27. here thou haſt plainly shewn thy ſelf to be both without the knowledge of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, who art in thy mediate natural knowledge, which from the light which comes from Chriſt is erred, and with it to be condemned; thou dreamer, what haſt thou to do to profeſs thy ſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who art but yet in thy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate natural conceivings, when the natural man knows not the things of God, for they are Spiritually diſcerned; ſo we from God is unto thee thou deceiver, who would make people believe that that which is natural and carnal is the foundation of Faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo would bewitch thy people with thy lyes, to draw them from the anointing within to obſcure ſomething without them, as they did, that would have drawn away the Galations from the Spirit, as thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt read, Gal. 3.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And whereas thou ſayeſt in the third Page that thou wilt reaſon with us, and tells us, that we did acknowledge the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be truth, which in the Page before thou did deny; and thus is making thy folly manifeſt, who ſaith that it is our judgment, that we are perfect and free from Sin, which thou never heard us affirm, but theſe thy lyes will clearly be made manifeſt by the Scriptures which thou calls thy foundation of faith, and only rule of obedience, by which thou ſhalt be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61238:35"/> judged, for Chriſt ſaith unto them whom he taught, be ye perfect, as your Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect, Mat.</hi> 5.28.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> But thou and thy generation hates this, and ſays that there is no perfection to be attained here; Oh thou blind guide! did Chriſt ever command any thing that might not be accompliſhed? or did he ſpeak of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfect, not till after death, here thou doſt deny the very end for which Chriſt came, who came to take away Sin, and in him is no Sin, Mat. i. 21. i. John 3.3, 4, 5, 6. and i. John 5.18. here thou haſt plainly made it manifeſt, that thou art without Chriſt and his knowledge, and in Antichriſt, now what the Scriptures ſpeaks, in our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure do we witneſs concerning theſe things, and thee we do deny, and all thy generation, thou enemy of God, who doth pervert the Scriptures, and wreſt them to thy deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and here with the light that never changed art thou to be condemned from God, and all the Children of God.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Another of thy lyes is made evident, thou ſlanderer, who art not aſhamed impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to affirm, that we deny the power of the Magiſtrates in the matters of God, and that we ſpeak not evil only of Governors, but of Government, and condemn the Miniſters of the Church of England, and deſpiſe them as falſe teachers,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 4. <hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and ſay they know nothing of the true light, and ſay we condemn them for preaching for hire, and ſay we deny Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61238:35"/> ſhould take any wages for their works.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> The powers that are of God ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we own in our ſouls, and for Conſcience ſake are ſubject to them, and ſuch as rule well in the things of God without reſpect of perſons, which reſpects of perſons is contrary to Scripture, ſuch we ſay are worthy of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour, and ſuch our Souls are ſubject to, for ſuch executed the Law upon tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and encourage them that do well, and their honour lyes not in a hat, or bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the knee, which is nothing but filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which thou and thy generation upholds, but the honour and ſubjection to him that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth well is in our ſouls, as it is written, Rom. 13.1. and here thy lyes and thy ſlanders we do deny and charge it upon thee from the Lord, to prove where ever we were not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto the power of Magiſtrates as it was of God, or where ever we ſpoke evil of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors or of Government: thus art thou found with lyes in thy right hand, thou ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of God, and where thou ſayeſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Miniſters of the Church of England, the Miniſters of Chriſt we own, but ſuch as thou art we deny, who ſeek for your gain from your quarter, and ſuch as call Steeple houſe Church, and letter word, and foundation, and light, and rule, when Chriſt ſaith he is the way, and he is the light, and he is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and he is the word, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Letter was, i. John i. 9. and John 3.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61238:36"/> and Rev. i9. i. Cor. 3. i2. and here again we do deny all ſuch as ſay that ſprinkling of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants is the Baptiſm and the ſeal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as thou <hi>Sampſon Townſend</hi> did affirm, and take i2 pence for ſprinkling of a poor priſoners child here in this priſon of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> the sixteenth day of the eleventh Month, and Scripture ſaith that the Baptiſme is with one Spirit into one body, and the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is but one, and the Church but one, which is in God, as thou may read, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 5, 6. and i. Theſ. i. and here thou and thy Church, and thy Baptiſme is ſhut out of Scripture, and with it judged, and with the light condemned to be upheld by ſuch ſottish blind guides as thou art.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And again thou ſayeſt that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of England ſpeaks nothing but what is according to the Law and the Teſtimony of God in his word, which is the rule to try all teachers by, and thou ſayeſt that this our Judgment is contrary to Tit.</hi> 2.15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whoſoever read that Scripture will condemn thy blindneſs in theſe things, who haſt pretended thy ſelf a teacher of others,<note place="margin">Mark, <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> this their Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and they are the ſame ſtill.</note> and yet ſhut up in perpetual darkneſs; thou blind ſot, where is it ſaid in all the Scriptures that the Letter is the rule to try all teachers by, or where doth it ever ſay that the Saints did ever try the Spirits by the Letter, or how canſt thou prove that ever it was called by the Saints the only rule of obedience; or a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61238:36"/> written word of God, with theſe thy lyes thou and thy generation hath deceived the blind and simple, taking their money for that which is no bread,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 5. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> making them believe lyes inſtead of truth, Oh, ye enemies of God, how long will ye deſpiſe the truth, if Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had not been theſe your filthy lyes would have gone forth as truth to thoſe that are in darkneſs, but praiſed be the Lord who hath diſcovered your filthineſs, and laid you open with his light, from which the Scripture was ſpoken, by which light we read you in the Scriptures to be among the falſe Prophets in their ſteps, and in the wayes of the Phariſes, and now finding you in the latter times your condemnation is juſtly related in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> as thou may read <hi>Iude</hi> 4.10, 11. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And again thou ſayeſt that Chriſt and his Apoſtles gave ſtrong reaſons for their maintenance, and to prove it; thou brings thoſe Scriptures, Mat.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let all that read theſe Scriptures judge thee by me to be a lyar, who formerly haſt teſtified, that the Scripture was the word of God, and thy rule and foundation, and now calls it reaſon, which from reaſon was never ſpoken, but holy men of God ſpoke them forth, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, now the Apoſtle which was as Miniſter of Chriſt never took wages of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61238:37"/> of the world, neither did he compel them. though to them he preached the Goſpel, and though he robbed other Churches, yet he robbed not the world, neither took he wages of the world, nor hired with them for a certain time, as thou and thy generation do, and this was his boaſting to cut off of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10, 12. but with the light of God in the offences we find you, who take wages of the world contrary to the Apoſtles, whoſe practiſes judges you to be without their life, whoſe entrance unto the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> he plainly doth declare, that it was neither for pleaſing men, neither of deceit, nor guile, nor a cloak of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, neither was their Goſpel burthenſom, as thou may read 1 Theſſ. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to which thou and thy generation art found in the ſteps of them,<note place="margin">Mark the Perverſion Offences for occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe are the Infallible Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles cryed againſt, as thou may read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. and <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. and <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. and <hi>Iude</hi> 11. And this is the Goſpel the Apoſtles preached, which is witneſſed by the ſame Spirit which to thee is hid, and all thy generations, who out of their ſteps are found walking in the ſteps of the falſe.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt the Apoſtle inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that God is mocked, when his Miniſters are not maintained, and thou ſayeſt that God will not be robbed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is another of thy lyes, who perverts the Apoſtles words, and art found adding thy lyes to Scripture, when there is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61238:37"/> not ſuch a word in all the Apoſtles words as intimate, but thou and thy generation are ſeen to be both thieves and robbers, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not in at the door, but climbs up another way, in your inventions, conſequences, and imaginations, which are here plainly ſeen and diſcovered to them that enter in at the door, and for diſhoneſt gain you deſtroy Souls, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.25, 26, 27.<note place="margin">P. 6. 4<hi>to</hi>
                        </note> and as a Troop of Robbers wait for a man, ſo do the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Prieſts murther by conſent, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.9. and are found Robbers of God, as the falſe Prophets were, who in the time of the Law took tythes, and did not bring them to the ſtore-houſe, as thy generation now do, as thou may read, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And thou ſays thy deſign according to promiſe, is, to prove the Scriptures to be the word of God, the only ground of faith, and rule for our obedience, which thou ſayeſt thou preſented us with, and bids us read it, examine it, if it be not truth, witneſs againſt it by truth, if it be ſo, as undoubtedly you will find it truth, as thou ſayeſt, and ſo bids us ſubmit to it, be ruled by it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly our bodies ſhall be freed from our deſerved Impriſonment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have read it, and examined it, and thee both, and have found thee to be a lyar, and a denyer of the Word, and of the rule, and of the foundation, which is Chriſt, and with that which thou calls a rule, and word, and foundation, art thou judged, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61238:38"/> with the light thou art ſeen to be a wreſter of the Scriptures, and thy Rotten foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being already to fail thee,<note place="margin">The Holy Scriptures they ſay are a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; this is their Ancient Teſtimony from which they have not varied.</note> for it is among the blind Watchmen and greedy dumb Doggs, and hirelings, and among the thieves and robbers, and among the Doggs and ſwine and filthy dreamers which the Scriptures ſpeaks of, and as for our deſerved impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, here thou lyar do we challenge thee and them that impriſoned us, to prove the breach of any law by us, for they that did impriſon us as many can witneſs, could not charge us with the breach of any Law; but by their wills to maintain ſuch dumb ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds as thou art; for, for the truths ſake, which witneſſes againſt thee and all thy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration do we ſuffer, for which thou and thy generation did never ſuffer impriſonment, nor perſecution of the world, for ye are the world, and the world ſpeaks well of you, and hears you, as it did of your Fathers the falſe Prophets, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4, 5, and <hi>Luke</hi> 6.26. drunkards ſwearers lyars and thieves ſpeaks well of you and fights for you, and loves you, and pleads for you, and there is your fruits and freedom; from our impriſonment will we never ſpeak for in yielding to thy lyes, and falſe accuſations, as is plainly here laid open.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And thou ſayeſt from thy ſtudy, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 29.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thy filthy rotten ſtuff which thou haſt been ſuch a long time of gathering
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61238:38"/> together in thy ſtudy, its tryed and ſeen to be fewel for the fire, and thou art ſeen to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy divinations of thy own brain, and to be an inventer of lyes, contrary to Scripture, and where did ever any of the Saints go into a ſtudy, and rake up ſuch filthy ſtuff, and invent ſuch lyes as thou art diſapproved in, and with that which thou calls thy word, thy foundation, and only rule of obedience. Here let the life of all the holy men of God judge thee to be both ſhut out of their life, and out of the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>Having returned anſwer to the former part of thy rotten ſtuff,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 7. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Sampſon Townſend</hi> wherein thy lies and deceit is uncovered to all them that have eyes to ſee, may ſee thy nakedneſs and thy ſhame laid open: now for the ſimple ones ſake, which thou by thy lyes and divinations makes a prey upon, and through thy covetouſneſs makes Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of, who phariſee-like would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enter into the Kingdom thy ſelf, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer others to enter in; now for their ſakes are we moved to unvail thee and thy deceit, that they that ſee not might ſee thee in thy lyes and wreſting the Scripture, as thou haſt alſo made it appear in the latter part of thy book; wherein thou ſayeſt,</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>That thou haſt undertaken againſt the Quakers theſe two Propoſitions,</hi> i. <hi>that the Scriptures contained in the Old or New-Teſtament (commonly called the Bible) is the revealed will and word of God,</hi> 2. <hi>That the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61238:39"/> Scripture, which is the word of God, is the only foundation of our Faith, and only rule for our obedience, which thou ſayeſt thou wilt prove,</hi> 1. <hi>by Scripture,</hi> 2. <hi>by Reaſon, and thou ſayeſt that he that will not hear the voice of the Scriptures is an Infidel, and he that will not hear the voice of reaſon is a beaſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> We who in ſcorn by thee and thy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations are called Quakers, do own Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but thee we utterly deny for an evill Beaſt, whoſe mouth muſt be ſtopped, <hi>Tit.</hi> i. 10, 11, 12. who in thy filthy reaſon art going about to maintain thoſe things which thou canſt not prove by any plain Scripture, but to it art found adding in thy reaſon, and thy invention, and therefore the plagues that are in it written is thy portion, and the lake, which is the portion of all lyars as thou art, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ought to convince us as Chriſtians, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as rational men.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that are Chriſtians do ſee and comprehend thee, and thy reaſon, thy faith, thy obedience, thy rule, thy foundation, to be without the foundation and the word, which was before thy inventions was, and before <hi>Tuball Cain</hi> the inventer thy father was,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 8. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> in whoſe condition thou art, and the word and foundation, and the way, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Beaſt and falſe Prophet was, which thou art, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.15, 16. and this rule and foundation and worde, did <hi>Moſes, David,</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61238:39"/> and the reſt of the holy men of God witneſs, who ſpoke forth Scripture, which thou calls the word, rule, and foundation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2.31.3. Here thou would make <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and the reſt of the holy men of God who ſpoke forth Scripture, blind, like thy ſelfe, both without the word rule, and foundation.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Now to prove the Scripture the word of God, thou brings</hi> Exod. 20.1. Levit. 10.13. <hi>and many other Scriptures thou brings to the ſame effect, how God ſpoke theſe words.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou blind ſot, we challenge thee in the preſence of the living God, to prove in any of theſe<note n="*" place="margin">They deny the Scriptures to be the written Word of God. This is their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, from which they are not changed; they tell you ſo.</note> Scriptures, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are the written word of God, or elſe ſtop thy mouth thou evil beaſt, and ſlow belly, doſt thou make no difference between the word and theſe words? and here again wee charge thee to be a lyar, and an adder to Scripture.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And thou brings theſe Scriptures</hi> Iſa. 24.3. <hi>and</hi> Pſal. 125. <hi>and other Scriptures to the ſame purpoſe, how the Lord ſaith, and thus ſaith the Lord, and</hi> Jer. 1.1, 2.4.9. <hi>the words of Jeremiah to whom the word of the Lord came.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> And the word of the Lord that came to <hi>Joel, Amos,</hi> and others, thou dreamer, doth ever <hi>Iſaiah, Jeremiah,</hi> or <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>Joel,</hi> or <hi>Amos,</hi> or any of the holy men of God, ſay that the Scripture is the written word, whenas God who is the word, <hi>John</hi> 1. ſpoke theſe words unto them, whoſe voice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61238:40"/> thou never heard, who ſpoke unto them before the Letter was written, which is a declaration of what the word ſpoke unto them, or was that paper and Ink, or could it be contained in paper and Inke, which came to the Prophets, whenas <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith the word is fire in his heart, and a burning ſhut up in his bones, and a hammer that breaks the rocks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29, 30. and behold I am againſt the Prophets ſaith the Lord, that ſteal my word every one from his neighbors, and behold I am againſt the Prophets ſaith the Lord, that uſe their tongues, and ſay he ſaith, and behold I am againſt them ſaith the Lord, that profeſs falſe dreams and tell them as thou doſt, and cauſe my People to erre by their lyes,<note place="margin">P. 9. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> and by their lightneſs, yet I ſent them not, nor commanded them, therefore they ſhall not profit the people at all ſaith the Lord, and there thou art among the falſe Prophets and dreamers, which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> who witneſſed the word, cryed wo againſt ſuch Paſtors as thou art, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.1.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Thou ſayeſt thou ſhalt not need to mention the ſayings and doing of our Saviour Chriſt, which are frequently recorded in the New Teſtament, and hence it is called the word of Chriſt, and thou brings the Scripture,</hi> Coloſſ. 3.16. <hi>let the word of Chriſt dwel in you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here again we challenge thee to be a lyar, and an adder to the Scripture: doſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61238:40"/> thou make no difference between death and life, for Chriſt ſaith, my words gives life, and it was by his word that the dead was raiſed, <hi>John</hi> 11. now that which <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> wrote of Chriſt, could not give life, for that is called a Declaration of thoſe things which was freely delivered among them, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1. and that thou calls the word which is death and killeth, as thou may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. and <hi>Paul</hi> was a Miniſter of the New-Teſtament, and not of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which thou calls the New-Teſtament: <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and this word which dwelt in the Saints, they did neither call the Bible nor the Letter, as thou doſt, here thou haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted thy ſelf to be a blinde guide, both ignorant of the Word and the Letter.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Thou ſayeſt that it is all one to ſay the Scripture ſaith, and God ſaith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou blaſphemous beaſt, doſt thou make no difference between the Scripture and God, or is the Scripture God,<note n="*" place="margin">God who is the Word; ſo they do not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Father from the Son, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Second Perſon of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</note> when the Scripture ſaith God who is the word, was in the beginning, and by him was all things made, and this was before the Scriptures was written, <hi>John</hi> 1.1. which thou would make thy God of, and here let all that reads this ſee thy blaſphemie.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt the word Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is put for God ſpeaking in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and thou brings Joſhua</hi> 1.5.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let all that reads that Scripture Judge and condemn thee to be a Lyar, for it ſpeaks not ſuch a word, as God ſpeaking in the Scripture.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61238:41"/>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again the ſame page thou ſayeſt, that all the reſt that is written in the volume is but a comment or expoſition of thoſe ten precepts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou diviner, where doſt thou prove ſuch a Scripture as comment? was that which the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles ſpoke out a comment or expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? here again we charge thee Prieſt <hi>Townſend,</hi> to be an inventer and a deviſer of lyes,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 9. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> which thou haſt no Scripture for.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt that thus it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Scriptures are the word of God, becauſe God writ them, and cauſed them to be written.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> That which is written is the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is death and killeth. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. but the word is living, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. there again with the Scipture thou art diſaproved to be a lyar.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again in another page thou ſayeſt, that the Scriptures are called the counſel of God, the will of the Lord, the myſtery of Gods will, and thou bring theſe Scriptures,</hi> Rom. 3.2. 1 Pet. 4.11. Acts 20.27. Pſal. 33.11. <hi>and</hi> Pro. 19.21. Epheſ. 5.17. <hi>and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this, thou ſayeſt that God himſelf calls the Scriptures his word, and to maintain that thou brings</hi> Zach. 1.6.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let all that reads theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Here Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi> is together with the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: behold their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony!</note> Scriptures, ſee thee to be a perverter of Scripture, and adds thy inventions to them, for they that ſpoke forth theſe Scriptures, knew the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God, and the myſtery, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61238:41"/> which to thee is hid, whom the God of this world hath blinded thy eyes, and out of the myſtery and Goſpel, and rule, and foundation, thou art with that which thou calls the only rule, and word, and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, art thou judged, and with light ſeen and condemned, to be an inventer of lies and a deceiver of the blind, but no further canſt thou proceed, for thy folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all men.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>In a ſecond reaſon of thine; thou ſayeſt, the antiquity of the Scriptures do clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove them to be of God, for man could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver write of things done before he had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the works of the five firſt dayes Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are mentioned in Scripture, but man was not made till the ſixt day, therefore they muſt needs be the word of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou blind Beaſt, who art ignorant of God, who makes antiquity as thou calls it, the perfect knowledge of God, and ſayes that man could not declare of things before ever he had a being, and ſo would make people believe that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reveal God; thou blind Beaſt, whether was man, or the Scriptures firſt? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did God make himſelf manifeſt unto? and thou that ſayeſt that the Scripture reveal God, thou art a lyar, for God revealed himſelf to <hi>Moſes,</hi> before the Scripture was written, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was the firſt pen-man of the Scripture, was 14 Generations after the fall, and yet he wrote of things, before the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61238:42"/> fall was, and thy father <hi>Cain</hi> was before Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was, and yet he knew no Scripture, and thou that would make the Letter the light and way of knowing God, are not ſo much as a Miniſter of the Letter, and here thou art made manifeſt to be in the fall, in the death, which paſt over all men before <hi>Moſes</hi> was, and are not come to fee the firſt Days VVork, to ſee light divided from darkneſs, and here let all the Prophets and holy men of God judge thee with the Light, from which thou art erred, for they wrote of Chriſt, and ſaw his day many Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations before he came in the fleſh, and here thy antiquity, and thy reaſons, and the three perſons thou dreams of, which thou would divide out of one, like a Conjurer are all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and thou ſhut up with them in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual darkneſs for the lake and the pit, for thou haſt no Scripture that mentions ſuch things.<note n="*" place="margin">This is their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, to damn the Bleſſed Trinity to the Pit of Hell.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 11. 4<hi>to</hi>
                        </note>Pieſt. <hi>And where thou art telling that the Scripture converts the Soul, and works Grace, and the opening thereof make hearts to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſays that Scripture diſcovers mens thoughts, and makes Laws for them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here thou haſt made thy ſelf mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, where did ever any of the holy men of God ſay that the Scriptures converts the Soul, or make Laws for mens thoughts? and what is that which opens the Scripture? or where is it, if the bare Letter convert the Soul? here thou Prieſt of <hi>Baal,</hi> for that is thy name, thy lyes are made manifeſt and deceits laid open
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61238:42"/> to the children of the Light, and art ſeen with the light from which the Scripture was ſpoken.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt the Scripture ſpeaks to all men alike, but thus do not the word of man, therefore thou ſayeſt they are the word of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> But thou thy ſelf and thy generation are perverters of the Scripture, and are reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of perſons, for you are called of men Maſter ſtands praying in the Synagogues, has the chiefeſt places in the aſſemblies, and the greeting in the Markets, and are pleading for cap and knee, and ſays we do not reverence Magiſtrates, becauſe we do not put off our hats, and bend our knees, as thou and the reſt of thy generation of Hypocrits do, who have mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, <hi>Iude</hi> 16. and this which you calls the word, ſpeaks not to all men alike, for wo is pronounced in it to ſuch as thou art, who art found in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets and Scribes, and Phariſees, and goes in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> to envie, and after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for gifts and rewards, which wo was never pronounced to the righteous, and wo unto thee thou lyar, who art a wreſter of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to thy own deſtruction, and art found with ſo many Lyes, as thou haſt here uttered.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>In another place thou ſayeſt no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (Angels men or, Devils if all were put together in one) could ever declare before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, what particular perſon ſhould be born,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61238:43"/> and what ſhould be their names, in ſo many thouſands yeers before their birth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here thou art taken with another lye, with which thou haſt ſtuffed up this thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Book, for both by Angels and Men was Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God propheſied of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was many years before Chriſt came in the fleſh, propheſied of Chriſt, and ſaid, like unto me will God raiſe up a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, him ſhall the People hear, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.17. ſee if thou can number the year of all theſe generations which propheſied of Chriſt, and when Chriſt came, he ſaith, before Abraham was I am, thus art thou known and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with the truth, which all thy fathers and generations paſt perſecuted, ſo be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſtop thy mouth for ever.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>In that thou calls thy two propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> 1. <hi>thou ſayeſt the Scriptures are the means by which faith is wrought, and to prove that ly thou brings, Rom.</hi> 10.17.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Shame cover thy face, thou full of rottenneſs and filthy dreams,<note place="margin">Scriptures not a means to work Faith. This is their Ancient Teſtimony</note> where did thou ever read in Scripture that it is the means whereby faith is<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 12. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                        </note> wrought, when that Scripture ſaith, faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word; here thou art deaf, and never heard the word, and thy faith and word is without, but the word of faith which we preach, is nigh in the heart and mouth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. therefore ſearch thou the Scripture with the Saduces who knew not Chriſt, for in them thou and thy generation thinks to have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61238:43"/> life, but ye will not come unto Chriſt, that ye may have life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.38, 39, 40.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>Again thou ſayeſt that the Scripture which thou calls the word, is an everlaſting rule ſo long as we live on earth.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which Mr. <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend</hi> calls the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Faith, in the Mire and Dirt.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thou blind ſot, ſee thy confuſion; can that Letter be everlaſting while we live upon earth? here thou haſt ſhewed thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon where it is, that they that are not ſtark blind may ſee thee, thy reaſon and thy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to be in the mire and dirt, and may ſee thee to be a ſenceleſs natural bruit Beaſt, who with thy lyes art made to be taken and deſtroyed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</p>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And again thou ſayeſt the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent believer ſin in many things.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here is the end of thy teaching, here is thy rule, and here is thy foundation, and here is thy obedience, and here is thy fruits, and here is thy ſervice, who commits Sin, and a Servant to Sin, and free from righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. Oh thou blaſphemer and ſlanderer of the juſt, when wilt thou ceaſe from thy Lyes and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, where doſt or canſt thou prove ſuch a Scripture as the moſt emminent believer, Sin in any things, when the Scripture ſaith he that believeth is born of God, and he that is born of God ſinneth not, for whoſoever ſinneth hath not ſeen him, neither known him, and he that committeth ſin is of the Devil, and theres thy condition, and he is thy Father, who is the Father of all lyars as thou art, i. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61238:44"/>
                     <p>Prieſt. <hi>And to conclude thy filthy rotten ſtuff, thou ſayeſt they that make not the word of God the rule for their actions are led either by their own fancies, or the Devils temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or both.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thee Prieſt <hi>Townſend</hi> art here laid open, and thou art uncovered, and here thou art found to be a denyer of the word, and rule, and foundation, and thou art led by thy dreams and fancies, and thy foundation<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Viz.</hi> The Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> is in the duſt, and thou art reſerved in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chains under darkneſs, for everlaſting fire, and here thou in all theſe thy lyes, are ſhut our from God, and all the Children of God, among the Doggs and Sorcerers, and the Lake is thy portion, which is the portion of all lyars, <hi>Iude</hi> 6, 7, 8. thus have we returned a full anſwer unto thy ſenceleſs ſtuff, and in plainneſs have we dealth with thee, and have not flattered thee at all there, call it not railing, leſt thou violate the Scriptures ſo with the word of truth thou art tryed, and comprehended, and us ſhalt thou witneſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, when the book of Conſcience comes to be opened, and thou judged out of it, ſo we remain,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Sufferers for the truth, and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt thee and thy generation. Named according to the fleſh,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>George Whitehead,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Chriſtopher Arkinſon,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>James Lancaſter,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Thomas Symonds.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="response">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61238:44"/>
                     <head>A Cutting Switch FOR THE <hi>Wounded Snake.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>I have uſed Similitudes, <bibl>
                              <hi>Hoſ. 12.10.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>READER,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>BY the Word Snake, which I uſe by way of Metaphor, (alluding to the <hi>Quakers</hi> obſcure way of Reaſoning, evermore hiding themſelves in the dark, by their Ambiguous and Doubtful Way of expreſſing themſelves in their Unintelligible Way of Writing) is what I call Quakeriſm; and having taken this Snake, <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> out of the Graſs, and laid her on the Table, and taken out her Sting, I am now coming to exerciſe my Switch, which I lately twiſted out of <hi>Joſ-Wyeth</hi>'s Hand, as <hi>David</hi> did the Sword out of the Hand of that uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtine, Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> which he deſign'd to wound the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with; for this <hi>Joſeph,</hi> like
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61238:45"/> blind <hi>Hob,</hi> playing at Blind-Man's-Buff, ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting every Man that paſſed by, without all Fear or Reſpect, being Fool hardy, I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to unarm him, and take his Weapon from him; for like <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Sword, <hi>there is none like it:</hi> And whereas this Water-Snake has ſwam over Sea, I am minded to ſend this Switch thither alſo, that ſo where-ever her Spawn is gone rattling up and down in other Nations, and Plantations, this Switch may purſue her, and deal ſeverely, or cuttingly, with her, for ſhe has done much Harm.</p>
                     <p>And now I ſhall tell what is the Cauſe of this Snake's Fury, which is, as on the Title Page of this Third Part, and where you may ſee ſhe put forth her Sting againſt Mr. <hi>Townſend;</hi> for that he, like other Chriſtian Champions, went to prove <hi>the Holy Scriptures to be the Word of God;</hi> for this the Rattle-Snake came out of his Thicket, and flung out his Deadly Poyſon at Mr. <hi>Townſend,</hi> thus, <hi>Iſhmael and his Mother caſt out among the Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. calling him a Dreamer, a Deceiver, a Witch, a Liar, a blind Guide, without Chriſt and his Knowledge, an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of God, an Antichriſt, a blind Sot, a ſottiſh blind Guide, ſhut up in perpetual Darkneſs, Blaſphemous Beaſt, as in <hi>P.</hi> 7, 8, 10, 14, 17, 25, 29. Thus, <hi>Reader,</hi> having ſhewed thee the Cauſe of the Dragon's Fury, and the Ground why he threw out his Floods of Malice againſt the Goſpel Miniſters, I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61238:45"/> ſhall next ſhew thee in ſhort a few Words to Confirm what I have ſaid, and that out of the Snake's own Mouth, as in <hi>P.</hi> 14, 17, 24. <hi>firſt, That the Scriptures are not the written Word of God, but a Rotten Foundation, not the Means to work Faith in the Heart:</hi> And becauſe Mr. <hi>Townſend,</hi> in Oppoſition to the <hi>Quakers</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Doctrine, had proved the Scriptures to be the written Word of God, and as ſuch, a good Foundation for our Faith in our Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and the Means to work Faith in our Hearts, which works by Love, Oh how did <hi>Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> and his Partners hiſs like Snakes, ſting like Adders, and roar like Dragons, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, as before noted, Dreamer, Deceiver, Witch, Liar, blind Guide, Enemy to God, Antichriſt, Sot, blind Sot, Blaſphemous Beaſt, ſhut up in perpetual Darkneſs, with other the like Virulent Railing, and Helliſh Malice! And this, Reader, is a Map of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Controverſie, between the Clergy and the <hi>Quakers,</hi> for with them the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are Death, Duſt, Carnal and Killing, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, a Rotten Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: For alas they have no need of the Scripture; with them the Holy Scriptures are needleſs, as I ſhall juſt now ſhew.</p>
                     <p>See <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi>'s Book, ſtiled, <hi>Some things relating to the Royal Society,</hi> &amp;c. p. 7. <hi>Now obſerve the Difference between the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which God hath taught us, and led us into, and the Religious of</hi> all Men upon the Earth <hi>beſides; our Religion ſtands wholly out of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61238:46"/> that, which all their Religions ſtands in; their Religion ſtands in the Comprehenſion, in a Belief of a Literal Relation or Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Religion ſtands in a Principle, which changeth the Mind, — where we hear the Voice, and ſee the expreſs Image of the Heavenly One,</hi> [i. e. God] <hi>and knows things not from an Outward Relation; yea, here</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we muſt profeſs, that we ſo know things, that we are fully ſatisfied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and could not doubt concerning them, tho' there had</hi> Never <hi>been</hi> Word <hi>or</hi> Letter <hi>written of them,</hi> &amp;c. And to this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the Doctrine of <hi>Edward Burroughs</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 17. and many other Places I could mention, but I ſtudy Brevity.</p>
                     <p>But, <hi>Reader,</hi> I have not done with this Snake, but muſt have the other Blow at her, and ſmite off her Head, leſt ſhe get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King's High Court of Parliament, and do miſchief, for ſhe is miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Beaſt, and full of deadly Poyſon, and begins to ſtink all the Nation over; and the Cauſe why I ſhall give this Mortal Wound to this Rattle Snake, which ſo often changes her Skin, while ſhe is the ſame, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to her Venomous Nature, that ſhe was at her firſt Riſe, <hi>Anno</hi> 1650. I ſay the Cauſe is this: Whereas Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> having proved the Scriptures to be (as indeed they are) the written Word of God, and a good Foundation for our Faith, and a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61238:46"/> great Means to work Faith in our Hearts; all which <hi>George Whitehead</hi> and his Partners oppoſed with great Vigor, he, Mr. <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend,</hi> having firſt proved theſe things, he then goes on to prove a Trinity of Three diſtinct Perſons in the Godhead, according to the Faith of all ſound Chriſtians; and for Proof thereof he does not only bring Scripture, but many ſtrong Reaſons, as well from Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as of later Date. To all which <hi>George Whitehead, &amp;c.</hi> from the Spirit of their Lord in them, as in <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>And here thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and thy Reaſons, and the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thou dreams of, which thou would divide out of one, like a Conjurer, are all denied, and thou ſhut up with them in perpetual Darkneſs, for the Lake, and the Pit,</hi> &amp;c. adding by way of Corroberation reſpecting Mr. <hi>Townſend,</hi> p. 26. thus: <hi>Thou</hi> (Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend) <hi>art Reſerved in Everlaſting Chains, under Darkneſs, for Everlaſting Fire,— ſhut out from God among the Dogs and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Having by this time not only diſcovered the Snake, but given her a deadly Blow, I ſhall next ſhew, that the <hi>Quakers,</hi> reſpecting their Principles, are the ſame that ever they were; only I am in Hopes they ſhall never do ſo much Hurt in a Hundred Years, as they have done in Fifty, the time of their date: The Sting of <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> being taken out, and the Bowels thereof ript up, and their Inſide turn'd Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61238:47"/> by many Infallible Proofs out of their Impious Books, eſpecially by Reprinting one of them; but let us not be too ſecure, leſt the deadly Wound which ſhe hath received ſhould be healed; and my Counſel is, that as Perſecution never did Good, ſo may it not be uſed amongſt Chriſtians; but yet a good Expedient is very proper, which is to have them examined, whether theſe things be ſo or no; and if what has been objected againſt them be proved upon them, let them be obliged to Retract and Condemn theſe their Ancient Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Heretical Books and Pamphlets, which have poyſoned many Thouſands of otherwiſe well-meaning People; and as this will be eaſie, ſo will it be one effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Means to ſtop the Gangrene of this Peſtilential Diſeaſe, and this will be no Perſecution.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="postscript">
                     <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                     <p>AND to ſhew that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the ſame ſtill, notwithſtanding their contrary Teſtimonies, I ſhall recite ſome few Paſſages out of their Writings, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">I. In their <hi>Yearly Epiſtle,</hi> 1696. <q rend="inline">We cannot <hi>(ſay they)</hi> but recommend unto you <hi>(our dear Brethren)</hi> the holding up the Holy Teſtimony of Truth, which hath made us to be a People, and that in all Parts of it<note n="*" place="margin">Then in Damning the Bleſſed Trinity.</note>, for Truth is one.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">II. <hi>The Quakers cleared,</hi> &amp;c. p. 7. <q rend="inline">God is the ſame, Truth is the ſame, his People the ſame, and their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples the ſame.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">III. Their <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1698. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <q rend="inline">Our Principles are now no other than what they were when we were firſt a People.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">IV. They have inſerted a long Paragraph in the <hi>Post-Man,</hi> Numb. 568. ſaying. <q rend="inline">The Quakers not queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but to acquit their Ancient Friends and their Writings, not being Conſcious of deviating in any one Point of Doctrine from what they firſt held<note n="†" place="margin">And what they held in <hi>1655. G. W.</hi>'s Book <hi>Iſhmael</hi> gives a Sample, for they are all of a Piece.</note>.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">V. But Jeſuit-like <hi>G. W.</hi> thus ſaith in his <hi>Count. Conv. p.</hi> 72. <q rend="inline">I may <hi>(ſays he)</hi> ſee Cauſe otherwiſe to word the Matter, and yet our Intentions be the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <div type="text">
                     <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61238:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>A Reply to a Book, Entituled,</hi> A Defence of an Apology for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> in Anſwer to a Book, Entituled, Quakeriſm Expos'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (wrote by <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi>) Or ſome Papers delivered to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament. PART III.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Have read and conſider'd this Book of <hi>John Field</hi>'s, <hi>A Defence,</hi> &amp;c. in Anſwer to the Books and Papers aforeſaid; but how far his Book anſwers his Titlte, will beſt be underſtood, by comparing both: For in <hi>J. Feild</hi>'s Book, of 32 Pages in Quarto, I find but 35 Lines of mine cited, which is not one Page of 64 of mine in Octavo, and that not pag'd, and thereby difficult for his Readers to find, in order to compare the Books; a right Trick of a Quaker. Now how this can rightly be call'd an Anſwer, is a Paradox to me; but however, an Anſwer they muſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61238:48"/> have, tho' nothing almoſt to the purpoſe, and then tell their poor Hearers <hi>Fr. Bugg</hi>'s Book is anſwered; Ay, that it is; nay, and repeatedly too, tho' I do not know of one ſingle Book of mine ſo anſwered by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> but that they have left untouched the greateſt Part of the Charges objected againſt them, and Six or Seven Books of mine never ſo much as pretended to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd. Oh the Polacy and Deceit of the Ringleaders of this Sect! And this has occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned me to give and take this Advice from a wiſe and prudent Caution, in a Book, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Miſſionaries Arts,</hi> &amp;c. wrote againſt the Jeſuits, Printed 1668. <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>viz. To diſtruſt every thing they ſay.</hi> For as the Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe of the Idolatry of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 282. very well obſerves, that they are as like, as if the <hi>Quakers</hi> and the Jeſuits were Children of one Father, and brought forth by one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, and Cage of every Unclean and Hateful Bird; His Words are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                        <q rend="inline">Any who compares them, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Jeſuits and <hi>Quakers</hi>) would imagine the Life of <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> had been their great Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar: I know not (ſaid the Biſhop) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of that Innocent and Religious. Order or Jeſuits had any Hand in forming this new Society (of <hi>Quakers</hi>) among us, (as hath been frequently ſuggeſted) but if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61238:48"/> one may gueſs the Father by the Child's Likeneſs, <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the Founder of the Jeſuits, was at leaſt the Grandfather of the <hi>Quakers, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </q> And as I do believe the recited Caution, <hi>To diſtruſt every thing they</hi> (i. e. Jeſuits) <hi>ſay,</hi> 'tis as applicable to the <hi>Quakers;</hi> and to demonſtrate this, let us but obſerve how frequent it is with them to blame their Opponents with ſplitting Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, mincing, mangling and curtailing, whilſt themſelves are ten times more guilty; for inſtance, I find a Paſſage in my Book, <hi>Quakeriſm Expos'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 27, 28. <q rend="inline">4thly, That you <hi>(Quakers)</hi> value the Scriptures above any Books in the World, <hi>This is falſe with a Witneſs,</hi> when you in Print tell us, we may as well burn the Bible as your Writings, <hi>Truths Defence, p.</hi> 2, 104. calling the Scriptures <hi>Duſt, Death, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Meat, Beaſtly Ware,</hi> and that Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of them is <hi>Conjuration.</hi> And <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> tells us in his Book, <hi>Truth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. p. 7. <hi>That what is ſpoken by the Spirit of Truth in any, is of as great Authority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and greater:</hi> And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your Books (nay, even that) are ſaid to be given forth from the Spirit of Truth, the Holy Ghoſt, and from the Mouth of the Lord; how then do you value the Scriptures above any Books in the World? But as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.3. <hi>A Whip for the Horſe, a Bridle for the Aſs, and a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61238:49"/> Rod for the Fool's Back:</hi> And ſo you muſt give me Leave to whip this <hi>J. Feild</hi> for his deep Hypocriſie and Deceit, and I wiſh it may do him Good; what! to pretend that the <hi>Quakers</hi> value the Bible above all Books, then conſequently above their own. This is ſuch a Lie, that it ſtabs it ſelf, when you exalt and value your own as of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Authority, and as ſuch, are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by your Teachers to read them in your Meetings, whilſt you never read, nor by your Teachers exhorted to read, one Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Old or New Teſtament in your Religious Meetings, (if ſuch I may call them) ſince you were a People; neither is it agreeable to your Ancient Teſtimony. Nay, farther I am fully perſwaded, That ſhould the Government think fit, for a Proof of your Sincerity herein, to enjoin you to read a Chapter of the Bible, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Meetings, (I mean, by ſuch of your Teachers as can read a Chapter, for many of them cannot) you would be ſo far from ſubmitting to Authority, that you'd firſt go to Jayl, and then call it Perſecution, and Record it as ſuch to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: But would it therefore ever the more be ſo? I trew not, ſince it was the Practice of the Jewiſh, as well as the Chriſtian Churches, in all Ages of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61238:49"/>
                     <p>Now in Anſwer to this long Paragraph, <hi>John Feild</hi> in his <hi>Defence, &amp;c.</hi> p. 7. <q rend="inline">This <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> ſaith is falſe with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo you muſt give me Leave to whip <hi>John Feild</hi> for his deep Hypocriſie and Deceit; what! to pretend that the <hi>Quakers</hi> value the Bible above all Books, then conſequently above their own, this is ſuch a Lie, that it ſtabs it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>This, <hi>Reader,</hi> is all he recites, neither does he go about to Refute my Reaſons for what I ſaid; nay, nor ſo much as mention them. How then can this be an Anſwer? Only he re-aſſerts in the ſame Page, ſaying, <hi>I do affirm that the Quakers always had, and ſtill have a high Eſteem, and true Value for the Holy Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. But this is his own bare <hi>Ipſe Dixit,</hi> without any Refutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of, or once reciting my Arguments for what I ſaid; and therefore this Tool, I am loth to ſay Fool, muſt yet be more ſcourged for his deep Deceit and Hypocriſie.</p>
                     <p>And therefore Chriſtian <hi>Reader,</hi> I beg of you to dwell a little here, and to conſider of the <hi>Quakers</hi> way of anſwering Books; you ſee my Charge, and how I proved it, both from Matter of Fact, and Demonſtration; <hi>firſt,</hi> They teach the Scriptures are Death, Duſt, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not a Word of it Deny'd or Refuted. Again, That Preaching out of them is Conjuration, not at all by him deny'd. Again, And that by <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s Doctrine, That their Sayings,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61238:50"/> from their Spirit of Truth, is of greater Authority than the Bible; not a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of it Deny'd or Refuted. Again, You hear they command their Diſciples to <hi>Read</hi> their <hi>Own Epiſtles</hi> in their Meetings for Divine Worſhip; not a Word of it deny'd or juſtified. Again, That they never, ſince they were firſt a People, did ſo much as read any one Chapter in the Bible in their Religious Meetings; which if they had ſuch an high Eſteem, and true Value for the Scriptures, even above theit own Books and Epiſtles, they ſurely would, or elſe they are very Hypocrites indeed, if they will not read, and recommend to be read in their Meetings, to their People, that which is beſt, moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd, and of higheſt Value, yet you ſee he cannot ſay that they do, or ever did read a Chapter in ſuch their Meetings. Now whether this Tool <hi>Feild</hi> does not deſerve to be ſeverely laſh'd, as well as his Tutor <hi>Geo. Whitehead,</hi> in this black Art, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge.</p>
                     <p>Thus much then as a Proof, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of their not citing the Subſtance of their Opponent's Poſition, but by picking Sentences, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in pieces, thereby marring the Senſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the <hi>Quakers</hi> are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſeveral things therein charged, elſe <hi>J. Field</hi> (who has a Fund to ſupport him in his Charge of Printing) would not ſo ſilently paſs by all thoſe ſeveral Charges, without a Vindication of his dear Friends;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61238:50"/> and this being a Figure of all their Anſwers, I ſhall paſs by many things of the like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and apply my ſelf next to their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>That</hi> being the beſt Flower in their Garden, and in which they moſt of all glory; much Good may it do them, ſince they bring moſt of it upon themſelves, by their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately adhering to their blind Guides and the Dictates of their Erroneous Conſciences, which has befaln them thorough their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Neglect of adhering to the Rule of the Sacred Word of God; I mean the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Holy Prophets and Apoſtles, and the Practice of the Primitive Saints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in all Ages. Again,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>A Brief Abſtract of ſome Sufferings of the People call'd</hi> Quakers, <hi>given to Confront</hi> Francis Bugg<hi>'s Diminutive Account,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reply,</hi> I find of late ſome Alteration in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Arrogant Stile touching them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it formerly was generally thus, <hi>The People of God called Quakers,</hi> or <hi>Some Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Elect People of God call'd Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> or from the People of the Lord call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> but now of late they are come a Step lower, <hi>viz. The People commonly call'd Quakers,</hi> or, <hi>The People call'd Quakers:</hi> I hope the Sermon I prepared for the <hi>Quakers</hi> (which I took out of their Writings, with no little Study and Pains) have done them ſome Good, ſee <hi>Pilg. Prog.</hi> p. 108, to 127. It was a long Sermon, I confeſs, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61238:51"/> it turn to a good Account, I think not my labour vain. But why is my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Sufferings diminutive? Were they not Sufferings? Yea, elſe they would not have recorded them; were they then not recoraed? Yea, I took them out of their Chronicle, and told them both Book and Page: Well, what then? Oh! but they were of the leaſt Size: No matter for that, if Sufferings, then Meritorious; elſe why were they ſo carefully Collected, and put in Order, even to a Row of Pins, a Child's Biggen, a Child's Double Clout, a Woman's Croſs-cloth, a Night-cap, a Dung-Fork, and the like; fit to be put into their Martyrology. But to deal plainly, I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the truth of them; and much more the truth of this Abſtract: For to me they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like <hi>Fox</hi>'s Miracles in his <hi>Journal,</hi> Publiſhed Thirty or Forty Years after they are ſaid to be wrought: And no Body can tell me where, not when, nor the Perſons Names Cured, or any Witneſſes to atteſt them. Even ſo are the Sufferings of this Abſtract. Nor is their one Juſtices Warrant cited; nor any formal Trial of any one of theſe Sufferers brought forth, to ſhew whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſuffered for the Name of Jeſus, or for Righteouſneſs ſake? Still, like <hi>Fox</hi>'s Miracles, never an one of which are ſaid to be wrought in the Name of Jeſus; but only in his own Name, and by his own Power; like <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> whom the <hi>Samaritans</hi>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61238:51"/> Adored, even as the Poor Infatuated Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Adore this <hi>Fox:</hi> They (the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi>) called him <hi>(Simon Magus)</hi> the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God; ſo do the Quakers call <hi>Fox;</hi> and that his Kingdom is Eſtabliſhed in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that of the increaſe thereof there is no End. And for theſe Reaſons, theſe Sufferings ought to be, even as <hi>Fox</hi>'s Miracles are (and thatby many of the Quakers too) rejected, and held as Fabulous as the Papiſts Legend. And now, as a further Demonſtration, that this Abſtract, with all its Appendices, ought to be rejected, and held as a Fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Story, I ſhall give Twelve Reaſons in order to <hi>Confront John Feild</hi>'s magnifying their Sufferings; which can be for no other Reaſon than for which they at firſt Record them; that is, Pride and Oſtentation. And my Reaſons ſhall be grounded upon ſuch a bottom, as all the Quakers that will ſee with their own Eyes, and read in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Books, muſt ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to; even upon that lying Spirit which has entred all their Inſpired Prophets. And if they can tell 12 Lies, they may tell 12000 Lies; and then what Credit is to be given either to the Miracles of <hi>Fox,</hi> or the Sufferings of the Quakers?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 1. In that they teach by their Books, That their Sufferings are <hi>greater,</hi> and more <hi>unjuſt,</hi> than the Sufferings in the Days of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, the Ten Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61238:52"/> or <hi>any</hi> time <hi>ſince. Burrough</hi>'s <hi>Works, p.</hi> 273.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 2. (That <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> one of their Wordy-windy Teachers, ſaid, and got it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, That he ſuffered Twenty Pound, when he did not ſuffer Twenty Farthings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 3. In that <hi>G. Fox,</hi> their Apoſtle, and High-Prieſt of their Profeſſion, ſaid, He was covered from the World; and that the World <hi>neither</hi> knew <hi>Him, nor his Name;</hi> when there was not Ten Men in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, whoſe Names were better known. See their Book, <hi>Several Petitions Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, p.</hi> 30.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 4. In that they teach, ſaying, <hi>HE that HATH the ſame Spirit that raiſed Jeſus from the Dead, is EQUAL with God.</hi> Saul<hi>'s Errand to</hi> Damaſscus, <hi>p.</hi> 8.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 5. In that they teach, That <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> was before Languages were. See the <hi>Introduct. to their Battledoor,</hi> in Folio.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 6. In that they teach, That the Thundering Voice anſwered <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> at his Trial in <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Aſſizes, as in <hi>p.</hi> 21. of his Book, (and which the Quakers have left out of his Journal) <hi>Saying, I have Glorified thee, and will Glorifie thee again: And immediately his Head and Ears was filled with Glory.</hi> Thus do they vye it with Chriſt, not only in ſaying their Sufferings are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than his, his Apoſtles, and all the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; but as there was a Voice from Heaven, from God the Father, ſpeaking to God the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61238:52"/> Son, or Second Perſon in the Trinity; ſaying, <hi>I have Glorifed thee, and will</hi> (after the ſtate of Humiliation was paſt) <hi>Glorifie thee again.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 7. In that <hi>Fox,</hi> your Apoſtle, ſaid, He ſaw a Pool of Blood, and a Channel of Blood, in the Town of <hi>Litchfield;</hi> when there was not a Drope of Blood, much leſs a Channel. See his <hi>Journal, p.</hi> 53. And the Young Prophets believe him, elſe they would not have Printed it after his Death in his <hi>Journal.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 8. In that <hi>William Mead,</hi> the great Quaker, told <hi>William Harris,</hi> That this <hi>Journal</hi> of <hi>Fox</hi> is a <hi>better</hi> Book than the <hi>Bible.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 9. In that <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſays, and the Quakers believe it, elſe they would not have Printed it in his <hi>Journal, p.</hi> 47. <hi>viz.</hi> That he ſaw the Heavens open, (as St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> did) nor that the Quakers had ſeen <hi>David</hi>'s Sepulchre, ſo many Thouſand Miles off <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Fox</hi> ſay they did. See <hi>Truth's Defence, alias,</hi> the Fountain of Lies and Blaſphemies.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 10. In that <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> teach, in his Book, <hi>Truth Defending the Quakers, p.</hi> 7. <hi>That what is now ſpoken from the Spirit of Truth in any,</hi> meaning the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) <hi>is of greater Authority than the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 11. In that Father <hi>Penn</hi> in Print Teach, (and whom <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61238:53"/> therein; <hi>Truth and Innocency Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 52.) <hi>That the Perſon that Suffered</hi> (at <hi>Jeruſalem) was properly the Son of God, we</hi> (Quakers, ſays he) <hi>utterly deny.</hi> See his <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 146.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 12. In that the Quakers teach, That the Name Jeſus and Chriſt belong to every Believer, as well as to the Head: See <hi>Pennington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtions to Profeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 27. When the Lie is ſo manifeſt, as that the Name Jeſus and Chriſt do not belong to <hi>Geo. Whitehead,</hi> nor <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> ſo well as it did belong to the Perſon that Suffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which the Quakers utterly deny to be the Son of God: And if not to them too, much leſs to the Quakers of a lower Form, whom yet they account Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; yea, the only Church of Chriſt: And that they may have full Tale, I'll give them a Baker's Dozen of Lies to <hi>confront</hi> their dubious and unintelligible Abſtract.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 13. They teach, Tht there is no Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation out of the true Church; and that the Quakers are this true Church: And alſo that in their Church there is no Tares, nor Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; See <hi>Joſiah Coal</hi>'s <hi>Whore unvailed,</hi> Firſt Impreſſion, <hi>p.</hi> 16, 18, 40, 41, 43. And <hi>R. Farnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s, <hi>A Rod to drive out the Wild Boars,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1655. <hi>p.</hi> 13. And to prove this a loud Lie, ſee the Cage of Unclean Birds, in my <hi>Pil. Prog. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 127, to 145.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LIE</hi> 14. The Quakers ſay, They are reſolved to Love their Enemeis, and Pray
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61238:53"/> for their Adverſaries; And for proof of this pretence, ſee <hi>John Feild</hi>'s <hi>Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 11, 19. Saying, <hi>I did not ſay, that</hi> Francis Bugg <hi>was like</hi> Judas, (Contradictory to the ſtream of the whole Gang) <hi>or that</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>and</hi> Judas <hi>his End might be his; for I pray God it may not — We are reſolved to love our Enemeis, Bleſs them that Curſe us, do Good to, and Pray for them that Perſecute us</hi> &amp;c. Oh! <hi>John,</hi> as this is contrary to thy Natural Temper, ſo it is to the Spirit of Quakeriſm; elſe you are changed, and not the ſame that ever you were. No, <hi>John,</hi> I take this as a Piece of Flattery, a ſudden Mood, a Fit that will over, and be gone preſently. Nay, <hi>John</hi> is yet more kind, (for I'll give the Devil his due) <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>ibid. I am perſuaded</hi> (the Quakers) <hi>never deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> (Fran. Bugg) <hi>any harm:</hi> O! <hi>John,</hi> I ſee thy Cloven Foot; and will keep out of harms way as near as I can; and therefore D. do thy worſt,</p>
                     <p>But to prove this a Lie, ſpoken in Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, to gloſ over their Malicious Spirit, which is the moſt revengeful of the Seven Evil Spirtis which poſſeſſes the Leaders of this Sect; and which is as contrary to their Ancient Principles as Light is contrary to Darkneſs; ſee their great Apoſtle <hi>Fox's</hi> Book, <hi>Truth's Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 15. who writing againſt <hi>Comelfeild</hi> a Miniſter, and being unwilling to unboſome himſelf at that time (a fault they are ſeldom guilty of)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61238:54"/> gave him this aſſurance, touching praying for their Enemies, <hi>viz. No Prayers can we ſend to thee, but for thy Deſtruction, thou Man of Sin, and Enemy of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. This is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Ancient Principles; and ſhall I think they are changed? No, not a tittle; they tell us ſo: And they do not only Pray for the Deſtruction of their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as you have heard; but if their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours do not pleaſe them to a Hair's Breadth, they'll not mention them in their Prayers to their God; (no matter indeed whether they do or no, for the late King <hi>James</hi> II. for whom they moſ Prayed, his Reign was the ſhorteſt Liv'd) for <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> whom they often ſaluted with their Familiar Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation of Dear Friend, Noble <hi>Oliver,</hi> and the like Flatteries; yet becauſe he turned them out of the Army, and would nto ſuffer them to be Juſtices of the Peace forſooth, Thee and Thou, by Yea and Nay, grew angry and pettiſh, and would no more mention him in their Prayers to God, than now they do his preſent Majeſty; as may be ſeen by <hi>Edward Burrough</hi>'s Book in Quarto, Printed 1656. <hi>Good Counſel and Advice rejected,</hi> p. 15. <hi>And theſe things are not right, that ſuch who have been Faithful in their Truſt for many Years, and hazarded Life and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for Conſcience ſake, which they cannot now Poſſeſs; but are caſt out for the exerciſe of their pure Conſciences; conſider of it, when ſuch are caſt out of their Places,</hi>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61238:54"/> p. 16. <hi>of Judicatories in thy Government, and out of thy Armies; for I know the Lord hath Curſed them</hi> (the King and Royal Party) <hi>and thou haſt had Dominion given thee of God to break them in Pieces: And what thou haſt done their King,</hi> (i. e. <hi>King</hi> Charles II.) <hi>ſhould not be reckoned againſt thee by the Lord, if thou art Faithful to what he requires of thee</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">By the Quaker Prophets, then they would Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the Murther.</note> p. 20. <hi>Though we the People of God, do not Envy thy Perſon nor Government; — Yet, Friend, the want of our Prayers to God for thee, is worſe to thee than all the Plotting of all wicked Men: And how can we mention</hi>
                        <note n="†" place="margin">Nor do they ever mention K. <hi>Will.</hi> III. in their Prayers.</note> 
                        <hi>thee in our Prayers to God for thee, except it be to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from thee,</hi> &amp;c. Here is then no Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (or what is Equivolent) no <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> for either Prieſt or Governours. See <hi>Pil. Prog. p.</hi> 78. for more of this. And that they valued themſelves as Members of the Army, ſee their Book ſtiled, <hi>A Diſpute with the Teachers</hi> of Cheſterfeild, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed 1655. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <q rend="inline">It is known (ſay they) that moſt of us have adventured Life and Eſtate for the preſent Power (or Government);</q> and and at that Day their Cry ran ſtrong againſt the Clergy and the King; ſee their Book, <hi>News coming out of the North, p.</hi> 19. <q rend="inline">So you (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Prieſts) muſt be cut down with the ſame Power that cut down the King (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Sword) who Reigned over the Nation, whoſe Family was a Nurſery for the Papiſts and Biſhops: But
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61238:55"/> the Beaſt (that is, the Government and the falſe Prophets (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Prieſthood) is ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill. — The <hi>ſame</hi> Teachers are ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill, that was in the time of the King and Biſhops. <hi>p.</hi> 31. Slay <hi>Beal, Balaam</hi> muſt be Slain, all the Hirelings muſt be turned out of the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q> Now I would ask this Knotty Queſtion of <hi>John Feild,</hi> and his Tutor <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> Whether this was not raiſing the <hi>Monſter Perſecution?</hi> And do deſire them not to paſs ſilently over it, as they do moſt of the Charge Objected againſt them; but in all Friendlineſs deſire their Anſwer by Yea, or by Nay.</p>
                     <p>But I cannot forget <hi>John Feild</hi>'s ſmooth pretence; That the Poor Quakers think or deſign me no Harm, but Pray for me; and do not mean to compare me to <hi>Judas;</hi> no, by no means; though it be their Common Text, when they are not able otherwiſe to anſwer me: And for a proof thereof, ſee their Book, <hi>A Defence of the People called Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>John Fiddiman, Rich. Aſhly,</hi> and four more; where, on the Title Page they thus ſay,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And</hi> Judas Iſcariot, <hi>one of the Twelve, went unto the Chief Prieſts to betray him unto them:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And when they heard it, they were glad, and Promiſed to give him Money; and he ſought how he might conveniently betray him,</hi> Mark. 14.10, 11.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61238:55"/>
                     <p>Ay; but ſays <hi>John Feild</hi> in his <hi>Defence of his Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <q rend="inline">But I did not ſay that <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> was like <hi>Judas,</hi> or that <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi>'s End might be like his, for I pray God it may not; I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the <hi>Quakers</hi> never deſigned him any Harm. <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. 'We are reſolved to Love our Enemies.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>And yet the very ſame <hi>J. Feild</hi> hath this Paſſage himſelf in his Epiſtle to the Reader, i. e. <hi>And when Satan entred into</hi> Judas, <hi>he went his way, and communed with the Chief Prieſts and Captains how he might betray him; and they were glad, and covenanted to give him Money.</hi> Thus then, tho' not ſo broad-fac'd as the former, yet it is their common Theme or Text, That any one who oppoſes and diſcovers their Errours, is <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> and themſelves <hi>Jeſus;</hi> eſpecially when they know not otherwiſe how to defend themſelves. But tho' they pretend to be all of one Mind and Judgment, and to give forth their Books from the Spirit, or Light within, yet as harmonious as Harp and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and agree in concord as Light with Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For, ſays <hi>Fiddeman</hi> and <hi>Aſhby, &amp;c.</hi> p. 1. <hi>And the Prieſts Mercenary Agent</hi> Bugg; again, <hi>p.</hi> 21. Francis Bugg <hi>their Mercenary Agent.</hi> Now as this agrees with the two Verſes in the Title-Page, and do ſhew they meant <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> to be <hi>Judas;</hi> yet ſmooth. <hi>J. Feild</hi> he denies any ſuch Deiſign, he loves me, and prays for me, as if he were as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61238:56"/> real a Chriſtian as he is a <hi>Quaker.</hi> But to make it yet more plain, if more can be, ſee their <hi>Letter to the Clergy,</hi> &amp;c. which the <hi>Quakers</hi> printed under the Sham-Name of a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Publiſhed many Thouſands of them. Nay, ſo fond they were of it, that they read it in their Meetings in ſome Places. Oh! an Excellent Epiſtle, and which in my ſmall Tract, intituled, <hi>The Chriſtian Miniſtry of the Church of</hi> England <hi>Vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. I have ſo replied to it, as ſince I have heard no News of it. Well, but let us hear whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by them two Texts on their Title-Page, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.10, 11. they do not mean <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> as <hi>John Feild</hi> pretends.</p>
                     <p>A Letter to the Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 6. <hi>The High Prieſts had a</hi> Judas <hi>at Work for Money, to betray Chriſt into their Hands for Money. Have not you a</hi> Judas <hi>at Work now for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? Pray where is the difference between theſe two Traytors? Why the difference is twofold; the firſt was a</hi> Judas, <hi>the latter a</hi> Bugg. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Judas <hi>had thirty Pieces of Silver, which was paid by the High Prieſts; the latter had his Money, not only from the High Prieſts, but a Recommendation alſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I am the larger herein, to ſhew <hi>John Feild</hi> the Nature of this Beaſt that carries their Bell, and how it ſuits with the Spirit of <hi>Quakeriſm:</hi> Only this Defence being deſigned for the Hands of ſome Perſons which he thought might reſent it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61238:56"/> he is now for not calling <hi>F. B.</hi> Judas; no, by no means; but for Praying for him: Which being rightly interpreted, is as <hi>Fox</hi> Prayed for the Prieſts, namely, for my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: But I thank God, I fear not their Curſes, nor regard their Phariſaical Prayers: And this being as great a Lie as moſt of the other, I ſhall therewithal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Head, thereby <hi>confronting John Feild</hi>'s Abſtract of Sufferings.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>J. Feild</hi> proceeds in his <hi>Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now if he prove that thoſe Miniſters of that Age, who entred into a Solemn League and Covenant againſt Prelacy, Kingly Office, Houſe of Lords,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were God's Heritage,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reply.</hi> I grant, that if any of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry did ſo, (for he names none) they were ſo far in the wrong; yet with this difference, The <hi>Quakers</hi> in thoſe Days did thus much, and much more, and that as Prophets of the moſt High God, and they tell us they are ſtill the ſame, Print and Reprint their Books which ſo teach. But the Publick Miniſters, if any ſuch did ſo, they did not pretend they were led therunto by the Eternal Spirit, that they are the ſame ſtill, and their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples now no other than they were then: They now are obedient to the King's Laws, they have by their joining in the Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, declared him Rightful and Lawful King, they Pray for him in their Aſſemblies: But the <hi>Quakers</hi> have in their Books of Divine Authority, as they boaſt, Anathematiz'd all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61238:57"/> Kings ſince the Days of the Apoſtles, as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and Spiritual <hi>Egyptians:</hi> That a Parliament choſen by the moſt Voices, were not like to act for God, or the Good of his People: And they tell us they are the ſame ſtill, only they word the Matter other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                     <p>I grant the Diſſenters then were againſt the Biſhops, yet not like the <hi>Quakers;</hi> for, in their Declaration recited by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they were for preſerving their Perſons from all Violence and Injuries, and for Liberty of Conſcience, tho' with ſome Reſtriction: But the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as in <hi>Burrough</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 618. and in <hi>R. Hubberthorn</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 229. aſſaulted this Declaration, ſaying; <hi>What are you about to make a League and Covenant with Antichriſt? Do you look upon them (i. e.</hi> the Clergy) <hi>to be Miniſters of Chriſt, or of Antichriſt? What are you now for tolerating Epiſcopacy? And if Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, why may not Popery be tolerated, and the like?</hi> No, nothing but Blood, and Slaughter, Baniſhment, and the utter Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of the Clergy, would ſatisfie their blood-thirſty and malicious perſecuting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: As in <hi>Fox</hi>'s Book ſtilled, <hi>New coming up out of the North,</hi> p. 31. <hi>So you muſt be cut down with the ſame Power that cut down the King, whoſe Family was a Nurſery for Papiſts and Biſhops; the ſame Teachers are ſtanding that were in the time of the King, and the ſame that were in the time of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61238:57"/> Biſhops. — Sound the Trumpet, ſound an Alarm; call up to the Battel, gather together for the Deſtruction, draw the Sword, hew down all fruitleſs Trees which cumber the Ground, cleanſe the Land from Filthineſs,</hi> ſlay <hi>Baal, Balaam</hi> muſt <hi>be</hi> ſlain; <hi>all the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> muſt be <hi>turned</hi> out <hi>of the</hi> Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Time, but you tell us you are the ſame ſtill, and your Actions manifeſt the ſame. For tho' you held in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Time a Mock-Court, wherein you Tried all the Clergy, and Condemned them; yet when in 1672. you reprinted the Works of your Prophet <hi>Burrough,</hi> you revived your Trial, and reprinted the ſame, as in <hi>pag.</hi> 223. Viz. <hi>A Juſt and Lawful Trial of the Teachers and Miniſters of this Age,</hi> (1672.) <hi>by a perfect Proceeding againſt them; and they are righteouſly Examined, juſtly Weighed, truly Meaſured, and Condemned, to be contrary to all the Miniſters of Chriſt in former Ages, and to agree and concur with all the falſe. Prophets and Deceivers; and being brought to the</hi> [Quakers] <hi>Bar of Juſtice, theſe Things are truly charged, and legally proved upon them, and found Guilty,</hi> &amp;c. I need not add the Trial,<note place="margin">And yet <hi>G. W.</hi> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> he was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> skilled i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Law-terms, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> more Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> he.</note> the Title of the Book ſetting forth the <hi>Quakers</hi> Verdict (where my Lob Chief Juſtice <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> the <hi>Quaker-Prophet,</hi> was both Judge, Witneſs, Jury and Executioner) is enough to ſet forth their preſumptuous, unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, arbitrary, and extrajudicial Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61238:58"/> not only againſt 12, but 1200 Perſons. And that it may further appear, that tho' this <hi>Quaker-Court</hi> was firſt erected (to ſhew what they would be at, had they Power) in <hi>O. Cromwell</hi>'s Time; yet in 1672, they to ſet forth his Skill in Law-Terms, reprinting the ſame Trial as a Monument of his Righteous Judgment; and that he might make Work on't to ſome purpoſe, in <hi>p.</hi> 273. he joined with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and all the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Heathen Emperours, againſt Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs; ſaying, <hi>That the Sufferings of the</hi> Quakers <hi>were greater, and more unjuſt than the Sufferings of Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs,</hi> &amp;c. But ſtill, as one Demonſtration more (though I could give twenty) that it was not the Miniſters in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Time only that the <hi>Quakers</hi> thus Arraigned, Judged, and Condemned, as <hi>John Feild</hi> would inſinuate, but alſo King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second his Reign; ſee <hi>W. Smith,</hi> another of their Preachers, in his Works printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1668, <hi>p.</hi> 161. viz. <hi>A General Summons from the Authority of Truth, to all Eccleſiaſtical Courts and Officers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>By which we may ſee their arrogant Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thus to Summons, Judge, Try, and Condemn, not only the Clergy, but all Courts Eccleſiaſtical and Officers; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they were Diſſenters, a poor illiterate People, that as <hi>Burroughs</hi> tells us, (in his Epiſtle to <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Myſtery</hi>) they lay in Barns (like Gypſies:) See then the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61238:58"/> of theſe Proud, Pragmatical <hi>Quaker-Prophets.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In my Book <hi>Quakeriſm Expoſed,</hi> &amp;c. there is this Paſſage, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <q rend="inline">Now tho' I profeſs my ſelf a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I have often, and do now again tell you, that I am againſt Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and will add, That Perſecution for the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> or for Righteouſneſs ſake, is a Badge of a falſe Church; of which your Schiſm in <hi>Penſilvania</hi> has given a Demonſtration; and had you Power in your Hand, (which God grant you may not) I doubt not but we ſhould ſoon feel your Little Finger as heavy as ever you felt the Parliament's Loins; witneſs your Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me in the <hi>Old Bailey,</hi> your Perſecuting G. <hi>Keith:</hi> But I hope all Suffering is not Perſecution. Shall Men Fire Houſes, and Poyſon Rivers, and not be controll'd, limited, nay, puniſhed, if they will follow their own Light, blind Zeal and Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? In like manner, ſuch as poyſon the Streams of the Chriſtian Religion, ſubvert the Faith, undermine Chriſtianity, broach and maintain damnable Errours, denying the Lord that bought them, as you have done; I hope then it is not raiſing Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, to have you Examined, and your Errours cenſured; which is the main thing you fear, whilſt you would make the World believe you fear Perſecution.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61238:59"/>
                     <p>In anſwer to this, <hi>John Feild,</hi> in his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 3. recites thus much, <hi>viz. I do profeſs my ſelf a Member of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>I have often, and do again tell you that I am againſt Perſecution; and will add, That Perſecution for Righteouſneſs ſake, is a Badge of a Falſe Church,</hi> &amp;c. But theſe Words (with many others, as by comparing you may ſee) <hi>for the Name of</hi> Jeſus he has dropt, as not for his turn. And in this, tho' <hi>John Feild</hi> was a Tool, yet he was no Fool; for he knew very well, that no <hi>Quakers</hi> ever ſuffered in <hi>England for the Name of</hi> Jeſus: Neither was there (in their time) ever known, that an Act Parliament was made, or a Juſtice's Warrant ever ſigned, to perſecute any Man <hi>for the Name of</hi> Jeſus. And I now anew do declare, That I am againſt Perſecution, and do refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to my Book, <hi>The Picture of</hi> Quakeriſm <hi>drawn to the Life,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 73, to 125. for my Judgment in that Caſe.</p>
                     <p>But there is one Paſſage I may not let ſlip in <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Truth and Innocency Vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. p. 44. <hi>Such Records are not intended to make the Governors nor Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment odious for Perſecution to Poſterity. — Neither do I know of any among us, that have ſo threatned to publiſh to After-ages,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reply.</hi> But Ah, <hi>George,</hi> what is become of thy Sincerity, that canſt thus Lie in the Face of the Government? What doſt not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61238:59"/> thou know <hi>W. Penn?</hi> Is he not ſtill among you? And tho' others be dead, yet their Books are ſtill among you. I am now turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee upſide down, even thy Inſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; therefore hold up thy Chin and draw near me, that I may take off thy Mask of Sincerity, and ſhew thy foul Inſide. Read the <hi>Picture of</hi> Quakeriſm, <hi>p.</hi> 102, 103. where divers of your Books are quoted, that do ſo threaten; particularly, <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s Judas <hi>and the</hi> Jews. <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 41. <hi>Our faithful Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of the Bloody Tragedies of that Profeſſing Generation will tell future Ages other things.</hi> Now, <hi>George,</hi> is not this a Threat? Yes ſure. Only <hi>Sam. Cater</hi>'s, and other Sham-Sufferings, are diſcovered, which will deſpoil your Chronicle. Again, in his <hi>Rejoinder, p.</hi> 410. <hi>New Provocations</hi> (ſays <hi>Penn) may give freſh occaſion for their Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory to come abroad to the Nation more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly than ever.</hi> See alſo R. <hi>Barkley</hi>'s <hi>Anarchy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>That as thro' our Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Teſtimony in the Hand of the Lord, that Antichriſtian and Apoſtatized Generation, the National Miniſtry, hath received a deadly Blow, by our diſcovering and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt their forced Maintenance and</hi> Tythes, <hi>againſt which we have teſtified by many cruel Sufferings, of all kinds, as our Chronicles ſhall make known to Generations to come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>What <hi>George,</hi> is here no Threatning? Doſt thou indeed ſay thou knoweſt of none
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61238:60"/> among you that have an intent to publiſh your Sufferings, to render the Government odious for Perſecution? This is ſuch a Lie, that it will wound the Author. And ſo I turn to <hi>John Feild</hi> again.</p>
                     <p>In my Book, <hi>Quakeriſm Expoſed,</hi> &amp;c. there is this Paſſage, <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>But this your Shuffle ſhewed the Gentry, Juſtices of Peace, the Clergy and Proteſtant Diſſenters, That your Principles are ſo deſtructive to Common Chriſtianity, as that you did not dare to ſtand the Teſt: And this, yea, on this, yea,</hi> only <hi>this, ſo far as I know, put them upon a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to do that for God and the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which they could not do; namely, to Examine your Principles, and Cenſure your Errours, as to their Wiſdom ſhould ſeem meet: And in this, they</hi> (i. e. <hi>both the Church of</hi> England <hi>Men and Proteſtant Diſſenters) are unanimous; and this diſturbs you, this perplexes you; and for this your Tool</hi> John Feild <hi>calls and compares them to</hi> Herod <hi>and</hi> Pilate, Haman <hi>and</hi> Judas.</p>
                     <p>Upon this, <hi>John Feild</hi> by way of Prayer, replies, <hi>Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Pray let</hi> Fra. Bugg, <hi>who aſſerts this, make it appear to the King and both Houſes of Parliament, that this, yea, only this, put them upon it, and that they are unanimous herein: For if ſo, there is not one of theſe Sorts, but what is conſenting thereto, or hath been actually concerned in the Petition. But if it hath not been ſo,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61238:60"/> then the Parliament may be hereby informed, That he hath not truly repreſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> (i. e. <hi>the Parliament;) for they are included in his general Words: And let him tell if he can, what that common Chriſtianity is, that the</hi> Quakers <hi>Principles are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Well, <hi>John,</hi> I have hear'd thy Prayer, and <hi>G. W.</hi>'s <hi>Iſhmael</hi> herewith reprinted, do tell you, (if what I have hitherto does not) what that common Chriſtianity is which your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are deſtructive to, and in a great part ſhew the Cauſe of your Shuffle; in that you did not dare to own your Books, and either defend or retract your Blaſphemous and Seditious Principles; together with many other Reaſons in my ſaid Book, <hi>Qua. Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> &amp;c. to which I refer the Reader. Nor doth it follow from what I therein ſaid, that every individual Man of all ſorts was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Petition; nor that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was at all concerned. What, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Petition the Parliament? No, <hi>John,</hi> this is a Quibble, which hath no Ground in any Field, but ſuch that bring forth nothing but Thorns or Thiſtles.</p>
                     <p>But, <hi>John,</hi> here is more in this Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion than every body on firſt ſight will be aware of. For what is it leſs, than to tell all the Counties, Shires, Cities and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> that their Repreſentatives are ſuch Friends to your Errours; that they are not unanimous in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61238:61"/> and with their Electors, as to have you exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined about them. And not only ſo, but the Proteſtant Churches abroad, who are Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized by your pernicious Errours; if you be (as your ſelves boaſt) Recognized Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. And this, <hi>John,</hi> I take to be Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant Parliament, who profeſs Faith in our Lord Jeſus, which you teſtifie was not the Son of God; which is a Damnable Errour, denying the Lord that bought you with the Price of his moſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood, if you would accept thereof on Goſpel-Terms.</p>
                     <p>And from this Scandal there needs be no other Vindication, than the Good and Chriſtian Laws already made, and their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Votes in Parliament, and the Humble Addreſs made to the King's Majeſty, in the Year 1697. which not only gave me Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Charge and Challenge you; and when you threw that off, and Challenged the Clergy, it likewiſe incouraged them to Charge you: And when you ſhuffled and evaded their Charge, it gave them Encouragement for the Petition, that they might Examine you; an Abſtract thereof is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                        <body>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61238:61"/>
                           <head>The Humble Addreſs of the Houſe of Commons to the KING.</head>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty.</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>WE your Majeſties moſt Dutiful and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Commons in Parliament Aſſembled, do, with great Joy and Comfort, remember, the many Teſtimonies which your Majeſty hath given us of your Sincerity and Zeal for the true Reformed Religion, as eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom, and in particular we beg leave to preſent to your Majeſty our moſt Humble and Thankful Acknowledgments for the late Gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration your Majeſty has made to us from the Throne, that you would effectually diſcourage Prophaneneſs and Immorality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>— We do further, in all Humility, beſeech your Majeſty, that your Majeſty would give ſuch effectual Orders, as to your Royal Wiſdom ſhall ſeem fit, for the ſuppreſſing all Pernicious Books and Pamphlets, which contain in them Impious Doctrine againſt the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and other Fundamental Articles of our Faith, tending to the Subverſion of the Chriſtian Religion, and that the Authors and Publiſhers thereof may be Diſcountenanced and Puniſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>And to the end that the Quakers may ſee the Zeal of our Government, againſt the Errors contained in their Books; and not to preſume to Diſcourſe as they do; as if they, and they only, were the White Hen's Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens and the only Favourites, as I can give parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Demonſtrations, both by what I have heard with my Ears from ſome of their Young Diſciples, (who, as the Old Cocks Crow, the Young ones Learn) as well as I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61238:62"/> from Credible Information, I ſhall recite His Majeſties moſt Gracious Anſwer to the foregoing Addreſs, which is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="response">
                        <body>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I</hi> Cannot but be very well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an Addreſs of this Nature; and I will give immediate Directions in the ſeveral Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars you deſire: But I could wiſh ſome more Effectual Proviſion were made for the ſuppreſſing thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Books and Pamphlets which your Addreſs takes notice of.</p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>By this time the Quakers thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerned, being Conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (as well they might) that no People in the King's Dominion, no, not the Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gletonians, were ſo obnoxious to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the King and Parliament, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Upon which they beſtirred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, like the Magicians in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s time, to bring forth a likeneſs: And therefore when there was a Bill Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, they Printed a Paper, and preſented it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61238:62"/> to the Houſe of Commons by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; in which there were theſe Words, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>WHereas the Bill enacts, That if any Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall deny any of the Perſons in the Holy Trinity to be God, and make it puniſhable by the ſame Bill, were it not more ſafe and plain to put it in Scripture Terms, as inſtead of <hi>Deny any one of the Perſons to be God,</hi> to inſert, <hi>If any one ſhall deny any of the Three, that bear Record in Heaven,</hi> the Father, the Word, or the Holy Ghoſt to be God? 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7.</q>
                     <p>Now if the Quakers can but bend the Parliament to their Bow, then they'll agree; (but as for them, they cannot condeſcend a Hair's Breadth, as one of their Teachers, <hi>Patrick Livingſton,</hi> formerly Taught). For, ſay they, <hi>The Father is Light, the Son is Light, and the Holy Ghoſt is Light:</hi> Nay, if they deſire three or four Perſons more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as that the Door is Light, the Elect Stone is Light, the Vine is Light, the Blood is Light, the Water is Light, they'll al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all; and all theſe are One, no one of which was before or after the other; nor one greater or leſſer than another; and yet all this while they mean not a Word accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures, and the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of all Sound Chriſtians, but Reduce all to their Light <hi>within.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But ſtill fearing what might happen, and to guard their Errors, they ſoon preſented His Majeſty with a Paper; and this put
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61238:63"/> me upon undergoing the Charge of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing one of their Books intirely, that ſo I may ſet them in their True Light, to be ſeen and read of all Men: And as it is my Duty, ſo by my Reaſonable Service to God and my Country; though by ſome my Words may be deſpiſed, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.16. A Copy of the Quakers Paper is as followeth. <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                        <body>
                           <head>To King <hi>William III.</hi> over <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. The Grateful Acknowledgment of the People Commonly called Quakers, Humbly Preſented.</head>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>May it pleaſe the King.</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>SEeing the moſt High God, who rules in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Men<note n="*" place="margin">
                                 <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.21.</note>, and appointeth over it whomſoever he will, hath by his over-ruling Power and Providence, placed thee in Dominion and Dignity over theſe Realms, and by his Divine Favour has ſignally preſerved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered thee from many Great and Eminent Dangers, and Graciouſly turned the Calamity of War into the deſired Mercy of Peace, we heartily wiſh that we, and all others concerned, may be truly Senſible, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Thankful to Almighty God for the ſame, that the Peace may be laſting, and a perpetual Bleſſing.</p>
                           <p>And now, O King, the God of Peace having return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee in Safety, it is Cauſe of Joy to all them that fear him, to hear thy good and ſeaſonable Reſolution, effectually to diſcourage Prophaneneſs and Immorality, Righteouſneſs being that which exalteth a Nation. And as the King has been <hi>Tenderly</hi> Inclined to give Eaſe and Liberty of Conſcience to his Subjects of different Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, (of whoſe Favour we have largely partaken) ſo we eſteem it our Duty Gratefully to Commemorate,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61238:63"/> and Acknowledge the ſame, earneſtly beſeeching Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to aſſiſt the King, to proſecute and effect theſe his juſt and good Inclinations, that his Days may be Happy and Peaceable, and hereafter he may partake of a laſting Kingdom that will never fade away.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>London, <date>
                                    <hi>the</hi> 7th <hi>of the</hi> 11th <hi>Month,</hi> 1697.</date>
                              </dateline>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Signed in Behalf of the ſaid People, by us,</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>George Whitehead</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Peter Bowen</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Will. Mead</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Gilbert Layty</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John. Edge</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Daniel Quane</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Tim. Emmerſon</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Thomas Hawes</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Samuel Jobſon</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Theod. Eccleſton</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Nicholas Gates</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Will. Ingram</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Will. Onkingate</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Thomas Lower</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John Paine</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John Butcher</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Will. Macket</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Rich. Needham</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John Vaughton</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John Hound</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Michael Ruſſel</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Jof. Wilkinſon</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Joſeph Wyeth</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>John Hall</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Joſiah Ellis.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>Now by this fair and ſmooth Paper, who would think but the Quakers would have Signed the Aſſociation, purſuant to the Act of Parliament; Intituled, <hi>An Act for the better Security of His Majeſties Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Government,</hi> &amp;c. Oh! no, by no means: For they tell you in their Paper, Intituled, <hi>The Ancient Teſtimony and Principle of the People called Quakers Renewed, with reſpect to the King and Government; and touching the preſent Aſſociation,</hi> Dated the 23d of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61238:64"/> 
                        <hi>March</hi> 1695/6 <hi>viz.</hi> 
                        <q rend="inline">And whereas we the ſaid People are required to ſign the ſaid Aſſociation; we ſincerely declare, That our refuſing ſo to do, is not out of any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction to the King and Government; nor in Oppoſition to his being declared <hi>Rightful,</hi> and <hi>Lawful</hi> King of theſe Realms; but purely becauſe we cannot for Conſcience ſake, Fight, Kill, or Revenge, either for our ſelves or any Man elſe.</q> Oh! no, by no means, this they could not be brought to; and the Riddle I have unfolded in my <hi>Pil. Prog.</hi> &amp;c. 2d <hi>Edition, p.</hi> 192, to 199. For as they yet never made one Publick Ad, dreſs to His Majeſty from thir Yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that great and dangerous Body; nor one Prayer, that I could ever hear of, either in their Books or in their Meetings; nor ever yet wrote one Book in Favour of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: But did all theſe in the late Reign. But ſtill there is one Clauſe in this Paper worth Notice, <hi>i. e.</hi> '<hi>As the King has been tenderly inclined to give Eaſe and Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. And I pray is it inconſiſtant with His Majeſties Tenderneſs to give Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience to His Proteſtant Diſſenters, who hold the Fundamentals of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, joined in the Aſſociation to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Majeſties Royal Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: And Pray heartily for him in their Meetings. And to Curb and Reſtrain ſuch as will doneither; but hold ſuch horrid Pernicious and Deſtructive Principles, both to Church and State, and even to Humane
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61238:64"/> Society? No ſure, God hath given him both Wiſdom and Conduct; and he knows how to make a difference, and diſtinguſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch as Subvert the Faith, undermine Chriſtianity, and Damn the Ever-Bleſſed Trinity to the Pit of Hell; and ſuch who make it their Buſineſs to Inſtruct their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity; as is well expreſſed in divers Laws, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in that wherein is this Clauſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Provided, and be it enacted, That no Quaker, or Reputed Quaker, ſhall by Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Act, be qualified or permitted to give Evidence on any Criminal Cauſes to Serve on any Juries, or bear any Office or Place of</hi> [Truſt or] <hi>Profit, in the Government; any thing in this Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the contrary; in any wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>And for this Clauſe all true Proteſtants have good cauſe to be Humbly thankful to God, the King and the Parliament; and that for more Reaſons than I think meet here to enumerate.</p>
                     <p>But notwithſtanding the Quakers Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Paper above recited, the King's Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty as a Nurſing-Father to the Church, and Spouſe of Chriſt; and as a Zealous Defender of the Faith, once delivered to the Saints, put forth his Royal Proclamation from his Court at <hi>Kenſington,</hi> the 24th of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1697.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61238:65"/> which we have read both at Church and Courts of Judicature: An Abſtract thereof is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proclamation">
                        <body>
                           <head>By the KING, <hi>A PROCLAMATION.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <opener>
                              <signed>WILLIAM REX.</signed>
                           </opener>
                           <p>WHereas we cannot but be deeply ſenſible of the great Goodneſs of Almighty God, in putting an end to a Long, Bloody, and Expenſive War, by the Concluſion of an Honourable Peace, ſo we are not leſs touched with a Reſentment, that notwithſtanding this, and many other great Bleſſings and Deliverances, Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Prophaneneſs, and Immorality, do ſtill abound in this our Kingdom; and whereas nothing can prove a greater Diſhonour to a well-ordered Government, where the Chriſtian Faith is profeſſed, nor is likelier to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God to withdraw his Mercy and Bleſſings from us, and inſtead thereof, to inflict Heavy and Severe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon this Kingdom, than the open and avowed Practice of Vice, Immorality, and Prophaneneſs, which amongſt many Men has too much prevailed in this our Kingdom of late Years, to the high Diſpleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the great Scandal of Chriſtianity, and the ill and fatal Example of the reſt of our loving Subjects, who have been ſoberly Educated, and whoſe Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would lead them to the Exerciſe of Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, did they not daily find ſuch frequent and repeated Inſtances of diſſolute Living, Prophaneneſs, and Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>— And whereas ſeveral Wicked and Prophane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have preſumed to Print and Publiſh ſeveral <hi>Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Books</hi> and Pamphlets, which contain in them <hi>Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Doctrines againſt the Holy Trinity, and other Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Articles of our Faith, tending to the Subverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Chriſtian Religion: Therefore for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Authors and Publiſhers thereof, and for the preventing ſuch <hi>Impious Books</hi> and Pamphlets being
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61238:65"/> Publiſhed and Printed for the future, we do hereby ſtrictly Charge and Prohibit all Perſons, that they do not preſume to Write, Print, or Publiſh any ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Books or Pamphlets, under the Pain of our High Diſpleaſure, and of being Puniſhed according to the uttermoſt Severity of the Law: And We do hereby ſtrictly Charge and Require all Our Loving Subjects to Diſcover and Apprehend ſuch Perſon or Perſons whom they ſhall Know to be the Authors or Publiſhers of any ſuch Books or Pamphlets, and to bring them before ſome Juſtice of Peace, or Chief Magiſtrate, in order that they may be proceeded againſt according to Law.</p>
                           <closer>God ſave the KING.</closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>For theſe and the like Reaſons, the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> Clergy did Accept the Quakers Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, did meet them at the time perfixed; and there did endeavour to ſhew them their Errors, and would have convinced them thereof, and then had them Retracted their Errors; and thereby to have merited the Indulgence of the Government, and the Love of their Chriſtian Neighbours. But they refuſing all this Labour of Love and Good Will; boaſting they were Proteſtants, and ſo Recognized; and with all boldneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all their Endeavours of Conviction; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Gentry in <hi>Norfolk</hi> (ſome of which were there) and many Juſtices of the Peace, and others; Signed a Petition (as they alſo in the County of <hi>Suffolk</hi> have done) waiting a ſeaſonable Opportunity to preſent the ſame. A Copy thereof, excepting Names, is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
                        <body>
                           <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61238:66"/>
                           <head>To the Honourable the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament Aſſembled; the Humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Juſtices of the Peace, and Grand-Juries of the ſaid County of <hi>Norfolk</hi> in Seſſion Aſſembled; in behalf of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Body of this County at large.</head>
                           <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                           <p>THAT We cannot without Reſentment take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Growth and Daily Increaſe of a Sect of People among Us, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the Miſchiefs and Dangers from thence threatning this Nation.</p>
                           <p>It is too obſervable with what reſtleſs Zeal their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding Teachers, and (as may well be ſuſpected) many Romiſh Emiſſaries under their Vizar and Diſguiſe, daily ramble into all parts of theſe Kingdoms, and boldly ſpread their Venemous Doctrine every where, attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Infect and Shock the Minds of Weak and Unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proteſtants, and Aſſuming to themſelves Rules of Diſcipline, Powers in Matters of Religion, and Forms of Government, repugnant to the Eſtabliſhed Laws of the Kingdom, contrary to the very Acts of Toleration and not allowed to any other Diſſenters, vouching in all their Practices Divine Inſpiration for their Warrant, and their Indulgence of the Government for their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity.</p>
                           <p>How apparently their Blaſphemous Books and Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Principles tend to ſubvert the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity, and the undermining the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are ſufficiently demonſtrable. The Publiſhing whereof by pretended Permiſſion of Authority We hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive to be of moſt dangerous Conſequence.</p>
                           <p>We therefore obliged in Duty to God and Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, do humbly pray, That you will vouchſafe to take theſe Matters into your Care and Conſideration, that (with whatever Tenderneſs to the Perſons and Eſtates of theſe People) their ſaid Principles and Practices may be ſtrictly Examined, and Cenſured, or Suppreſſed, as they ſhall appear to deſerve, and as in your great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61238:66"/> ſhall ſeem expedient; and that our true Chriſtian Religion (more dear to us than our Lives) may be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and Preſerved to all Poſterity, free from Popiſh Superſtition, and unpolluted with Enthuſiaſtical Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>Thus have I recited the Petition, and that for theſe Reaſons following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is nothing but what is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Mind and Pleaſure of the King's Majeſty, and his Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and thereby no Diſhonour to the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Becauſe that when the Petition is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, every Member may have one of them in his Cuſtody to Conſider of it; and the Reaſon that put them upon ſo doing.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Becauſe there are more Petitions of the ſame Nature prepared, and preparing, as this find Acceptance; when a convenient oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity offer it ſelf.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To let the World ſee how reaſonable a thing it is; and not ſuch a monſtrous thing as the Quakers have repreſented it, even to raiſe up the <hi>Monſter Perſecution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Becauſe it is nothing but what they conceive to be their Duty to God and their Country, to acquaint that great Aſſembly, with the Grievances of the County; and that as the moſt proper place for a Remedy.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And Laſtly, that the Contents are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Laws of the Land; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the very Act of Tolleration: And to manifeſt the ſame, I may recite a Branch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:61238:67"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Provided alway, and be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid; that neither this Act, nor any Clauſe, Article, or Thing herein contained, ſhall extend, or be conſtrued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to give any Eaſe, Benefit or Advantage to any Papiſt, or Popiſh Recuſant what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; or that any Perſon that ſhall deny in his Preaching or Writing the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the aforeſaid Article of Religion.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <p>I have likewiſe Diſcourſed with ſome of the moſt Eminent of the Proteſtant Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and with their own Mouths they have declared that they are ſorrowfully affected to think that the Quakers ſhould be joined with them in the Act of Toleration; and to ſee Chriſtianity ſuffer ſo deeply by their Antiſcriptural Doctrine: And not only ſo, but I have a Teſtimony well Atteſted of their Abhorrence of their Blaſphemous Tenets. The ſubſtance of which is as follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>THat the <hi>Quakers</hi> render the Holy Scripture to be of no more Authority than <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fables: That the Blood of Chriſt is no better than the Blood of another Saint: That the <hi>Quakers</hi> are the Spawn of the Ranters: That the <hi>Quakers</hi> owning Chriſt is no other than a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Romance: The the Tendency of all the <hi>Quakers</hi> Reaſoning about Inſtituted Religion is to Debauch Mankind *: that their Principles improved are deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to all Humane Society: That their Teachers are Cheats and Impoſtors, and Implacable Enemies to the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61238:67"/>
                     <p>Here then is the unanimous Conſent of all ſound Proteſtants, the King's Majeſty, and his Honourable Houſe of Commons, and the Laws of the Land. What remains now, but Examination, and for that too we have ſome Encouragement from the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves, if they mean as they ſay. See <hi>An Apology for the</hi> Quakers, <hi>by</hi> J. Feild, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 7. <hi>Examine</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Doctrine of your Neighbours the</hi> Quakers, <hi>blame not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſt examined the matter; firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and then rebuke,</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>George Whitehead</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, in his Book, <hi>Truth and Innocency vindicated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>Let our Books</hi> (ſays <hi>George) be compared, to evince them more fully, and clear our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Now whereas the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves (if they be ſincere in what they ſay) ſeem to be willing to have their Books, and the Doctrine contained in them, come under Examination, in order to be cleared from the Objections againſt them; and as this is highly reaſonable on their parts, ſo it will (I humbly conceive) be a means to put a ſtop to the Gangrene of <hi>Quakeriſm;</hi> (as alſo anſwer the Requeſt of many Thouſands, who are earneſtly ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to have their Books Examined, and their Errours Cenſured, who yet are not for Perſecution, nor any Alteration in the Act of Toleration;) ſo is it alſo a Method purſuant to their own Terms and Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and with which they cannot reaſonably be offended.</p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61238:68"/>
                     <p>And thereupon I do moſt humbly pray, That our Superiours (if it may ſeem good in their ſight, in Anſwer to the <hi>Quakers</hi> Requeſt, and the Peoples Prayer) would appoint, ſome Judicious Learned Men to give us an Equal Hearing, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books an Impartial Examination: And if I do not make a full Proof of what I Charge them with, let me ſuffer any Puniſhment (for my Default) which our Government ſhall think fit. But then on the other hand, if I do make good my Charge, (as an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to my Suffering, in caſe I do not) let the <hi>Quakers</hi> be obliged to Retract and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ſuch Books of theirs as do contain ſuch Impious Doctrines, as I have, or yet ſhall both Charge and Prove: And this is all I deſire, and which I believe would be a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Satisfaction to the Nation, as well as for the Good of the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves.</p>
                     <p>But remembring a Saying of <hi>Feſtus</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Governour, tho' in a contrary Caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.27. <hi>For it ſeemeth a thing unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to ſend a Priſoner, and not withal to ſignifie the Crimes laid againſt him.</hi> And ſo it ſeems to be unreaſonable in me, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Examination of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books, and not ſignifie the Errours (at leaſt ſome of them) contained in them; and eſpecially, ſince it is at the <hi>Quakers</hi> earneſt Requeſt: For ſay they in their Book, <hi>A Defence of an Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>Pray let</hi> Francis Bugg <hi>make it appear to the King, and both
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61238:68"/> Houſes of Parliament, that (our Shuffle at</hi> Weſt-Dereham <hi>in</hi> Norfolk) <hi>put the Gentry, Clergy, and Proteſtant Diſſenters, upon their Petition to the Houſe of Commons; and that they are unanimous therein. — And let him</hi> (Francis Bugg) <hi>tell, if he can, what he means by that Common Chriſtianity, which the</hi> Quakers <hi>Principles are ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As to the firſt, that is, That the Juſtices of Peace, the Gentry, the Clergy, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters are unanimous herein, I have already ſhewed: And as to the ſecond Part, that is, what I mean by that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtianity, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are ſodeſtructive to, I ſhall at his viz. <hi>J. Feild</hi>'s, Prayer and Requeſt, ſhew in the next place. For wherein I can find his Prayers and Requeſt reaſonable, I hope I ſhall be ready to gratifie him. For I believe with the Gentry, the Juſtices, the Clergy, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, and all other Chriſtians, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who was Born at <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem</hi> of <hi>Judea,</hi> of the B. Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was the Son of God, that he was Crucified, Dead and Buried, that he Roſe again the third Day, and Aſcended into Heaven, and there ſits at the Right Hand of God, making Interceſſion for us Sinners, who lay hold on him by Faith, and live in Obedience to him, his Laws, Inſtitutions and Precepts in the Goſpel, left upon Record by the Four Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:61238:69"/> and others of his Apoſtles, in their Epiſtles: And that we ought to Worſhip and Adore him, together with God the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, Three Perſons and One God, in the Unity of his Eſſence. This is the Trinity in Unity, of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which is One God, bleſſed for evermore: And this is that Common Chriſtianity which I mean, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> Principles are ſo deſtructive to. Now the next thing I am to tell at the Prayer and Requeſt of <hi>John Feild,</hi> is, Wherein and whereby their Principles are Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">I. The <hi>Quakers</hi> deny <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> who was Born of the Virgin, and Suffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be the Son of God.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. That they account him only a Vail, a Garment, an outward Veſſel; and can (as their Books teach) never call him Chriſt, and that his Blood was no better than the Blood of another Saint.</p>
                     <p n="3">III. They teach, that their Sufferings are greater, and more unjuſt, than the Sufferings of Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs, in all Ages ſince. For that (as they teach) the Sufferings of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Army of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, were inflicted by a Law, and in great part by the <hi>due</hi> Execution of a Law.</p>
                     <p n="4">IV. That ſuch are Falſe Miniſters, who bid People believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as he is in Heaven above, at God's Right Hand; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61238:69"/> that by Preaching Chriſt in Heaven, the Devil gets his Work done on Earth.</p>
                     <p n="5">V. They teach, That G. <hi>Fox</hi> was their great Apoſtle, which ſaid thus of himſelf; <hi>I am the Light of the World, him by whom the World was made, and doth inlighten every Man that cometh into the World.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">VI. They teach, That the Name Jeſus and Chriſt belongs to every Believer, as well as to the Head Chriſt, that Suffered, Died, Roſe again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">VII. And thereupon they teach, <hi>That</hi> he that, hath the ſame Spirit that raiſed Jeſus from the Dead, is equal with God.</p>
                     <p n="8">VIII. And in coherence with this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine their Prophet <hi>Sol. Eccles</hi> taught, That <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> was a Prophet indeed: And that as it was ſaid of Chriſt, He was in the World, and the World was made by him; and the World knew him not: <hi>So</hi> it might be ſaid of G. <hi>Fox,</hi> as in the 5th Inſtance.</p>
                     <p n="11">XI. They teach, That G. <hi>Fox</hi> was the Father of many Nations; that his Being and Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was in the Power of the higheſt, that he Ruled and Governed in Righteouſneſs; that his Kingdom is eſtabliſhed in Peace; and that of the Increaſe thereof there was never to be an End.</p>
                     <p n="10">X. They teach, That the Holy Scriptures are not the written Word of God; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe, that they are Duſt, Death, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Meat, Beaſtly Ware; but that their own Writings are the Word of God, given
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61238:70"/> forth by Divine Iuſpiration, and that they, as ſuch, are of greater Authority than the Bible; and thereupon read them in their Meetings for Divine Worſhip, whilſt they never read in any ſuch Meeting this Fifty Year, one Chapter of the Bible, either in the Old or New Teſtament: For they teach, They are not the means to work Faith in the Heart, but are a Rotten Foundation.</p>
                     <p n="11">XI. They teach, That Circumciſion is as much in force as Water-Baptiſm; and the Paſchal Lamb as Bread and Wine; and their diſuſe of theſe two Ordinances for this Fifty Years, ſhew that they reject them, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not of them.</p>
                     <p n="12">XII. And touching the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, they are ſo far from owning it, as that they Damn them to the Pit of Hell; as in <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s Book <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> &amp;c. herein Reprinted, may he ſeen.</p>
                     <p>Now, <hi>John,</hi> I having Replied to your Book, <hi>A Defence of an Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> to the principal parts of it; and ſhewed your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies, and ſhallow Subterfuges, as well as in ſome places anſwered your Requeſt; I reſt, deſiring that your ſelf and your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may Conſider of it: Repent of your Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Retract and Condemn the ſame, and Pray to God, and the Nation, to forgive you; in which I ſhall join with you, [And in this you will have no cauſe to cry out of Perſecution] who am your Friend,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Fran. Bugg.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="petition">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:61238:70"/>
                     <head>An Humble Addreſs to His Majeſty King <hi>WILLIAM III.</hi> over <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> by one of the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt yet most Dutiful Subject <hi>FRANCIS BUGG.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe your Moſt Excellent Majeſty,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Cannot but with great Joy and Comfort Remember your Majeſties Repeated Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances given to your Loving Subjects, of your Majeſties Care and Chriſtian Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, as by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in this Kingdom, by your many and repeated Speeches to your Parliaments; and particularly by your late Gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, conſiſting of two Parts: In which your Majeſties Pious Zeal has been abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly manifeſt, Firſt, Againſt Vice and Prophaneneſs; and, Secondly, Againſt ſuch Books as contain in them Impious, Doctrine againſt the Holy Trinity, and other Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith; and therein have given Encouragement to all your Loving Subjects to diſcover the Authors of ſuch Books.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore in Obedience to your Majeſties Royal Command, as well as my Duty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to God, I have herein Reprinted one of the Quakers Books, of which <hi>Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> is one of the Authors, to the intent that your Sacred Majeſty, and the whole
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61238:71"/> Kingdom may be preſented with a Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Quakers Doctrine. And do moſt Humbly Pray in the Name of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other your Majeſties Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Proteſtants, that ſuch Care may be taken to ſuppreſs the ſame, (with others of their Books of the ſame Narure) as to your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Wiſdom ſhall ſeem meet. And as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God Almighty to give King <hi>Solomon</hi> Wiſdom to Execute Juſtice; ſo will he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the King with an Underſtanding Heart to Judge who is in the wrong, and to Puniſh accordingly: And in this caſe let not the King Reſpect Perſons in Judgment, but if I be not able to maintain my Charge, then let me bear his Majeſties Diſpleaſure, and ſuffer what Puniſhment ſhall be due for the ſame: But if I do make good my Charge, then do as ſeems good in your Eye. Thus, with all Dutiful Submiſſion, do I Sign this my Humble Addreſs, this 13th Day of <hi>December</hi> 1699.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Francis Bugg.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="bibliography">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:71"/>
                  <head>A Catalogue of Books wrote by <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>DE Chriſtiana Libertate,</hi> &amp;c. in 8<hi>vo.</hi> bound.</item>
                     <item>2. The Painted Harlot ſtript and whipt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Reaſon againſt Railing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Innocency Vindicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi> never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>5. The Quakers Detected, and their Errors Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp;c. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. A Letter to the Quakers, ſhewing their frequent Addreſſes to, and Prayers for the late King <hi>Jam.</hi> II. and not to King <hi>Will.</hi> III.</item>
                     <item>7. Battering Rams againſt <hi>New Rome,</hi> &amp;c. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. One blow more at <hi>New Rome,</hi> &amp;c. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. <hi>New Rome</hi> Unmask'd, and her Foundation Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10. <hi>New Rome</hi> Arraigned, and out of her own Mouth Condemned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. A Sheet Preſented to the Parliament, 1693. in Anſwer to the Quakers Allegations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>12. Quakeriſm Withering, and Chriſtianity Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>13. Quakeriſm Anatomized, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi> never An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</item>
                     <item>14. The Quakers Yearly Meeting impeached on the behalf of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>15. The Quakers ſet in their true Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Houſe of Lords, 1696. never anſwered.</item>
                     <item>16. A Brief Reply to the Quakers Ancient Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, preſented to the Lord's Houſe, 1696. never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>17. A Brief Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of Quakeriſm, 8<hi>vo.</hi> never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>18. The Picture of Quakeriſm drawn to the Life, 8<hi>vo.</hi> never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>19. A Sober Expoſtulation with their Hearers touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Mercenary Teachers, never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>20. The Pilgrim's Progreſs from Quakeriſm to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed in 4<hi>to.</hi> and Reprinted in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>21. Seventy Queries to ſeveral Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> never Anſwered.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:61238:72"/>
                     <item>22. A Broad Sheet with a Scheme of the Quakers Synod, preſented to the Parliament, 1699.</item>
                     <item>23. <hi>Jezebel</hi> withſtood, and her Daughter, <hi>Anne Dowcra</hi> publickly Reproved, never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>24. Quakeriſm Expoſed to Publick Cenſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>25. The Chriſtian Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> vindicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi> never Anſwered.</item>
                     <item>26. A Defence of my Book Quakeriſm Expoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Beſides three Books I wrote part of.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>27. <hi>Will. Rogers</hi> his Seventh Part of the Chriſtian Quaker diſtinguiſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> about 1682.</item>
                     <item>28. A Looking Glaſs for the Quakers, in 2 Columns.</item>
                     <item>29. A Poſtſcript to the <hi>Norfolk</hi> Clergies Book, <hi>i. e.</hi> A Brief Diſcovery ſome of of the Quakers Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and Seditious Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                  <p>IF any Perſon be deſirous to have this Book and my former Books, Bound, either them in <hi>Quarto</hi> or them in <hi>Ostavo,</hi> or Single, ſticht; they may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all (except them of thoſe Impreſſions wholly Sold off) at Mr. <hi>Janeway</hi>'s a Bookbinder in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, next Door to <hi>Child</hi>'s Coffee-Houſe, <hi>London.</hi> And,</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, if any Abler Men (for of ſuch there is very great need) be diſpoſed farther to unmask the Leaders of this Hereſie; this is to give notice, that in the Library of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> there is, by a Worthy Gentleman, a Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> bought of me, and given by him for the Service of the Church, of Quakers Books, wrote by the moſt approved Authors of that Sect, which I think are thus Chained up (from doing any more hurt). Firſt, <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Journal;</hi> next to it <hi>Muggleton</hi>'s <hi>Journal</hi> or Works, (containing more than 1000 pages 4<hi>to.</hi>); and I think the beſt Quaker of the two; next to that <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Fol.</hi> with near 20 more of his Books; next the Works of <hi>Edw. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Francis Howgil, Will. Smith, Sam. Fiſher;</hi> all in great <hi>Folio</hi>'s; next the Works of <hi>Joſ. Coal, Step.
<pb facs="tcp:61238:72"/> Smith, R. Hubberthorn, Will. Bayly, Iſ. Pennington, G. Fox,</hi> Junior, in 4<hi>to.</hi> next divers Books wrote by <hi>James Naylor, Will Penn, Chriſt. Atkinſon, G. Whitehead, Sol. Eccles, Tho. Lawſon, Chriſt. Taylor, R. Farnſworth, Geo. Biſhop,</hi> and divers others; in all near the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Four Hundred, bearing diſtinct Titles, which may furniſh any Perſon ſufficiently with Matter of Fact.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>A Parable of an Iſland <hi>Page</hi> 14</item>
                     <item>In which aroſe a Sea Monſter <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Who ſtung many of the Inhabitants <hi>ibid</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Phyſicians ſeveral Applications <hi>Page</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>The Quakers Ingratitude <hi>Page</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>The Wounded Peoples Ingratitude <hi>Page</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example a good Preſident <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anne Docwra</hi>'s witneſs touching the Quakers <hi>Page</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>R. Sandylan</hi>'s Letter of Retraction <hi>Page</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will. Mucklow</hi>'s witneſs is true <hi>Page</hi> 21</item>
                     <item>Their Singuler way of Anſwering Books <hi>Page</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Their Sufferings greater and more unjuſt than the Sufferings of Chriſt or his Apoſtles <hi>Page</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>They deny Jeſus to be the Son of God <hi>Page</hi> 26</item>
                     <item>The Author's Apology for his proceedings <hi>Page</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>Prayers for their Recovery <hi>Page</hi> 28</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Part the Firſt.</head>
                     <item>Their Contradictory Books hinted at <hi>Page</hi> 2</item>
                     <item>How the Quakers and Papiſts agree <hi>Page</hi> 4</item>
                     <item>About chuſing of Parliaments <hi>Page</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>Their Sentence of all Kings <hi>Page</hi> 14</item>
                     <item>Of their denying the Bleſſed Trinity <hi>Page</hi> 17, 30</item>
                     <item>Of their Light within being God <hi>Page</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>The Quakers began this Conteſt <hi>Page</hi> 23</item>
                     <item>Of <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s owning his <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> his ſhuffle about it ſince <hi>Page</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>His Blaſphemy therein hinted at <hi>Page</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Counſel given him, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21, 22, 23. <hi>Page</hi> 32</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>The Second Part</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s Book <hi>Iſhmael</hi> Reprinted <hi>Page</hi> 1</item>
                     <item>The cauſe of the Quakers Rage diſcovered <hi>Page</hi> 2</item>
                     <item>They deny the Scriptures to be the Word <hi>Page</hi> 4</item>
                     <item>They alſo deny the Scriptures to be the Rule <hi>Page</hi> 10</item>
                     <item>Saying they are a Rotten Foundation <hi>Page</hi> 14</item>
                     <item>That they are Death, and killeth <hi>Page</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>That they do not work Faith <hi>Page</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>And to them not neceſſary <hi>Page</hi> 29</item>
                     <item>As a conſequence thereof they Damn the B. Trinity to the Pit, and Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi> the Miniſter alſo. <hi>Page</hi> 22, 26</item>
                     <item>The Snake deciphered <hi>Page</hi> 27</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joſ. Wyeth</hi> wounded and unarmed <hi>Page</hi> 28</item>
                     <item>The Snakes Hiſs like Serpents <hi>Page</hi> 29</item>
                     <item>Another ſtroke at the Rattle-Snake <hi>Page</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s Blaſphemy explained <hi>Page</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>She not changed in Principles proved. <hi>Page</hi> 32</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Part the Third.</head>
                     <item>A Caution to beware of Quakeriſm <hi>Page</hi> 2</item>
                     <item>The Quakers the Off-ſpring of the Jeſuites <hi>Page</hi> 3</item>
                     <item>Their Anſwer to Books horribly falacious <hi>Page</hi> 5</item>
                     <item>Of their diminitive Sufferings <hi>Page</hi> 7</item>
                     <item>Their Sufferings and Miracles jointly conſidered <hi>Page</hi> 8</item>
                     <item>Twelve Reaſons to confront <hi>J. Feild</hi>'s magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sufferings <hi>Page</hi> 9</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Field</hi> does not ſay <hi>F. B.</hi> is like <hi>Judas Page</hi> 13</item>
                     <item>His Hypocriſie therein diſcovered <hi>Page</hi> 17</item>
                     <item>Their not Praying for <hi>K. W.</hi> III. <hi>Page</hi> 15</item>
                     <item>The Quakers greateſt Perſecutors <hi>Page</hi> 16</item>
                     <item>Their Diſſimulation thereabout diſcovered <hi>Page</hi> 18</item>
                     <item>Quakers fling at Diſſenting Proteſtants <hi>Page</hi> 19</item>
                     <item>The Quakers againſt Liberty of Conſcience <hi>Page</hi> 20</item>
                     <item>At firſt lay in Barns like Gypſies <hi>Page</hi> 22</item>
                     <item>Their rendring the Government odious for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution further Illuſtrated. <hi>Page</hi> 24</item>
                     <item>An Addreſs from the Honourable Houſe of Commons to His Majeſty, and his Anſwer <hi>Page</hi> 30</item>
                     <item>Their Printed Paper to the Parliament <hi>Page</hi> 31</item>
                     <item>Their Paper to his Majeſty <hi>Page</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>They debar'dd of Places of Profit <hi>Page</hi> 35</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61238:73"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
